<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="app.bidi">
  <title id="app.bidi.title">Directional Formatting Characters</title>

  <para>Bidi control characters are available from <link
  linkend="menus.edit" endterm="menus.edit.title"/><link
  linkend="menus.edit.insert.unicode.control.character"
  endterm="menus.edit.insert.unicode.control.character.title"/>. They can be used
  to:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Insert an invisible character with a strong directionality
	  to force a specific position for a character with weak or neutral
	  directionality.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Create a section of text that flows in the
	  direction opposite that of the segment.</para>
	</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>These control characters change directionality but are invisible.
  Use <link linkend="menus.view" endterm="menus.view.title"/><link
  linkend="menus.view.mark.bidirectional.algorithm.control.character"
  endterm="menus.view.mark.bidirectional.algorithm.control.character.title"/> to
  show a visual indication of their position.</para>

  <section id="app.bidi.marks">
	<title id="app.bidi.marks.title">Marks</title>

	<para>To change the position of a character with weak or neutral
	directionality (like punctuation symbols), insert an LRM or RLM character
	after the character, depending on the directionality of the segment:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<para>Insert a LRM after a weak-directionality character that must run
		left-to-right in a right-to-left segment (e.g. an English excerpt inside
		Arabic text).</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para>Insert a RLM after a weak-directionality character that must run
		right-to-left in a left-to-right segment (e.g. an Arabic excerpt inside
		English text).</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="app.bidi.embeddings">
	<title id="app.bidi.embeddings.title">Embeddings</title>

	<para>Embeddings can be used to create a longer section of text (containing
	several words and spaces) that must flow in the direction opposite that of
	the segment. You can create two kinds of embeddings depending on the
	directionality of the segment:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<para>To create a left-to-right embedding in a right-to-left segment,
		insert a left-to-right embedding (LRE) character, type or insert the
		left-to-right text, and then insert the pop directional formatting (PDF)
		character.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para>To create a
  right-to-left embedding in a left-to-right segment, insert a
  right-to-left embedding (RLE) character, type or insert the right-to-left
		text, and then insert the PDF character.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
