<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % manualvariables SYSTEM "manualvariables.mod">
%manualvariables;
]>
<section id="how.to.installing.omegat">
  <title id="how.to.installing.omegat.title">Install
  OmegaT</title>

  <para>OmegaT comes in two editions:</para>

  <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Standard: OmegaT &vernb;</term>
	  <listitem>
		<para>This edition is recommended for everyday use.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Developer: OmegaT Weekly</term>
	  <listitem>
		<para>This is the edition of OmegaT in active development. It is automatically generated every week,
			and serves as a beta version for testing purposes.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>The files are downloadable directly from <ulink
  url="https://omegat.org/download">https://omegat.org</ulink>.</para>

  <note>
	<para>OmegaT &vernb; requires a &javaversionlong; (JRE) to run.</para>

	<para>OmegaT packages are available both in versions bundled with Java, and
	versions without it. Packages without Java rely on a &javaversionlong;
	installed systemwide.</para>

	<para>OmegaT 6.1.0 and later can also run with a Java 17 Runtime Environment
	on any platform.</para>

	<para>Due to licensing considerations, the OmegaT team recommends the Eclipse
	Temurin Java runtime provided by the &preferedopenjdk;, but any Java 11 compatible runtime environment should work.
		See <ulink
	url="https://projects.eclipse.org/projects/adoptium.temurin">The Eclipse
	Temurin™ project</ulink>.</para>

	<para>IBM provides JREs for Linux PowerPC at <ulink
	url="https://developer.ibm.com/languages/java/semeru-runtimes/downloads/"/>.</para>
  </note>

  <section id="installing.omegat.windows">
    <title id="installing.omegat.windows.title">On Windows</title>

    <para>Double-click on the package you downloaded.</para>

    <para>You can choose the language used during the installation and the
    language used by OmegaT. You can also change this later by editing the
    <filename>OmegaT.l4J.ini</filename> file.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installing.omegat.linux.intel">
    <title id="installing.omegat.linux.intel.title">On Linux</title>

	<para>Some Linux distributions offer OmegaT in their package manager. The
	instructions given here apply to people who download the package from the
	<ulink url="https://omegat.org/download">https://omegat.org</ulink>
	site and install it manually.</para>


    <para>Unpack/untar the file you downloaded. This creates a new
    folder named after the package you downloaded. That folder contains
    all the files needed to run OmegaT.</para>

    <note>
	  <para>Although you can run OmegaT directly from the available files, you
	  can also run the <filename>linux-install.sh</filename> script found there
	  to have OmegaT installed in more appropriate locations.</para>

      <para>Running the script will require you to enter your
      <filename>sudo</filename> password.</para>

      <para>The script checks for an existing installation of the same OmegaT
      version in <filename>/opt/omegat/</filename>. If there isn’t one, it
      installs the program in <filename>/opt/omegat/OmegaT_&vernb;</filename>
      and sets it as the default version (in
      <filename>/opt/omegat/OmegaT-default</filename>).</para>
	</note>

    <para>After the unpacking or installation is complete, you can delete the
    downloaded file as it is no longer needed.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Installing.omegat.macos">
    <title id="Installing.omegat.macos.title">On macOS</title>

    <para>Double click on the package you downloaded to unpack it.  This creates
    a folder called <filename>OmegaT</filename>. The folder contains two files:
    <filename>index.html</filename> (the user manual entry file) and
    <filename>OmegaT.app</filename> (the application). Copy the folder to a
    suitable location (e.g.  <filename>Applications</filename>).</para>

    <para>If so desired, drag and drop <filename>OmegaT.app</filename> onto the
    Dock for easier access.</para>

	<para>Once you have done this, you can delete the downloaded package as it
	is no longer needed.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="installing.omegat.other.systems">
    <title id="installing.omegat.other.systems.title">On other platforms</title>

    <para>This information applies to any system for a Java version
    compatible with &javaversionlong; is available. That includes the platforms
		described above, as well as platforms for which no specific OmegaT package
		is provided.</para>

    <para>Download the <emphasis>Cross-platform without JRE</emphasis>
    version.</para>

    <para>Unpack the file that you downloaded. This creates a folder with all
    the files necessary to run OmegaT.</para>

    <para>Follow your system’s instructions to install OmegaT shortcuts in
    convenient places of your choosing.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="update.and.delete.omegat">
	<title id="update.and.delete.omegat.title">Upgrade</title>

	<para>OmegaT can tell you when a new version is available. See the <link
	endterm="dialogs.preferences.updates.title"
	linkend="dialogs.preferences.updates"/> preference for details.</para>

	<para>The changes between your version and the current version are
	documented in the development site’s <ulink
	url="https://sourceforge.net/p/omegat/code/ci/master/tree/release/changes.txt">changes.txt</ulink>
	file.</para>

	<note>
	  <para>If you decide to install a new version, keep the following in
	  mind:</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>OmegaT’s preferences are stored in the configuration folder and
		  will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be modified by the new version.  See the
		  <link endterm="configuration.folder.title"
		  linkend="configuration.folder"/> chapter for details.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>Projects that you have created in the past or are currently
		  using will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be modified or deleted. OmegaT
		  projects are <emphasis>not</emphasis> stored inside OmegaT. They are
		  separate objects that have no physical connection to the OmegaT
		  application itself.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>Parameter files that are included in the downloaded OmegaT
		  package (especially the <filename>OmegaT.l4J.ini</filename> for
		  <link linkend="running.omegat.on.windows">Windows</link> and the
		  <filename>Configuration.properties</filename> and
		  <filename>Info.plist</filename> files for <link
		  linkend="running.omegat.on.macos">macOS</link> packages) might be
			overwritten or deleted, so you may want to create a backup before
			upgrading, if you have been using these files to modify OmegaT’s
			launch parameters.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>The <filename>plugins</filename> and
		  <filename>scripts</filename> folders might be overwritten, so you
		  may want to create a backup before upgrading.</para>
		</listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</note>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry id="update.and.delete.omegat.over.existing.package">
		<term id="update.and.delete.omegat.over.existing.package.title">Over an existing version</term>

		<listitem>
		  <para>To do this, simply select the same installation folder as the
		  existing installation when installing the new version. The “old”
		  version of OmegaT will be overwritten, but settings made from the
		  OmegaT interface will be retained in the various configurations
		  folders (see above).</para>
		</listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  
	<varlistentry id="update.and.delete.omegat.along.existing.package">
	  <term  id="update.and.delete.omegat.along.existing.package.title">Alongside an existing version</term>

	  <listitem>
		<para>This will enable you to keep any number of versions side-by-side,
		which you may wish to do until you feel comfortable with the new
		version.</para>

	  <para>All the parameters located in the OmegaT configuration folder will
	  be shared unless you specify a different configuration folder with the
	  <literal>--config-dir=&lt;path&gt;</literal> option on the command
	  line. See the <link
	  endterm="launch.with.command.line.omegat.options.title"
	  linkend="launch.with.command.line.omegat.options"/> section.</para>

	  <para>All the parameters located in a <link
	  linkend="chapter.project.folder">project folder</link> will apply to that
	  project regardless of which version of OmegaT opens it.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
  </section>
  
	<section id="update.and.delete.omegat.delete">
	  <title id="update.and.delete.omegat.delete.title">Delete OmegaT</title>

	  <para>Use your operating system’s standard procedure to remove OmegaT.  If
	  you want to remove OmegaT completely, you will also have to delete the
	  configuration folder.</para>

	  <para>If you performed a manual installation on Linux, you will have to
	  manually delete the OmegaT folders in <filename>opt/</filename>, as well
	  as the symlinks placed in <filename>/usr/local/bin/</filename> by the
	  installation script.</para>
	</section>

  <section id="build.omegat.from.source">
	<title id="build.omegat.from.source.title">Build OmegaT</title>

	<para>The source code for the current version can either be downloaded
	directly from the OmegaT <ulink url="https://omegat.org/download">download
	page</ulink>, or cloned from the <ulink
	url="https://git.code.sf.net/p/omegat/code">Sourceforge</ulink> or <ulink
	url="https://github.com/omegat-org/omegat.git">GitHub</ulink>
	repositories.</para>
	<para>Once the code is downloaded, open a terminal in the source folder
	(<filename>omegat-code/</filename> if you cloned from Sourceforge, or
	<filename>/omegat</filename> if you cloned from GitHub) and type:</para>

	<programlisting>./gradlew installDist</programlisting>

	<para>This will create a full, ready to launch distribution of OmegaT in the
	<filename>build/install/OmegaT</filename> folder.</para>

	<para>You can also run the application directly with the following
	command:</para>

	<programlisting>./gradlew run</programlisting>

	<para>You can get a list of all available tasks by typing:</para>

	<programlisting>./gradlew tasks</programlisting>

	<para>Detailed instructions on building OmegaT can be found in the  <ulink
	url="https://sourceforge.net/p/omegat/svn/HEAD/tree/trunk/docs_devel/README.txt">README.txt</ulink>
	file located in the <filename class="directory">docs_devel</filename> subfolder.</para>
  </section>
</section>
