<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="how.to.use.team.project">
   <title xml:id="how.to.use.team.project.title">Use a team project</title>
   <para>Team projects use synchronization mechanisms between project members.</para>
   <para>Once an OmegaT team project has been set up on a server, the project
      manager sends members the information they need to access it. This can be a URL
      giving the location of the project, or an 
      <filename>omegat.project</filename>
      file.</para>
   <para>Downloading the project creates a copy on the translator's computer
      that only needs to be opened locally to synchronize with the server.</para>
   <para>Repository credentials are stored in the 
      <link linkend="configuration.folder.extra.contents.repositories" endterm="configuration.folder.extra.contents.repositories.title"></link> file and
      can be deleted from the 
      <link linkend="dialog.preferences.team.title.repository.credentials" endterm="dialog.preferences.team.title.repository.credentials.title"></link>
      preferences.</para>
   <para>Since synchronization takes place every three minutes by default, 
      one project member may translate or modify a segment that has already
      been translated by another member, but not yet synchronized. When that happens,
      members have to select the appropriate translation.</para>
   <para>Members can take turns translating and reviewing the files. The Search
      function offers a number of useful options to filter the content of the files.
      For example, members can have the Editor pane show translations made by a
      given person, or contents translated before or after a given time, or combinations
      thereof.</para>
   <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
         <term>Downloading the project</term>
         <listitem>
            <orderedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>From a URL</para>
                  <para>Use 
                     <link endterm="menus.project.title" linkend="menus.project"></link>
                     <link endterm="menus.project.download.team.project.title" linkend="menus.project.download.team.project"></link> to bring up the
                     			
                     <guilabel>Download Team Project</guilabel> dialog.</para>
                  <para>Enter the URL provided by the project manager in the
                     			
                     <guilabel>Repository URL:</guilabel> field at the top of the dialog,
                     			and specify a folder for the project in the 
                     <guilabel>New Local
                        			Project Folder:</guilabel> field. Leave the 
                     <guilabel>Default
                        			branch</guilabel> option checked unless the project manager
                     			has provided instructions for using a custom branch.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>From an 
                     <filename>omegat.project</filename> file</para>
                  <para>Put the 
                     <filename>omegat.project</filename> file in an empty
                     			folder, and open it in OmegaT. The project will automatically be
                     			downloaded to the folder containing that file.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <note>
               <para>Servers generally use two main types of authentication: entering
                  		  a 
                  <emphasis>username/password</emphasis>, or
                  		  
                  <emphasis>SSH</emphasis>.</para>
               <para>If the server relies on username/password authentication, OmegaT
                  		  will present you with an 
                  <guilabel>Authentication</guilabel> dialog to
                  		  enter your username and password either when you first download the
                  		  project or later on in the process. OmegaT will then remember your
                  		  credentials for that specific project unless you explicitly delete
                  		  them. See the 
                  <link linkend="dialog.preferences.team.title.repository.credentials" endterm="dialog.preferences.team.title.repository.credentials.title"></link>
                  		  preferences for details.</para>
               <para>If the server uses SSH authentication, make sure you update your
                  		  SSH configuration to include that server before attempting to download
                  		  the project, otherwise you will get an authentication error and the
                  		  project will fail to load.</para>
               <para>Some hosting services require you to generate a passphrase
                  or other form of access token in addition to your password.
                  In such cases, enter that passphrase or token when OmegaT asks for
                  your password.</para>
               <para>If you use multiple projects on the same server, you will only be
                  asked to enter your credentials once for that server.</para>
            </note>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term>Synchronization</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Synchronizing the project adds translations made by all team
               members to local copies of the project. Only the contents of the two
               following files are synchronized:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>
                     <filename>project_save.tmx</filename>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>
                     <filename>glossary.txt</filename>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>During synchronization, all other local files are overwritten
               with the versions on the remote server, except for
               
               <filename>omegat.project</filename> (see below).</para>
            <para>OmegaT synchronizes a team project when it is opened, reloaded,
               closed or saved. This means the automatic save function also regularly
               synchronizes local versions with the version on the server at the
               interval specified in the 
               <link endterm="dialog.preferences.saving.and.output.interval.title" linkend="dialog.preferences.saving.and.output.interval"></link>
               preference.</para>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term>Team project configuration</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>As in regular local projects, the configuration of the team
               project is defined by the contents of the 
               <filename>omegat.project</filename>
               file and the optional use of special files for project-specific
               filters or segmentation rules.</para>
            <para>The first time the project is downloaded, OmegaT retrieves the
               
               <filename>omegat.project</filename> file from the server. This file
               defines the following parameters:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>
                     <emphasis>Basic project configuration:</emphasis> Source and
                     languages, tokenizers, and the project folder hierarchy.</para>
                  <para>In a team project, the basic configuration parameters of the
                     			local project are always overridden by the configuration on the
                     			server originally set by the project manager.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>
                     <emphasis>Repository mappings</emphasis>
                  </para>
                  <para>See the 
                     <link linkend="how.to.setup.team.project.mapping.parameters" endterm="how.to.setup.team.project.mapping.parameters.title"></link>
                     how-to for details.</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>If no custom mappings have been defined for the remote
                           project, but local mappings have been customized, the local
                           settings are preserved without affecting the settings on the
                           server.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>If the remote project contains custom mappings, but the
                           local project does not, the mappings from the server are applied
                           to the local project.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>If the remote project specifies a URL protocol and you
                           download it using a different protocol, your local configuration
                           will be preserved.</para>
                        <para>For example, many hosting services support access to the
                           same repository using either the SSH +Git or https protocol.
                           OmegaT will respect the local protocol selection.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>If you first download the remote project using an
                           
                           <filename>omegat.project</filename> file provided by the project
                           manager, OmegaT will use the mappings in that file, if
                           any.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>If there is a conflict between the remote and local
                           versions of the 
                           <filename>omegat.project</filename> file and the
                           local version is overwritten, OmegaT creates a backup file
                           called 
                           <filename>omegat.project.YYYYMMDDhhmm.bak</filename>.
                           OmegaT creates up to ten backup files, and older backups
                           are automatically deleted in turn.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <warning>
               <para>Remember that any modifications to local project configuration
                  files will be overwritten by the versions on the server when the
                  project is synchronized.</para>
            </warning>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term>Source files</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>Unless special mappings or 
               <link endterm="how.to.setup.team.project.selective.sharing.title" linkend="how.to.setup.team.project.selective.sharing"></link>,
               have been set up all source files are shared by all team members,
               and any changes made to the local source files are overwritten the
               next time the project is synchronized, unless they are committed
               to the server using the 
               <link endterm="menus.project.title" linkend="menus.project"></link>
               <link endterm="menus.project.commit.source.files.title" linkend="menus.project.commit.source.files"></link> command.</para>
            <warning>
               <para>Since changes to the source files affect 
                  <emphasis role="italic">all</emphasis>
                  members, use that command with caution and only in accordance with the guidelines
                  and
                  workflow established for the project by the project manager.</para>
            </warning>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term>Target files</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>After you generate the target, files use the 
               
               <link endterm="menus.project.title" linkend="menus.project"></link>
               <link endterm="menus.project.commit.target.files.title" linkend="menus.project.commit.target.files"></link> command to add them to the
               server if the project manager has requested you to do so.
               Committing the target files also uploads the statistics files to the server.</para>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term>Deleting files</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>This task normally has to be performed by the project manager, since
               files in a team project are restored the next time the project is synchronized.
               This means users cannot delete from OmegaT or the local file system unless
               the project manager removes them from the server.</para>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term>Working offline</term>
         <listitem>
            <para>You can open a team project and work on it offline. All changes
               will be synchronized the next time a connection is available.</para>
            <para>If there are any conflicts at that time, OmegaT will present a
               dialog to let you choose the correct version.</para>
            <para>There are two ways to work offline:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Disconnect from the network before opening the
                     project.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Open the project from the command line with the
                     
                     <parameter>--no-team</parameter> option. See the 
                     <link linkend="launch.with.command.line" endterm="launch.with.command.line.title"></link> section for
                     details.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
</section>