<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="how.to.translate.other.files">
  <title id="how.to.translate.other.files.title">Support other formats</title>

  <para>OmegaT's file filters provide a wide range of support for common and
  less common file formats. If you need to support formats that are not covered
  by OmegaT, there are four ways to do so:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><link linkend="how.to.translate.other.files.associate">Associate</link> the format to an already supported format.</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  <para><link linkend="how.to.translate.other.files.convert">Convert</link> the format to an already supported format.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><link linkend="how.to.translate.other.files.third.party.plugins">Extend</link> OmegaT with third-party plugins that support the format.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><link linkend="how.to.translate.other.files.develop">Develop</link> a filter for the format.</para>
	</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
	<section id="how.to.translate.other.files.associate">
	  <title id="how.to.translate.other.files.associate.title">Association</title>

	  <para>File filters have a list of file extensions that are associated to
	  them. If the format you want to translate is structurally close to an
	  already supported format, just add its file extension to the supported
	  format extension list, or change the file extension to one that is
	  accepted by the file filter that you want to use. See the <link
	  linkend="file.filters" endterm="file.filters.title"/> chapter for
	  details.</para>
		
	  <para>You can also use OmegaT's custom tag function to register format
	  specific strings and have OmegaT handle them as if they were normal
	  tags. See the <link
	  linkend="dialogs.preferences.tag.processing.regular.expressions.for.custom.tags"
	  endterm="dialogs.preferences.tag.processing.regular.expressions.for.custom.tags.title"/>
	  preferences for details.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="how.to.translate.other.files.convert">
	  <title id="how.to.translate.other.files.convert.title">Conversion</title>

	  <para>To ensure that all the properties of a format are properly taken
	  into account, it is sometimes preferable to convert the file to a
	  supported format and then convert the translated file back to the original
	  format.</para>

	  <para>A number of free software third party utilities provide such
		“round-trip” conversion, including:</para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist id="how.to.translate.other.files.third.party.utilities">
		<listitem id="how.to.translate.other.files.third.party.utilities.rainbow">
		  <para>Rainbow, from the <ulink url="https://okapiframework.org">Okapi
		  Framework</ulink></para>

		  <para>License: Apache License Version 2.0</para>

		  <para>The Okapi Framework comes with a number of file filters,
		  including some not supported natively by OmegaT. See <ulink
		  url="https://okapiframework.org/wiki/index.php?title=Filters">List of
		  file filters</ulink> for details.</para>

		  <para>Rainbow can create XLIFF 1.2 compliant files or OmegaT projects
		  from all the files set as “input” files. Rainbow-supported files are
		  converted into XLIFF and inserted as source files into a full fledged
		  OmegaT project that you can open with OmegaT right away. See <ulink
		  url="https://okapiframework.org/wiki/index.php/Rainbow_TKit_-_OmegaT_Project">Rainbow
		  TKit - OmegaT Project</ulink> for details.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem id="how.to.translate.other.files.third.party.utilities.po4a">
		  <para><ulink url="https://po4a.org">po4a</ulink></para>

		  <para>License: GNU General Public License v2</para>

		  <para>po4a supports a number of free software documentation formats,
		  listed on the site front page, and offers conversion tools to and from
		  the po format. See the <link linkend="file.filters.po"
		  endterm="file.filters.po.title"/> section for details.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>The converters from the <ulink
		  url="http://docs.translatehouse.org/projects/translate-toolkit/en/latest/index.html">Translate
		  Toolkit</ulink></para>

		  <para>License: GNU General Public License v2</para>

		  <para>The Translate Toolkit offers a number of convertion tools to and
		  from the po format. See <ulink
		  url="http://docs.translatehouse.org/projects/translate-toolkit/en/latest/commands/index.html">Converters</ulink>
		  for details.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem id="how.to.translate.other.files.third.party.utilities.openxliff">
		  <para>OpenXLIFF from <ulink
		  url="https://maxprograms.com/">Maxprograms</ulink></para>

		  <para>License:  Eclipse Public License v1.0</para>

		  <para>OpenXLIFF supports a number of file filters, including some
		  not supported natively by OmegaT. See <ulink
		  url="https://maxprograms.com/products/openxliff.html">OpenXLIFF
		  Filters</ulink> for details. Maxprograms also distributes <ulink
		  url="https://maxprograms.com/products/xliffmanager.html">XLIFF
		  Manager</ulink>, a graphical user interface for the OpenXLIFF
		  Filters.</para>

		  <para>OpenXLIFF produces XLIFF 1.2 compliant files.</para>
		</listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
		<para>Some formats, like PDF, cannot be properly handled through “round
		trip” conversions. They require an intermediate conversion to a supported
		format that serves as a base to manually create a proper target language
		document.</para>
		
		<para>You can find a number of online or offline utilities that convert PDF
		to common office formats, but the conversion will always require extensive
		manual adjustments to the target document before a proper PDF document can
		be produced. Make sure you understand the format requirements when you
		start working on a PDF or similar file.</para>
	  </section>

	  <section
		  id="how.to.translate.other.files.third.party.plugins">
		<title
		id="how.to.translate.other.files.third.party.plugins.title">Third-party
		plugins</title>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			<para>The Okapi Filters Plugin for OmegaT, from the <ulink
			url="https://okapiframework.org">Okapi Framework</ulink></para>

			<para>License: Apache License Version 2.0</para>

			<para>Not all of the Okapi Framework file filters are included into
			the file filter plugin. See <ulink
			url="https://okapiframework.org/wiki/index.php/Okapi_Filters_Plugin_for_OmegaT#Filters_Included">Filters
			Included</ulink> for details.</para>

			<para>When installed, the plugin offers direct access to the added
			formats and also allows you to associate a custom filter parameters
			file created in Rainbow. See <link
			linkend="how.to.translate.other.files.third.party.utilities.rainbow">above</link>.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Other plugins for less common formats are listed on the OmegaT
		wiki. See <ulink
		url="https://sourceforge.net/p/omegat/wiki/Plugins/">Plugins</ulink>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="how.to.translate.other.files.develop">
	  <title id="how.to.translate.other.files.develop.title">Development</title>

	  <para>OmegaT provides developers with thorough documentation to create
	  file filter plugins. See <ulink
	  url="https://omegat.readthedocs.io/en/latest/11.HowToCreateFilterPlugin/">How
	  to create a file filter plugin for OmegaT</ulink> for details.</para>
	</section>
  </section>
