<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.instant.start.guide">
  <title>Naučte se používat aplikaci OmegaT za 5 minut!</title>

  <section id="create.and.open.new.project">
    <title>Nastavení nového projektu<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Projekt</primary> <secondary>Vytvořit / otevřít nový</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><remark>Poznámka:</remark> Na počítačích Apple Mac používejte klávesu <keycap>Command</keycap> místo <keycap>Ctrl&lt;/k3&gt;</keycap>.</para>

      <indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Nabídka Projekt</primary> <secondary>Nový...</secondary>
      </indexterm>

    <para>Prvním krokem při používání OmegaT je vytvoření projektu, který bude obsahovat všechny vaše soubory, jako např. zdrojové soubory, překladové paměti, glosáře a nakonec také váš překlad. V nabídce <guimenu>Projekt</guimenu> vyberte položku<menuchoice> <guimenuitem> Nový...</guimenuitem> </menuchoice>&lt;i3/&gt; a zadejte název vašeho projektu. Při vytváření projektu nezapomeňte kam jste ho uložili, protože později se k němu budete potřebovat vracet.</para>

    <para>Po zadání jména projektu se otevře dialogové okno Vytvořit nový projekt. V horní části dialogového okna vyberte jazyk vašich zdrojových souborů a jazyk překladu a pro pokračování klikněte na <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.</para>

    <para>Pokud máte zájem poznat další nastavení tohoto dialogového okna, můžete se k němu vrátit kdykoliv stisknutím <keycap>Ctrl+E.</keycap> </para>

    <para>V dalším kroku se otevře dialogové okno <guilabel>Soubory projektu</guilabel>. Click on <guibutton>Copy Files to Source Folder...</guibutton> to select your source files. OmegaT will then copy the selected files to the <filename>/source/</filename> subfolder of your newly created project. After the source files have loaded in the <guilabel>Editor</guilabel> pane, you can close the <guilabel>Project Files</guilabel> dialog.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="translate.the.segments.one.by.one">
    <title>Překlad souboru</title>

    <para>OmegaT při překládání aktivuje v daném časovém úseku vždy jen jeden segment pro zpracování. After you have translated each segment, press <keycap>Ctrl+U</keycap> to move to the next untranslated segment (or <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+U</keycap> to move to the next translated segment). Whenever you want to see what your translation will look like in its final format, press <keycap>Ctrl+D</keycap> to generate the translated documents, which will be created in the <filename>/target/</filename> subfolder of your project folder. During translation, use the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> and <guimenu>Go To</guimenu> menus to perform various useful functions.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Ověřujte tagy</title>

    <para>If your source files are formatted files, e.g. Microsoft Word, LibreOffice Writer nebo HTML, OmegaT zkonvertuje formátování do tagů, které obklopují překládaný text. Often documents will also have tags that have nothing to do with formatting, but which are also important in the source files (and in the translated files). A source sentence might look like: <mediaobject> <imageobject role="html"> <imagedata align="justify" fileref="images/InstantGuide_1.png"/> </imageobject> <imageobject role="fo"> <imagedata align="justify" fileref="images/InstantGuide_1.png" width="40%"/> </imageobject> </mediaobject>
    </para>

    <para>OmegaT, however, will present this sentence in the following
    fashion:
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="justify" fileref="images/InstantGuide_2.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="justify" fileref="images/InstantGuide_2.png" width="45%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </para>
    
    <para>Tagy jsou v OmegaT zašedlé, takže je jednoduché je odlišit od textu. They are protected, so that you cannot modify their contents, but you can delete them, enter them by hand or move them around in the target sentence. However, if you made mistakes when you typed the formatting tags, your translated files might fail to open. Therefore, press <keycap>Ctrl+T</keycap> before you generate your translated files, to validate that your tags are correct.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Generování přeloženého souboru.</title>

    <para>Once you have made certain that there are no tag errors in your
    translation, press <keycap>Ctrl+D</keycap> to generate the target files,
    which will be created in the <filename>/target/</filename> subfolder of
    your project folder.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Ještě pár věcí, na které je dobré dbát</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If a file does not load into the <guilabel>Editor</guilabel> pane, then it could be that it is in a format that doesn't work in OmegaT. See
        <link linkend="chapter.file.filters">File Filters</link> for a list of file formats that OmegaT can handle.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can create a new project for each new job, and you can add
        new source files to a project at anytime time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To remind yourself of the project's initial settings, open the
        project settings dialog by pressing <keycap>Ctrl+E</keycap>. To see a
        list of files in the project, open the <guilabel>Project Files</guilabel> dialog by
        pressing <keycap>Ctrl+L</keycap>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>At the end of your translation, OmegaT exports three translation
        memories called <filename>level1</filename>, <filename>level2</filename> and <filename>omegat</filename> to your project
        folder. The <filename>level1</filename> and <filename>level2</filename> memories can be shared with users of
        other translation programs. The memory named <filename>omegat</filename> can be used by
        OmegaT itself, in future projects that you create. If you place such
        translation memory files in the <filename>/tm/</filename> subfolder of a project,
        OmegaT will automatically search them for similar segments, called
        &quot;fuzzy matches&quot;.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can add a new term to the glossary by pressing
        <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+G</keycap>, or copy existing glossaries to
        the <filename>/glossary/</filename> subfolder of your project folder,
        and OmegaT will automatically look up words in them.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>It is often useful to search for words and phrases in the source
        text and in your translation, so press <keycap>Ctrl+F</keycap> for the
        <guilabel>Text Search</guilabel> dialog at any time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Podrobnější úvodní poznámky najdete na webu OmegaT <ulink url="http://www.omegat.org/en/tutorial/OmegaT%20for%20Beginners.pdf">OmegaT pro začátečníky</ulink>  Pokud potřebujete pomoc s jakýmkoliv aspektem OmegaT, nebojte se přidat k <ulink url="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/OmegaT/">Uživatelské skupině OmegaT</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>