<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="windows.projectfiles">
  <title>Project Files</title>

  <para>This window is displayed automatically when OmegaT loads a project,
  and at any time by pressing <menuchoice>
      <guimenuitem>Project</guimenuitem>

      <guimenuitem>Project Files...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.</para>

  <para><remark>Note:</remark> it is possible to inhibit the window displaying
  at opening, by setting <emphasis>project_files_show_on_load</emphasis> to
  <emphasis>false</emphasis> in <filename>omegat.prefs</filename> file
  (accessible by <menuchoice>
      <guimenuitem>Options</guimenuitem>

      <guimenuitem>Access Configuration Folder</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> menu).</para>

  <para>Use <guimenuitem>Ctrl+L</guimenuitem> to open and <keycap>Esc</keycap>
  to close it. The <guilabel>Project Files</guilabel> Window displays the
  following information:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>the total number of translatable files in the project. These are
      the files present in the /source folder in a format that OmegaT is able
      to recognize. This number is displayed in brackets, next to the &quot;Project
      file&quot; title</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>the list of all translatable files in the project. Clicking on any
      file will open it for translation.</para>

      <para>Typing any text will open a <guilabel>Filter</guilabel> field
      where parts of filenames can be entered. You can select a file with
      <keycap>Up</keycap> and <keycap>Down</keycap> keys, and open it for
      translation by pressing <keycap>Enter</keycap></para>

      <para>Note: filenames (in first column) can be sorted alphabetically by
      clicking in the header. It also possible to change the position of a
      filename, by clicking on it and pressing <emphasis>Move ...</emphasis>
      buttons.</para>

      <para>Right-clicking on a filename opens a popup that allows to open the
      source file and (if it exists) the target file.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>File entries include their names, file filter types, their
      encoding and the number of segments each file contains</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>the total number of segments, the number of unique segments in the
      whole project, and the number of unique segments already translated are
      shown at the bottom</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The set of <emphasis role="bold">Unique </emphasis>segments is
  computed by taking all the segments and removing all duplicate segments.
  (The definition of “unique” is case-sensitive: &quot;Run&quot; and &quot;run&quot; are treated
  as being different)</para>

  <para>The difference between &quot;Number of segments&quot; and &quot;Number of unique
  segments&quot; provides an approximate idea of the number of repetitions in the
  text. Note however that the numbers do not indicate how relevant the
  repetitions are: they could mean relatively long sentences repeated a number
  of times (in which case you are fortunate) or it could describe a table of
  keywords (not so fortunate). The <filename>project_stats.txt</filename>
  located in the omegat folder of your project contains more detailed segment
  information, broken down by file.</para>

  <para>Modifying the segmentation rules may have the effect of modifying the
  number of segments/unique segments. This, however, should generally be
  avoided once you have started translating the project. See the chapter
  <emphasis>Segmentation rules</emphasis> for more information.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Adding files to the project: </emphasis>You can
  add source files to the project by clicking on the &quot;<guimenuitem>Import
  Source Files...&quot;</guimenuitem> button. This copies the selected files to the
  <filename>source</filename> folder and reloads the project to import the new
  files. You can also add source files from Internet pages, written in
  MediaWiki, by clicking on<guimenuitem> &quot;Import from MediaWiki&quot;</guimenuitem>
  button and providing the corresponding URL.</para>
</section>