You don't like flying, do you?
What gives you that idea?
You want to know the secret...
to surviving air travel?
After you get
where you're going,
take off your shoes and socks.
Then walk around,
making fists
with your toes.
Fists with your toes?
It sounds crazy,
but I've been doing it
for nine years.
Better than a shower
and a cup of coffee.
Okay.
It's okay.
I'm a cop.
Trust me.
I've been doing this
for 11 years.
On behalf of
the captain and crew,
we'd like to welcome you
to Los Ángeles.
Have a very Merry Christmas.
Flight 227 to Tucson
now boarding at gate 14.
Ah.
How do you do?
Ladies and gentlemen.
Ladies and gentlemen!
I want to congratulate
each and every one of you...
for making this
one of the greatest years...
in the history
of the Nakatomi Corporation.
On behalf of
the chief executive officer,
Mr. Ozu,
and the board of directors,
we wish you
a Merry Christmas...
and a Happy New Year!
Merry Christmas!
Happy New Year!
Hey, Holly,
what about
dinner tonight, huh?
Harry, it's Christmas Eve.
Families, stockings...
chestnuts...
Rudolph and Frosty.
Any of these things
ring a bell?
Actually, I was
thinking more...
of mulled wine,
a nice aged brie,
and a roaring fireplace.
You know what I'm saying?
Ginny, it's 5:40.
Go join the party.
Have some champagne.
You're making me feel
like Ebenezer Scrooge.
Can the baby
handle a little sip?
That baby's ready
to tend bar.
Last chance.
Bye.
McClane residence.
Lucy McClane speaking.
Hello, Lucy McClane.
This is
your mother speaking.
Mommy!
When are you
coming home?
Pretty soon.
You'll be in bed
when I get there, though.
Let me talk to Paulina.
And no snooping
around the house,
looking for presents.
Is Daddy coming home
with you?
Well, we'll see what...
Santa and Mommy
can do, okay?
Put Paulina on.
Bye, honey.
Paulina!
Hola, Mrs. Holly.
Um, did Mr. McClane call?
No, Mrs. Holly.
No teléfono.
Well, he probably just
didn't have time...
before his flight.
Um, make up
the spare bedroom...
just in case.
Si, Mrs. Holly.
I do that already.
What would I do
without you, Paulina?
Oh!
California.
Hey, I'm John McClane.
Argyle.
I'm your limo driver.
Nice bear.
Okay... Argyle.
What do we do now?
You tell me.
It's my first time
driving a limo.
This is my first time
riding in one.
Relax. We got everything
in this mug, man.
Look at this...
CD, CB, TV,
telephone, full bar, VHS.
If your friend's
hot to trot,
I know a few
mama bears.
Or is he married?
He's married.
Okay.
Oh, sorry about that.
It's the girl's day off.
I didn't know
you were gonna sit up front.
So, uh, your lady
live out here?
About the past
six months.
Meaning you still
live in New York?
You always ask
this many questions, Argyle?
Sorry, man.
I used to drive a cab.
People would expect
a little chitchat.
So you divorced?
Just drive the car, man.
Come on.
You divorced?
You separated?
She beat you up?
She had a good job.
It turned into
a great career.
That meant
she had to move here.
You're very fast, Argyle.
So why didn't you come?
Well?
What's up?
Because I'm
a New York cop.
I got a six-month backlog
of New York scumbags.
I can't just pick up
and go that easy.
You thought
she wouldn't make it out here,
so why bother
to pack, right?
Like I said,
you're very fast, Argyle.
You mind if we
hear some tunes?
Hey, that will work.
Don't you got
any Christmas music?
This is Christmas music.
#It was December 24th
on Hollis Ave. After dark #
# When I seen a man chillin'
with his dog in the park #
#I approached them
very slowly #
# With my heart full of fear
looked at his dog #
# Oh, my God,
a ill reindeer #
#But then I was illin'
'cause the man had a beard #
#And a bag full of goodies
12:00 hit, man #
#So I turned my head a second #
#And the man was gone #
#But he must have
dropped his wallet #
#Smack dead on the lawn #
#I picked the wallet up,
and then I took a pause #
# Took out the
license and it cold said "Santa Claus"#
#A million dollars in it
cold hundreds of G's ##
So your lady sees you,
the music comes up,
and you live happily
ever after, right?
I can live with that.
If it doesn't work out,
you got a place to stay?
I'll find a place.
Tell you what.
I'll wait
in the parking garage.
You score, you call
on the car phone.
You strike out,
I'll get you a hotel.
You're all right, Argyle.
Just remember that
when you sign for the tip.
Hi.
Good evening.
I'm here to see
Holly McClane.
Just type it in there.
Cute toy.
If you have to
take a leak,
it finds
your zipper.
Christ.
30th floor.
The party.
They're the only ones
left in the building.
Take the express elevator...
until you hear the noise.
Thanks.
Champagne, sir?
Yeah, thanks.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Hey, Merry Christmas!
Jesus.
Fuckin' California.
Why don't
I talk to him right now?
Hi.
I'm looking for...
Holly Gennero.
Yeah.
You must be
John McClane.
Joe Takagi.
How was your ride in?
I have you to thank?
Seemed the least
we could do.
Quite a place
you have here.
It will be.
Several floors are
under construction.
Holly went to fax
some documents.
In the meanwhile,
her office is
right back here.
Ellis.
I was just making a call.
I want you to meet
John McClane,
Holly's husband...
Holly's policeman.
Ellis is in charge of
international development.
Heard a heck of a lot
about you.
Missed some.
Can I get you anything?
Food? Cake?
Some watered-down
champagne?
No, thank you.
I'm fine.
You throw quite a party.
I didn't realize...
they celebrated
Christmas in Japan.
Pearl Harbor
didn't work out,
so we got you
with tape decks.
Actually, it's sort of
a double celebration.
Holly helped us close
a big deal today.
I'll be out in
a couple of minutes.
John.
Have you met everyone?
We've been
sticking him with spears.
Of course, he has.
She was made
for the business.
Tough as nails.
I was hoping...
you made that flight.
Show him the watch.
Later.
Go on.
Show him.
What, are you
embarrassed?
A token of appreciation
for her hard work.
It's a Rolex.
I'm sure
I'll see it later.
Is there a place
where I could wash up?
Sure.
Ellis gets very depressed...
this time of year.
He thought he was
God's greatest gift.
Yeah.
I know the type.
Think he's got
his eye on you.
That's okay...
I have my eye...
on his private bathroom.
Where you staying?
Things happened so fast,
I didn't get
a chance to ask you.
Cappy Roberts
retired out here.
He told me
I could bunk with him.
Cappy retired, huh?
Where's he live?
Ramona.
Pomona.
Huh?
Yeah.
You'll be in the car
half the time.
Why don't we make it easy?
I have a spare bedroom.
It's not huge
or anything, but...
the kids would love
to have you at the house.
They would, huh?
I would, too.
Ooh!
Sorry.
I missed you.
I guess you didn't
miss my name, though, huh?
Except maybe when
you're signing checks?
Since when are you
"Ms. Gennero"?
This is
a Japanese company.
- They figure
a married woman's got...
- You are a married woman.
- You're married to me.
- Are we going to have
this conversation again?
- We never finished
this conversation in July.
- I had an opportunity...
- I had to take it.
- Right, no matter
what the consequences.
- No matter what it did
to our marriage.
- It didn't do anything...
except change your idea
of what our marriage should be.
- You don't have a clue what my
idea of our marriage should be.
- I know exactly...
what your idea
of our marriage should be.
Ms. Gennero, I...
Excuse me.
Hi.
Um, Mr. Takagi
is looking for you.
He wants you
to say something to the troops.
Speech time.
Be back in
a few minutes.
That was great, John.
Good job.
Very mature.
So Kareem rebounds, right?
Feeds Worthy on the break,
over to A.C., to Magic,
then back to Worthy, right?
Boom!
Two points!
We're in.
# La da da da
da da daaa! #
# Da da daaa! ##
Ha ha ha!
Links...
rechts...
und wieder links.
Son of a bitch.
Fists with your toes.
Yeah, Argyle?
How's it going up there?
All right.
Where are you?
What's the word with
you and your lady?
Uh, the vote's
not in yet.
Nein! Nein! Nein!
Argyle?
Mac, you there?
Hello?
#Somebody... ##
You know the number.
Use it.
Stay calm.
Everything's going to be fine.
Shit!
Think. Think.
Ladies and gentlemen.
Due to the
Nakatomi Corporation's...
legacy of greed
around the globe,
they're about to be
taught a lesson...
in the real use of power.
You will be witnesses.
Now...
Where is Mr. Takagi?
Joseph Yoshinobu Takagi,
- Born Kyoto, 1937.
- Don't move.
Family emigrated to
San Pedro, California, 1939.
Interned at Manzanar,
1942 to 1943.
Scholarship student,
University of California,
1955.
Law degree,
Stanford, 1962.
MBA, Harvard, 1970.
President,
Nakatomi Trading.
Vice chairman,
Nakatomi Investment Group.
Enough.
And father of five.
I am Takagi.
How do you do?
It's a pleasure
to meet you.
Okay, 32, construction,
33, computers.
#Do de do do do #
# Do do do do
do do do de do do ##
Nice suit.
John Phillips,
London.
I have two myself.
Rumor has it
Arafat buys his there.
On the left.
# Ba da da da #
# Ba da da ##
"And when Alexander saw
the breadth of his domain,
he wept, for there were
no more worids to conquer."
Benefits of
a classical education.
Oh,
that's beautiful.
I always enjoyed
to make models...
when I was a boy.
The exactness,
the attention to every
conceivable detail.
It's beautiful.
Is this what this is all about?
Our project in Indonesia?
Contrary to what
you people may think,
we're going to
develop that region,
not exploit it.
I believe you.
I read the article
in Forbes.
Mr. Takagi,
I could talk about industrialization
and men's fashions all day,
but I'm afraid
work must intrude,
and my associate here
has some questions for you.
Sort of fill-in-the-blanks
questions, actually.
I don't have that code!
You broke in here
to access our computer?
Any information you could get,
when they wake up in Tokio,
they'll change it.
You won't be able to blackmail
our executives, threaten our pro...
Sit... down!
Mr. Takagi,
I'm really not interested...
in your computer.
But I need the code key...
because I am interested
in the $640 million...
in negotiable bearer bonds...
that you have
locked in your vault.
And the computer
controls the vault.
You want money?
What kind
of terrorists are you?
Who said
we were terrorists?
The bonds represent
at most ten days'...
operating capital
for your parent organization.
The code, please.
It's useless to you.
There are seven vault safeguards,
and the code key's only one of them.
You'll never get it open.
Then there's no reason
not to tell us.
I told you.
It's not over yet.
It's a very nice suit...
Mr. Takagi.
It would be a shame
to ruin it.
I'm going to
count to three.
There will not be a four.
Give me...
the code.
One...
Two...
- Three.
- I don't know it. I'm telling you!
Get on the jet to Tokio
and ask the chairman.
I'm telling you.
You're just gonna have to kill me.
Okay.
We'll do it
the hard way.
Tony, see if you
can dispose of that.
Karl, better check
on Heinrich's work.
Nothing.
See to Heinrich.
Now...
you can
break the code?
You didn't
bring me along...
for my charming
personality.
Argyle, tell me
you heard the shots.
You're callin'
the police right now.
Of course
I'm coming by later.
Have I ever lied to you?
My boss?
Thinks I'm on my way to Vegas.
Uli, get up on the pipes.
Marco, you go
through here.
I'll throw you the cord.
Hans, we're on the roof.
Here.
Thirty minutes
to break the code,
Two hours, two and a half hours
for the five mechanicals...
at the minimum.
The seventh lock,
however, is out of my hands.
I'm sorry...
The seventh lock...
the electromagnetic seal.
You do understand...
the circuits cannot
be cut locally.
Trust me.
Why the fuck
didn't you stop him, John?
'Cause then
you'd be dead, too, asshole!
Think, goddamn it!
Think!
We've got a fire alarm.
Call 911.
Give them the guard's name
and the building code number,
and cancel the alarm.
Then disable the system.
On what floor
did the alarm go off?
Now, shall we go?
Nein.
Oh, baby, come to Papa.
Come on.
Come on, baby.
Come to Papa.
I'll kiss
your fuckin'dalmatian.
You stupid motherfuckers!
No!
Turn the fuckin' truck around!
The fire has been
called off, my friend.
No one is coming to help you.
You might as well
come out and join the others.
I promise
I won't hurt you.
Drop it, dickhead.
It's the police.
You won't hurt me.
Yeah? Why not?
Because
you're a policeman.
There are rules
for policemen.
Yeah. That's what
my captain keeps telling me.
Aah!
You bet your ass
I wish to proceed.
Nine million terrorists
in the worid,
and I got to kill one
with feet smaller than my sister.
I wanted this
to be professional,
efficient, and cooperative.
Not a lot to ask.
Alas, Mr. Takagi
did not see it that way,
so he won't be joining us
for the rest of his life.
We can go
any way you want it.
You can walk out
or be carried out,
but have no illusions...
we are in charge.
So... decide now, each of you,
And please remember...
we have left nothing
to chance.
Get them back!
"Now I have
a machine gun.
Ho-ho-ho. "
A security guard
we missed?
They're usually
just growing fat on a pension.
This is
something else.
We have to do
something, Hans.
Yes, we do.
Tell Karl his brother is dead.
Tell him
to come down.
Karl...
komm sofort.
Franco, you and Fritz take
the body upstairs and out of sight.
I don't want the hostages
to think too much.
Aah!
I want blood!
But let Heinrich
plant the detonators.
The police will waste hours
trying to negotiate.
Then you can
tear the building apart.
But until then,
do not alter the plan.
And if he alters it?
What do you think?
Something's wrong.
Cops?
John.
John... Aw, Christ!
He can fuck this whole thing up!
What does
he think he's doing?
His job.
Bullshit. His job's
3,000 miles away.
Without him, we might
be able to get out of here.
Tell that to Takagi.
Mayday. Mayday,
Anyone copying channel nine.
Terrorists have seized
the Nakatomi Building...
and are holding
30 hostages.
Unknown number
of terrorists...
Six or more armed
with automatic weapons.
Where's the best place
to transmit?
- Somebody answer me, goddamn it!
- The roof!
Go! Go!
It's the same
address as that fire signal.
I'll handle it.
Attention,
whoever you are,
this channel
is reserved for emergencies.
No shit, lady!
I'm not ordering
a pizza!
No one kills him
but me.
They have
killed one hostage.
They are fortifying
their positions...
while you're jerking
me off on the radio!
Sir, I've
already told you.
This is
a reserved channel.
If this is
an emergency call, dial 911.
Otherwise, I'll report
this as an FCC violation.
Fine! Come and arrest me,
just send the police now!
Ow!
See if there's
a black-and-white
to do a drive-by.
Thought you guys
just ate doughnuts.
They're for my wife.
Yeah.
She's pregnant.
Bag it.
Big time.
Thanks.
Dispatch
to 8-Lincoln-30. Over.
This is 8-Lincoln-30.
Come on in. Over.
Investigate a Code 2...
at Nakatomi Plaza,
Century City.
8- Lincoln-30 to dispatch.
I'm on my way.
Giris.
Shit! Where the fuck?
Oh, my God.
He's in the elevator shaft.
Perfect.
The elevators are locked off.
Just shut him in
and come back down.
Oh, fuck.
Karl, the police
are probably...
on their way already.
Christ.
I can stall them but not
if they hear gunshots.
If you lock him in,
he'll be neutralized...
Come out to the coast!
We'll get together,
have a few laughs.
Now I know
what a TV dinner feels like.
Such!
Karl, komm!
Die polizei!
Well, it's about time.
No signs
of disturbance, dispatch.
Possible crank call.
Check the area
and confirm.
Who's driving this car?
Stevie Wonder?
I see a guard inside.
I'm going in
for a closer look.
Use caution.
Eddie?
I had a feelin'
you'd be callin'.
Evenin', Officer.
What can I do for you?
Heh heh heh!
We had
that false alarm, you know.
That computer
sent you out...
on another
wild-goose chase.
They been chasing bugs...
since they installed
this system.
Notre Dame
on top of USC...
Ah, shit!
I got 50 bucks bet
on them assholes.
Come on, come on.
Where's the fucking cavalry?
Ah!
Bah!
... was good for 52 yards.
Mind if I look around?
Help yourself.
Seven seconds left
in this period.
Seven to nothing,
Notre Dame.
Freeze, Motherfucker!
Don't shoot!
Drop it!
Okay! Don't shoot!
Ah!
Ah, the hell with this!
You are dog now!
No more table!
Where are you going, pal?
Next time
you have a chance...
to kill someone,
don't hesitate.
Thanks for the advice.
Sorry to waste your time.
No problem.
Merry Christmas.
# Oh, the weather outside
is frightful #
# Dum de dum delightful #
For the love...
8- Lincoln-30
to dispatch.
Go ahead.
That's a wild-goose chase...
here at Nakatomi Plaza.
Everything here's okay.
Over.
# But nobody has no place to go #
# Let it snow, let it snow ##
Goddamn it!
Jesus H. Christ!
Welcome
to the party, pal!
Goddamn it!
# Turn up the heat #
#It's getting ready
to pop ##
Police under automatic
rifle fire at Nakatomi!
I need back-up assistance now!
Now, Goddamn it! Now!
Monica,
I can get us a table.
Wolfgang and I
are very close friends.
I interviewed him,
for God's sake.
... Nakatomi.
Repeat.
Officer needs assistance at...
I'm at Nakatomi Plaza.
They're turning my car
into Swiss cheese!
I need
back-up assistance now!
Now, Goddamn it! Now!
Never thought I'd love
to hear that sound.
All of you relax.
This is a matter
of inconvenient timing.
Police action was inevitable...
and, as it happens,
necessary.
Let them fumble about outside,
and stay calm.
This is simply the beginning.
I thought I told all of you
I want radio silence.
I didn't get
that message, Hans.
You should have put it
on the bulletin board.
Since I waxed Tony and Marco
and his friend,
I figured you and Karl
and Franco might be lonely.
How does he know
so much...
That's very kind of you.
I assume you are
our mysterious party crasher.
You are most troublesome
for a security guard.
Eeeh! Sorry, Hans.
Wrong guess.
Want to go
for DoubleJeopardy,
where the scores
can really change?
Mm, these are
very bad for you.
Who are you, then?
The fly in
the ointment, Hans.
The monkey
in the wrench,
the pain in the ass.
Whoa!
Don't use the radio.
See if he's lying about Marco.
Find out who's missing.
Mr. Mystery Guest,
are you still there?
Yeah, I'm still here,
unless you want to open
the front door for me.
I'm afraid not,
but you have me
at a loss.
You know my name,
but who are you?
Just another American...
who saw too many movies
as a child?
Another orphan
of a bankrupt culture...
who thinks he's
John Wayne, Rambo,
Marshal Dillon?
I was always partial
to Roy Rogers, actually.
I liked those
sequined shirts.
Do you think you have
a chance, Mr. Cowboy?
Yippee-kai-yay,
motherfucker.
I can get the jump
on everybody...
with a remote.
Harvey,
keep your pants on.
Sam, I'm begging you.
Simon's already out
with the remote.
I'm not sitting on this!
I am going out there!
You don't give me a truck,
I'll steal a truck.
Give us a break,
Thornburg.
Eat it, Harvey!
Four, three, two...
one.
Harvey, we're
on the air.
Good evening.
This is Harvey Johnson.
And I'm Gail Wallens,
and this is
Nightline News at 10:00.
Our top stories
on this Christmas eve...
Take truck number five.
Get out of here.
He wasn't lying
about Marco.
He's down
on the street.
The other man
was Heinrich,
and his bag
is missing.
He had the detonator.
Theo.
Yo!
We may have
some problems.
How's your schedule?
Three down.
Four to go.
Then don't waste time
talking to me.
This is sergeant Al Powell
of the L.A.P.D.
If the person
who radioed can hear me,
acknowledge
this transmission.
I say again...
If the person who radioed
can hear me,
acknowledge
this transmission!
I read you.
You the guy in the car?
What's left of him.
Can you identify
yourself?
Not now.
Maybe later.
This is a party line.
The neighbor's got
itchy trigger fingers.
You got 30 hostages
on the 30th floor.
- The leader's name is Hans.
- We have to find him
and shut him up.
- He's telling them everything!
- Let him. I'm waiting for the FBI.
Until then, he can waste
as much time as he likes,
but we must find
the bag, Fritz.
We must have
the detonators.
They got
missiles, automatic weapons,
and enough explosives
to orbit Arnold Schwarzenegger.
They're down to nine now.
These guys
are mostly European,
judging by
their clothing labels and...
cigarettes.
They're well-financed
and very slick.
How do you
know that?
I've seen
enough phony I.D. S...
to recognize that the ones
they got must have cost a fortune.
Add all that up,
I don't know
what the fuck it means,
but you got some bad-ass
perpetrators here to stay.
I hear you, partner.
L.A.'s finest are on it.
Light 'em
if you got 'em.
Way ahead of you, partner.
So, what do I call you?
Call me...
Roy.
If you think of
anything else,
don't you be shy, okay?
In the meantime,
let us do our job.
They're all yours, Al.
All right,
who's talking to him?
I am, sir. Sergeant Powell.
Al Powell.
Dwayne Robinson, Powell.
What's the deal here?
What do
these pricks want?
Well, we don't exactly know.
We haven't heard from them.
Who have you been talking to?
We don't know.
He won't give us his name.
He appears to be
the one who phoned.
He's killed
one terrorist,
and he claims two others.
Claims? Powell,
has it occurred to you...
he could be one
of the terrorists...
or some nutcase in there?
No. In fact,
I think he's a cop...
Maybe not L.A.P.D.,
but he's a badge.
Why?
A hunch,
things he said,
like being able
to spot a phony I.D.
Jesus Christ, Powell.
He could be a fucking
bartender for all we know!
TV's here.
Oh, shit.
I have a request.
What idiot
put you in charge?
You did...
when you murdered
my boss.
Now everybody's
looking to me.
Personally,
I'd pass on the job.
I don't enjoy being
this close to you.
Go on.
We have
a pregnant woman.
Relax. She's not due
for a couple weeks,
but sitting on that rock isn't
doing her back any good.
So, I would like permission
to move her to one of the
offices where there's a sofa.
I'll have a sofa
brought out. Good enough?
Good enough.
Unless you
like it messy,
start bringing us
in groups to the bathroom.
Yes. You're right.
It will be done.
Was there
something else?
No, thank you.
Mr. Takagi chose
his people well, Mrs...
Gennero.
Miss Gennero.
We interrupt this program
for a special bulletin.
This is Richard Thornburg
live from Century City.
Tonight, Los Ángeles
has joined...
the sad and woridwide
fraternity of cities...
whose only
membership requirement...
is to suffer the anguish
of international terrorism.
Approximately
two hours ago,
an unidentified
group of men...
seized control
of the Nakatomi Building,
sealing off
all entrances and exits.
All telephone lines
have been cut,
and the only communication
now possible...
has been through the use
of CB communicators,
the group apparently
brought with them.
According to
official sources,
the perpetrators
of this building siege...
Unit Five, hold your position.
We got Charlie Unit
in position...
by the parking structure.
Let me ask you something.
Does this stairway
go up to the escalator?
Yeah.
Tell them to go ahead.
What's going on?
What's it look like?
We're going in.
Going in?
Man, that's crazy!
There could be
over 30 hostages!
We don't know shit,
Powell.
How come there were
no ransom demands?
Where's their list
of demands?
All we know is
somebody shot your car.
It's probably the same
son of a bitch...
you've been
talking to on that radio.
Excuse me, sir.
What about the body
that fell out the window?
Probably some stockbroker...
Got depressed.
Let's go.
Hit your lights.
Lights on!
Powell?
You still with me, babe?
What's going on?
Yo, Al.
I'm kind of busy.
I'll talk to you later.
Al, what's wrong?
We'll talk later.
If you are what
I think you are,
you'll know when
to listen, shut up,
and when to pray.
Jesus Christ!
You're coming in.
I told you what kind
of people they are.
Let's load them up.
Blue go.
They'll be coming.
Everyone get ready.
Theo, you are
the eyes now.
Rivers, begin
your reconnoiter.
Shit!
Hey, come on, man.
Let's go.
Ow! Jesus!
All right, spread out.
Shut up.
Let's go.
You macho assholes.
No! No!
Ahem... all right.
Listen up, guys.
'Twas the night
before Christmas,
and all through the house,
not a creature
was stirring, except...
the four assholes
coming in the rear...
in standard
cover formation.
We're all set.
We're ready.
Kick ass.
Go.
Right.
Let's do it.
They're shooting
at them.
It's panic fire.
They can't see.
They're shooting
at the lights.
They're going
after the lights.
Pull them back.
It's not happening.
Mike, burn it.
Don't be impatient.
Just wound them.
They're sitting ducks
without lights.
They're almost in.
Send in the car.
Jesus Christ!
Rivers, Rodriguez,
report.
Whoa! Wait a minute.
What have we here, gentlemen?
The police
have themselves an RV.
Southeast corner.
Oh, Jesus Christ.
Get back!
Get the fuck back!
Get over there!
Schnell! Schnell!
Mach schnell!
Weiter! Weiter!
Weiter!
Mach schnell!
Mach los! Mach los!
I see him!
Oh, my God!
The quarterback is toast!
Hang on, Rivers.
That's an order.
Hit it again.
Hans, you motherfucker!
You made your point!
Let them pull back!
Thank you, Mr. Cowboy.
I'll take it under advisement.
Hit it again!
Thank you, Mr. Cowboy.
I'll take it under advisement.
Hit it again!
Fire.
Fuck me.
Get them out of the car.
- Aah!
Fuck it.
Mach schnell!
Mach los!
Let's see you take this
under advisement, jerkweed.
Geronimo,
motherfucker.
Shit!
They're using
artillery on us!
You idiot,
it's not the police.
It's him.
Holy shit.
My God.
Tell me you got that.
I got it.
Eat your heart out,
Channel Five.
We've had
an update on the takeover
of the Nakatomi Building...
Sources say
the terrorist leader, "Hans,"
may be this man...
Hans Gruber,
a member of the radical
West German Volksfrei movement.
Strangely,
the Volksfrei leadership...
issued a communique
an hour ago...
stating Gruber had been expelled
from that organization...
Al? Al? Do you copy?
Are you all right?
Yeah, I'm fine.
What was that?
Remember that plastic
explosive I told you about?
There you go.
Is the building on fire?
No, but it's going to
need a paint job.
Our spotter said
you got two that time.
Is that him?
Yes, sir.
I don't know
who you think you are,
but you just destroyed
a building.
We do not want your help.
Is that clear?
I've got 100 people
down here,
and they're covered
with glass.
Who gives a shit
about glass?
Who the fuck is this?
This is deputy chief of police,
Dwayne T. Robinson,
and I am in charge
of this situation.
Oh, you're in charge?
I got bad news
for you, Dwayne.
It doesn't look like you're
in charge of jack shit.
- Listen to me, you little asshole...
- Asshole?
I'm not the one who just got
buttfucked on national TV, Dwayne!
Listen to me, jerkoff,
quit being part
of the fucking problem...
and put the other guy
back on!
Hey, Roy, how are
you feeling?
Pretty fucking
unappreciated, Al.
Hey, look.
I love you.
So do a lot
of the other guys.
You hang in there.
You hear me?
Yeah, thanks, partner.
What are you doing?
I'm tired
of waiting to see...
who gets us killed first...
them or your husband.
What are you
going to do?
Hey, babe, I negotiate
million-dollar deals for breakfast.
I think I can
handle this "Euro-trash."
Hey,
sprechen sie, talk?
If you'd listened to me,
he'd be neutralized.
I don't want neutral. I want dead.
Hope I'm not
interrupting.
What does he want?
It's not
what I want.
It's what
I can give you.
Oy, let's be
straight, okay?
It's obvious you're not
some dumb schmuck up here...
to snatch a few purses,
am I right?
Very perceptive.
I watch
60 Minutes.
I say to myself,
"these guys are professional,
"they're motivated,
they're happening,
i.e., they want
something," huh?
I couldn't care less
about your politics.
Maybe you're pissed off
at the camel jockeys,
maybe it's the Hebes,
Northern Ireland...
It's none
of my business.
I figure you're here to negotiate.
Am I right?
You're amazing.
You figured this
all out already?
Hey, business
is business.
You use a gun.
I use a fountain pen.
What's the difference?
Let's put it
in my terms.
You're here on a hostile takeover.
You grab us for some greenmail,
but you didn't expect
some poison pill running around.
Am I right?
Hans, bubby, I'm
your white knight.
I must have missed
60 Minutes.
What are you saying?
The guy upstairs is
fucking things up, huh?
I can give him to you.
Oh, God...
Uhh...
Roy?
Roy,
you all right?
Just trying to fire down
a 1,000-year-old Twinkie.
What do they put
in these things anyway?
Sugar, enriched flour,
partially hydrogenated
vegetable oil,
polysorbate 60...
and yellow dye
number five...
Just everything
a growing boy needs.
How many kids
you got, Al?
My wife is working
on our first.
How about you,
cowboy?
You got any kids?
Yeah... two.
Hope I can see 'em
swingin' on a jungle gym
with AIJr. Someday.
Well, now,
that's a date,
but you bring
the ice cream.
Touching, cowboy. Touching.
Or should I call you...
Mr. McClane.?
Mr. Officer John McClane...
of the New York
Police Department?
- Get on the phone to Harry
in New York. Come on, baby. Move.!
- Got it.
Better get a hold
of somebody at dispatch.
Sister Theresa called me
Mr. McClane in the third grade,
my friends call me John,
and you're neither,
shithead.
I have someone
who wants to talk to you...
A very special friend...
who was with you
at the party tonight.
Hey, John boy.
Ellis?
Yeah.
Now, listen, John.
They're giving me
a few minutes...
to try to talk
some sense into you.
I know you think
you're doin' your job,
but you're just
draggin' this thing out.
No one gets out of here
until these guys can talk...
to the L.A. Police, and that
just ain't gonna happen...
till you stop messing up
the works, capisci?
Ellis, what have
you told them?
I told them
we were old friends,
and you were
my guest.
You shouldn't
be doing this.
Tell me about it.
All right, John,
listen.
They want you to tell them
where the detonators are.
They know people
are listening.
They want
the detonators,
or they're
going to kill me.
John, didn't you
hear me?
Yeah, I hear you.
John, get
with the program.
Tell these guys...
where
the detonators are...
so no one else
gets hurt!
I'm putting my life
on the line, pal!
Ellis,
listen to me carefully.
John...
Shut up, Ellis!
Just shut your mouth!
Put Hans back on!
Hans, this shithead doesn't
know you, but I do...
Good. Then you'll
give us what we want.
You're not part
of this equation.
What am I,
a method actor?
Put away the gun.
This is radio,
not television.
Hans, he's not my friend!
I don't know him!
Jesus, Ellis!
They'll kill you!
Tell them
you don't know me!
How can you say that
after all these years?
John? John?
Do you hear that?
Talk to me! Where
are my detonators?
Where are they,
or shall I shoot
another one?
Sooner or later,
I'll get to someone
you care about.
Go fuck
yourself, Hans.
Did you hear that?
He just let
the guy die, man.
Man, can't you see
what's happening?
Can't you read
between the lines?
He did everything
he could...
to save him.
If he gave up,
they'd both be dead!
No. They'd be
talking to us.
You tell your partner
to stay out of this.
If he doesn't,
I'm going to
nail his ass.
The man is hurting.
He is alone, tired,
and he hasn't seen
diddly-squat...
from anybody here!
You think
he'll give a damn...
about what you do
if he makes it?
Wake up and smell
what you shoveling.
Anytime you want
to go home,
you consider
yourself dismissed.
No, sir.
You couldn't drag me away.
Attention, police.
This is Sergeant
Al Powell...
This is deputy chief
Dwayne Robinson.
Who is this?
This is Hans Gruber.
I assume you realize
the futility of direct action.
We have no wish
for further loss of life.
Well, what is it
you do wish for?
I have comrades
around the worid...
languishing
in prison.
The American
State Department...
enjoys rattling its saber
for itself.
Now it can rattle it
for me.
The following are to be
released from their captors...
The seven members
of the New Provo Front,
in Canada, the five imprisoned
leaders of Liberté du Quebec,
in Sri Lanka, the nine members
of the Asian Dawn.
What the fuck?
I read about them
in Time magazine.
When these revolutionary
brothers and sisters are free,
the hostages will be
taken to the roof...
and will accompany us
in helicopters...
to the Los Ángeles
International Airport...
where they'll be given
further instructions.
You have two hours
to comply.
Wait a minute,
Mr. Gruber.
This is crazy.
I don't have
the authority.
Two hours
is not enough.
Hello? Hello!
Did you get
all that?
We got to make
some calls.
Do you think
they'll try?
Who cares?
Theo, are we
on schedule?
One more. Then
it's up to you.
This one will
take a miracle.
It's Christmas, Theo.
It's the time of miracles,
so be of good cheer.
Call me when you hit
the last lock.
Hunt that little shit down
and get those detonators.
Fritz is checking
the explosives.
I'll check
Hey, Powell,
you out there?
I'm here, John.
I'm here.
Believe me, there was
nothing I could do.
It's gonna be
both our asses...
if you're wrong.
I hear you.
Did you catch that bullshit
Hans was running?
It doesn't
make sense, man.
I'm just
a desk jockey...
who was on my way
home when you rang.
The way you drove,
I figured you
for the street.
In my youth.
... Author of Hostage Terrorist,
Terrorist Hostage...
A Study in Duality.
What can we expect
in the next few hours?
The hostages
are probably experiencing...
the early stages
of the Helsinki Syndrome.
As in Helsinki,
Sweden.
Finland.
Basically, it's when
the hostages...
and the terrorists...
go through a sort of
psychological transference...
and a projection
of dependency.
A strange sort of trust
and bond develops.
We've had situations
where the hostages...
embraced their captors
after release...
and even corresponded
with them in prison.
No, no, darling.
Asian Dawn. Dawn.
D- A-W-N.
Sir?
Yeah?
The FBI is here.
The FBI is here now?
Yes, sir.
Right over there.
Hold this.
Want a breath mint?
Hey, how you
doing, man?
I'm Agent Johnson.
This is Special Agent Johnson.
Oh, how you doing?
No relation.
I'm, uh...
I'm Dwayne Robinson,
L.A.P.D.
I'm in charge here.
Not anymore.
Hi there.
How you doing?
Ooh...
Please, God. You're
one of them, aren't you?
You're one of them.
No! Don't kill me!
No, please.
Don't kill me,
please! No!
Relax. I'm not
going to hurt you.
I won't hurt you!
Oh, God.
What the fuck are
you doing up here?
What were you
looking for?
I managed to get
out of there.
I was trying to get
up on the roof...
and see if I could
signal for help.
Why don't you
come and help?
Hold it. Hold it.
Forget the roof.
They got people
all over it.
You want to stay alive,
you stay with me.
The best
we can figure it,
we've got maybe 30 or 35
hostages up there,
probably
on the 30th floor,
and maybe seven or eight
terrorists up there.
Sounds like
an A-7 scenario.
We'll handle it
from here.
When we
commandeer your men,
we'll let you know.
Aren't you...
forgetting something?
Such as?
What about
John McClane?
He's the reason...
we have
any information.
He's also the reason...
you're only facing
seven terrorists.
He's inside?
Who is he?
He might be a cop.
We're checking.
One of yours?
No way.
You smoke?
Yeah.
Thanks.
You don't work
for Nakatomi.
And if you're not
one of them...
I'm a cop
from New York.
New York?
Yeah. Got invited to
the Christmas party by mistake.
Who knew?
Well, it's better than being caught
with your pants down, huh?
I'm John McClane.
You're, uh...
Clay.
Bill Clay.
Know how to use
a handgun, Bill?
I spent a weekend
at a combat ranch...
The guns that shoot
red paint.
Probably seems
kind of stupid to you.
Nope.
Time for the real
thing, Bill.
All you got to do
is pull the trigger.
Put down the gun...
and give me
my detonators.
Well, well, well...
Hans.
Put it down now.
That's pretty tricky
with that accent.
You ought to be
on fucking TV.
What do you want
with the detonators, Hans?
I already used
all the explosives...
or did I?
I'm going to
count to three.
Yeah.
Like you did
with Takagi?
Oops.
No bullets.
- What do you think...
I'm fucking stupid, Hans?
You we're saying?
Karl.
Shoot the glass!
Jesus Christ!
Smile, Karl.
We're back in business.
... is the last resort
of diplomacy,
couldn't we
just as well say...
that terrorism
has an equal claim...
on being that, too?
You got something.
Tell me you got something.
Just McClane's name,
badge number, employment record,
vital statistics,
and his family's home address,
right here in L.A.
Woo!
Go to work.
You got it.
God!
That man looks...
really pissed.
He's still alive.
What?
Only John can drive
somebody that crazy.
Hans, you better
heat up that miracle.
We broke through
on number six.
The electromagnetic
came down like a fucking anvil.
See what our friends
outside are doing,
and I'll be right up.
Hey, John.
John McClane,
you still with us?
Yeah.
All things being equal,
I'd rather be
in Philadelphia.
Chalk up
two more bad guys.
Well, the boys
down here...
will be glad
to hear that.
We got a pool
going on you.
What kind of odds
am I getting?
- You don't want to know.
- Put me down for 20.
I'm good for it.
Hey, pal, you got flat feet?
What the hell are
you talking about?
Something had to
get you off the street.
You don't think
jockeying papers...
is a noble effort?
No.
I had an accident.
The way you drive,
I can see why.
You run over
your captain's foot?
I shot a kid.
He was 13 years old.
Oh, it was dark.
I couldn't see him.
He had a ray gun that
looked real enough.
When you're a rookie,
they can teach you...
everything
about being a cop,
except how to live
with a mistake.
Anyway, I just
couldn't bring myself...
to draw my gun
on anybody again.
Sorry, man.
Hey, man,
how could you know?
I feel like shit
anyway.
Well, then,
this won't matter.
The L.A.P.D. is not...
calling the shots
down here anymore.
The feds?
You got it.
All right.
Those are the city engineers.
They're going into
the street circuits.
Those guys in the suits,
I don't know who they are.
That's the FBI.
They're ordering
the others...
to cut
the building's power.
Regular
as clockwork.
Or a time lock.
Precisely.
The circuits
that cannot be cut...
are cut automatically...
in response to
a terrorist incident.
You asked for miracles.
I give you the FBI.
It's going to go!
Yes!
Merry Christmas.
Those bastards are probably
pissing in their pants.
The mayor will
have my ass.
Woo!
What will we do now?
Arrest them for not paying
their electric bill?
We've shut them down.
We let them sweat,
then give them
helicopters.
Right up the ass.
This is Agent Johnson.
No, the other one.
I want air support
ready in five minutes.
Damn right.
Fully armed.
We're on the way.
Yeah!
I wish to talk to the FBI.
This is
Special Agent Johnson.
The State Department
has arranged...
for the return
of your comrades.
Helicopters are en route
as you requested.
We'll be ready.
When he realizes
what hit him,
he'll be dead.
When they touch down,
we'll blow the roof.
By the time
they figure out...
what went wrong,
we'll be sitting
on a beach...
earning 20%.
Ah! Jeez!
Powell?
Yo, Powell, you got a minute?
I'm here, John.
I'm starting to get
a bad feeling up here.
I want you to do
something for me.
Um...
I want you
to find my wife.
Don't ask me how.
I want you
to tell her something.
to tell her that...
Um...
Mmm...
Tell her it took me
a while to figure out...
what a jerk I'd been,
but, um... that...
that when things started
to pan out for her,
I should have been
more supportive,
and, uh...
I just should have
been behind her more.
Oh, shit.
Tell her that, um...
that she's the best thing
that ever happened...
to a bum like me.
She's heard me say
"I love you"
a thousand times.
She never heard me
say "I'm sorry."
I want you to
tell her that, Al.
I want you
to tell her...
that John said
that he was sorry.
Okay?
You got that, man?
Yeah, I got it, John,
but you can
tell her that yourself.
Just watch your ass
and make it out.
You hear me?
I guess that's up to
the man upstairs.
John? John?
What the fuck...
were you doing
upstairs, Hans?
John?
Al, listen.
Just lay off
for a while.
I got to go
check on something.
One minute,
that's all I'm asking...
One minute
to speak to them.
All right.
Get back. Get back.
All right,
look, look, look.
- Let me in right now,
or I call the I.N. S. ¿Comprende?
This is the last time
these kids will have...
to speak
to their parents.
- All right?
- Mm.
All right.
Come on.
What were you
doing, Hans?
What were you doing?
Jesus, Mary,
Mother of God.
It's a double-cross!
The roof is wired to...
John?
John!
John, come in!
Did you get that?
Something about
a double-cross.
Tell me about it.
We are both
professionals.
This is personal.
Ah...
Aagh!
Aah!
They're coming!
The choppers
are coming.
Okay,
Time to gather your flock,
Miss Gennero.
Your mom and dad
are very important people.
They're very brave people.
Is there something
you'd like to say to them?
Come home.
Mrs. McClane.
How nice to make
your acquaintance.
Everyone
to the roof!
Lock them there.
Come right back.
Ah!
You should have heard
your brother squeal...
when I broke
his fucking neck!
What do you
figure the breakage?
We take out
the terrorists,
lose 20, 25%
of the hostages... tops.
I can live
with that.
Get this thing
on the deck.
They're expecting
transports, not gun ships.
Move it!
Come on! Move!
Go! Move!
Theo.
A little bonus for us.
Please, sit down.
Sit down!
A policeman's wife
might come in handy.
McClane, I have
some news for you.
McClane.
Ah!
Aah!
Come on! Move!
Come on!
Yaah!
Motherfucker!
I'll kill you!
Armed.
The truck?
The truck.
After all
your posturing,
all your little
speeches,
you're nothing
but a common thief.
I am an exceptional thief,
Mrs. McClane,
and since I'm moving
up to kidnapping,
you should be
more polite.
Yaah!
Oh!
Going to kill you!
I'm going to
fucking cook you!
Going to fucking
eat you!
I don't
like this, Sarge.
Yaa-hah!
Just like
fucking Saigon,
Hey, slick?
I was in junior high,
dickhead.
Where's Holly?
Where's Holly Gennero?
Holly Gennero?
Where's Holly?
Where is she?
They took her!
Where?
The vault!
Where
is the vault?
The 30th floor!
They took her!
Get downstairs!
The whole fucking roof
is wired to blow!
Get down!
Get the fuck downstairs!
They made us, Bureau.
You got a terrorist
shooting at hostages.
Break left!
Nail that sucker!
I'm on your side,
you assholes!
Swing around again!
I'll bag
this little bastard.
What the fuck...
Oh, John, what the fuck
are you doing?
How the fuck did you
get into this shit?
Aah! Aah!
Aah!
There's something wrong!
They're coming back down!
Blow the roof.
Karl's up there!
Blow the roof!
I promise
I will never even think...
about going up
in a tall building again.
Oh, God,
please don't let me die!
Yaah!
Oh!
Aah!
Holy Christ!
We're
going to need...
some more
FBI guys, I guess.
Aah! Aah!
Jesus fucking Christ!
Fuck!
What the fuck
is going on?
What are you going to do?
Sit here while
the building falls?
Shit!
Oh! All right!
Uli.
Hey!
Hang on, baby.
Hang on, honey.
Oh, God.
Oh!
Allez! Allez vite!
J'y vais!
Hans!
Jesus.
Hi, honey.
So that's what this
is all about?
A fucking robbery?
Put down the gun.
Why'd you have to nuke
the whole building, Hans?
Well, when
you steal $600,
you can disappear.
When you steal
600 million,
they'll find you...
unless they think
you're already dead.
Put down the gun.
Uh.
Nein. This is mine.
You got me.
Still the cowboy,
Mr. McClane.
Americans, all alike.
This time, John Wayne doesn't
walk off into the sunset...
with Grace Kelly.
That was Gary Cooper,
asshole.
Enough jokes.
You'd have made...
a good cowboy
yourself, Hans.
Oh, yeah.
What was it you said
to me before?
Yippee-kai-yay,
motherfucker.
Holly!
Happy trails, Hans.
Aah!
Holly.
I hope that's
not a hostage.
Water hook-up
companies 93, 96...
Must have burned down
the whole building.
Over here.
It's a better angle.
Let's give them...
Keep it going, now.
Keep it going.
Come on.
We're going to miss it!
Okay.
Hand me my notes!
Come on, folks.
What was it like
in there?
How did they
treat you?
Al, this is
my wife Holly.
Holly Gennero.
Holly McClane.
Hello, Holly.
You got yourself
a good man.
You take
good care of him.
McClane!
McClane,
I want a debriefing!
You got some things...
to answer for,
mister...
Ellis' murder,
for one thing,
property damage,
interfering with
police business.
All right!
Two of you go inside...
- and see if there's
anybody else!
- Yes, sir...
This one's with me.
Mr. McClane.
Mr. McClane!
After this
incredible ordeal,
what are
your feelings?
Well, well, well.
Merry Christmas,
Argyle.
Merry Christmas.
Did you get that?
Let me through.
If this is their idea
of Christmas,
I got to be here
for New Year's.
# Oh, the weather outside
is frightful #
#But the fire
is so delightful #
#And since we've
no place to go #
#Let it snow, let it snow,
let it snow #
#It doesn't show signs
of stopping #
#And I brought
some corn for popping #
# The lights are turned
way down low #
#Let it snow, let it snow,
let it snow #
# When we finally
kiss good night #
#How I hate goin'out
in the storm #
#But if you
really hold me tight #
#All the way home,
I'll be warm #
# The fire is slowly dying #
#And, my dear,
we're still good-byeing #
#But as long as you
love me so #
#Let it snow #
#Let it snow ##