<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="Ch01.about.OmegaT">
  <title>About <application>OmegaT - introduction</application></title>

  <section id="OmegaT-Highlists">
    <title> OmegaT highlights</title>

    <para><application>OmegaT</application> is a free multi platform Computer
    Aided Translation tool, with the following highlights:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Translation
        memory:</emphasis><application> OmegaT</application> memorizes your
        translations in a translation memory. At the same time it can use
        memories from previous translations for reference. Translation
        memories can be very useful for a translation with a number of
        repetitions or reasonably similar segments of text.
        <application>OmegaT</application> uses translation memories to
        remember your previous translations and suggest to you the most
        probable translations for the text you are working on</para>

        <para>The translation memories can be very useful when a document,
        that's been already translated, needs to be updated. Unchanged
        sentences will remain as translated, and updated sentences will be
        shown with an older version of the same sentence as the most probable
        translation. Modifications to the original document will thus be
        handled with greater ease. If you are using previously created
        translation memories, for example given to you by translation agency
        or your client, <application>OmegaT</application> will be able to use
        them as a reference memories.</para>

        <para><application>OmegaT</application> uses the standard TMX file
        format to store and access translation memories, which guarantees that
        you can exchange your translation material with other CAT
        applications, supporting this file format.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Terminology
        management</emphasis>:Terminology management is important for
        translation consistency. <application>OmegaT</application> uses
        glossaries that contain translations of single words or small phrases,
        a sort of simplified bilingual dictionary for a specific domain.
        <application>OmegaT</application> displays the translation of those
        words that happen to be present in the current segment for your
        reference.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Translation process:</emphasis> Imagine
        having to translate anything from a single file to a folder that
        contains subfolders with a number of files in a variety of formats.
        When you let <application>OmegaT</application> know that you need to
        translate those files it will look for the included files it supports
        according to the file filtering rules, recognize the textual parts in
        them, split the biggest text groups according to the segmentation
        rules and display the segments one by one so that you can proceed with
        the translation. <application>OmegaT</application> will memorize your
        translations and will propose you translation candidates for segments
        similar to those recorded in memory. Once you want to see how the
        files would look once translated, you can create the translated files
        open them in the appropriate application and see what your translation
        looks like.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="OmegaT.chapters.summary">
    <title>Summary of chapters</title>

    <para>This documentation should serve both as a learning help and as a
    reference guide. Here a short summary of chapters and its contents.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"> Start Using OmegaT in 5
        Minutes!</emphasis> this chapter is intended as a Instant Start Guide
        for beginners and tyre kickers,showing the complete way from opening a
        new translation project to the finished translation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Installing OmegaT and running it:
        </emphasis>this chapter will be useful when starting to use OmegaT. It
        contains the specific instructions on how to install OmegaT and run it
        for Windows, OS X, and Linux users.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The user interface</emphasis>,and<emphasis
        role="bold"> Main Menu and Keyboard Short-cuts</emphasis>: these two
        chapters will be among often read, as they explain the user interface
        of OmegaT and the functions available via the main menu and the
        keyboard shortcuts. C</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Project properties</emphasis> and<emphasis
        role="bold"> <application>OmegaT</application> Files and
        Directories:</emphasis> a project in the context of OmegaT is the
        piece of work OmegaT as a CAT tool can work on. In this chapter the
        project properties, like the source and the target languages, are
        described. The latter chapter describes different subfolders and files
        in the translation project and their role, as well as other user and
        application files, connected with OmegaT.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Editing field behaviour:</emphasis> a
        short chapter, describing how the editing of the segment being
        translated can be set up.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Working with plain text</emphasis> and
        <emphasis role="bold">Working with formatted text</emphasis>: these
        two chapters explain some important points, as regards texts to be
        translated, like the encoding set used - in the case of plain text
        files - and the tag handling - in the case of formatted text.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Translation memories: </emphasis> explains
        the role of different subdirectories that contain translation memories
        and provides information on some other important aspects connected
        with translation memories.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Segmentation</emphasis>: translation
        memory tools work with textual units called segments. In OmegaT
        segments can ntatin be either based on paragraphs - rarely used
        option, retained mainly for historical reasons - or on a rule-based
        segmentation. A number of rules is already available, however,
        additional rules can be defined by the user, as described in this
        chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Searches</emphasis>: and<emphasis
        role="bold"> </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Regular
        expressions</emphasis>: Searches in OmegaT can be as simple as
        "<emphasis>list segments containing
        <emphasis>memory</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis>". </emphasis> Or they
        can be more involved, for instance, when proofreading the target text:
        "<emphasis>list segments with target text containing two or more
        consecutive spaces</emphasis>". In the second example the regular
        expression ^s^s+ will find and list the offending segments. Regular
        expressions are extensively used also segmentation rules.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Dictionaries, Glossaries</emphasis>,
        <emphasis role="bold">Machine translation</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="bold">Spellchecker:</emphasis> OmegaT allows extensive use of
        dictionaries and glossaries. When online, different MT services, like
        Google Translate can be used. If spell checking is activated, the
        spelling mistakes are being recognized and can be corrected while
        translating the texts. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Miscellanea</emphasis>: contains different
        issues of interest, for instance how to avoid data loss and
        similar.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Appendices</emphasis> contain the
        following information</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">OmegaT on the web:</emphasis>
            information about on-line OmegaT sources</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Languages:</emphasis> contains the ISO
            list of languages and language codes</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>K<emphasis role="bold">eyboard shortcuts</emphasis>: the
            list of shortcuts used in the editor</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Legal notices</emphasis></para>

            <para><emphasis role="bold"></emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Keyword index:</emphasis> an extensive
        keyword index is provided to help the reader find the relevant
        information.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
