<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch03.user.interface">
  <title>The user interface</title>

  <section id="user.interface.items">
    <title>User interface items</title>

    <section id="windows.you.will.use.frequently">
      <title>Windows you will use frequently</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><application>OmegaT</application> main window</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>contains the main menu, status bar and several panes:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Editor - where you type and edit the translation</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Match Viewer - with the most similar segments from
                translation memories</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Glossary Viewer - with the terminology
                translation</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Dictionary Viewer - with the information , provided by
                dictionaries</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Google Translate - with the translation, provided by
                Google Translate</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Project Files window</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>with the list of your translatable files (opened with
            <keycombo>
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

                <keycap>L</keycap>
              </keycombo>, closed with <keycap>esc</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Search window</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>to search for specific segments in the project (opened with
            <keycombo>
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

                <keycap>F</keycap>
              </keycombo>, closed with <keycap>esc</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section id="windows.you.may.use.now.and.then">
      <title>Windows you may use now and then</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tag Validation window</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>to check for tag mistakes in translations (opened with
            <keycombo>
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

                <keycap>T</keycap>
              </keycombo> closed with <keycap>esc</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Help browser</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>to read the user manual, opened with <keycap>F1</keycap>,
            closed with <keycap>esc</keycap></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section id="dialogs.to.change.settings">
      <title>Dialogs you'll use to change your project settings</title>

      <para>You'll use the dialogs below to change
      <application>OmegaT</application> and project settings. All of them are
      described in separate sections, below we just summarize what they can be
      used for and how you may call them up:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Project Properties</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>to modify the project folders and languages, triggered with
            <menuchoice>
                <shortcut>
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

                    <keycap>E</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                </shortcut>

                <guimenu>Project</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>properties...</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>, closed with <keycap>esc</keycap></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Font</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>to modify the font <application>OmegaT</application> uses
            for displaying source, translation, matches and glossary terms,
            triggered with <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Font...</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>, closed with <keycap>esc</keycap></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>File filters</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>to adjust the handling of supported file formats (opened
            with <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>File Filters...</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>, closed with <keycap>esc</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Segmentation</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>n to change the way your text is segmented into sentences
            (opened with <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Segmentation</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>, closed with <keycap>esc</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Editing Behaviour</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>to change how <application>OmegaT</application> behaves when
            you iterate between the segments (opened with <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Behaviour...</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>, closed with <keycap>esc</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="OmegaT.main.window">
    <title><application>OmegaT</application> main window</title>

    <figure id="fig.omegat.main.window">
      <title><application>OmegaT</application> main window</title>

      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="images/OmegaT_panes.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Main window consists of several panes, main menu and a status
    bar.You can change the position of any pane or even undock it to a
    separate window by dragging the pane by its name. Depending on the pane
    status, different signs can appear at its top right corner:</para>

    <table>
      <title>Pane widgets</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="left" colnum="1" colwidth="60" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/Minimize.gif" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            </entry>

            <entry>minimizes the pane, so that only its name is shown at the
            bottom of the window.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/Maximize.gif" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            </entry>

            <entry>maximizes the pane, i.e. makes the pane take all the
            available window space.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/undock.gif" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            </entry>

            <entry>undocks the pane from the main window.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/dock.gif" />
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
            </entry>

            <entry>puts the pane back within the main window.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>You can make panes overlap, when necessary. In this case the panes
    will display a tab at their top. Clicking on the tab will show the pane in
    the foreground. The separators between the panes can be dragged to resize
    panes. In case you get lost, while doing changes, you can always use
    <guimenuitem>Options → Restore the main window</guimenuitem> to return to
    a sensible setup <guimenuitem>. </guimenuitem></para>

    <section id="editor.pane">
      <title>Editor pane<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Windows in OmegaT</primary>

          <secondary>Editor pane</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Here you'll type and edit the translation. Editor pane displays
      the text of the partially translated document: the text already
      translated is displayed translated, and the untranslated text is
      displayed in the original language. The displayed text is split into
      segments, and you may scroll through the document and double-click on
      any segment to edit it. In the above case the already translated
      segments are shown in yellow, but you may change the setup to suit your
      preferences (see <xref linkend="submenu.View" />).</para>

      <para>One of the segments is the active segment. It is the only one that
      is displayed in two parts: the upper part is in the original language,
      in bold characters with a green background color, the lower part is the
      editing field, delimited by two markers: the leftmost marker is
      <literal>&lt;segment nnnn&gt;</literal> where nnnn is a number of the
      segment in the project, the rightmost marker is <literal>&lt;end
      segment&gt;.</literal> You use the upper part as a reference and
      overwrite or modify the contents of the editing field with your
      translation.</para>

      <para>Depending on the editing behaviour the editing field for the
      untranslated segment may be empty, contain the source text or the
      translation of the string most similar to the one you are going to
      translate. When you move to another segment, the translation is
      validated and stored. If you want the segment to stay untranslated,
      simply make the editing field empty by removing all the text (select all
      with <guimenuitem>Ctrl+A </guimenuitem>and delete with
      <guimenuitem>Del</guimenuitem>). <application>OmegaT</application> may
      remember a translation when it is identical to the source. It is useful
      for documents that contain trade marks, names or other proper nouns, or
      parts in a third language that does not require translation. See
      Translation editing for more details.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="match.viewer">
      <title>Match viewer</title>

      <para><figure id="matches.pane">
          <title><indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Matches</primary>

              <secondary>Matches pane - figure</secondary>
            </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Windows in OmegaT</primary>

              <secondary>Matches pane - figure</secondary>
            </indexterm>Matches pane</title>

          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/MatchesPane.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>Match viewer shows the most similar segments from translation
      memories, both from project translation memory created while you
      translate your project, and from legacy translation memories you import
      from your earlier jobs, or you may receive from your client or
      translation agency.</para>

      <para>When you move to the next segment, the first fuzzy match (the one
      with the best matching percentage) is automatically selected. You may
      select another one by pressing <guimenuitem>Ctrl+2, 3, 4, or
      5</guimenuitem>. Of course, pressing <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap>5</keycap>
        </keycombo> will do nothing, if there is no match #5.To use the
      selected match in your translation, use
      <guimenuitem>Ctrl+R</guimenuitem> to replace the target field with that
      match or use <guimenuitem>Ctrl+I </guimenuitem> to insert it at the
      cursor position.</para>

      <para>The matching percentage is roughly equivalent to taking the number
      of common words in the matched and the matching segment and dividing by
      the number of words in the longest of the two. The selected fuzzy match
      will be highlighted in bold, words that are missing from the segment you
      translate will be colored in blue and word adjacent to missing parts in
      green. In the above example the source segment is <emphasis
      role="bold">Information about Java &amp;
      <application>OmegaT</application></emphasis>. The top match is 75%,
      because 3 out of 4 words (with &amp; getting ignored) match. The line
      with the matching percentage also includes to source TMX, where the
      match has been found. If there's no file name displayed, the source is
      the default project translation memory. Orphan segments (the match #4)
      describe segments in the default project translation memory without the
      corresponding source segment.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Glossary<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Windows in OmegaT</primary>

          <secondary>Glossary pane</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Glossary pane allows you to access your private collection of
      expressions and specialty terminologies, which you have accumulated in
      your glossary files. It shows translation of terms found in the current
      segment, but it only shows it for reference purposes, and does not allow
      to insert or replace the term with its translation.</para>

      <para><figure id="glossary.pane">
          <title><indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Glossaries</primary>

              <secondary>Glossary window - figure</secondary>
            </indexterm>Glossary pane</title>

          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Glossary_pane.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>The source segment in the above example was “I<emphasis>n most
      translation jobs it is considered important to have the translated
      document look similar to the original</emphasis>.”, and two words in it,
      document and translation were found in the glossary file.
      <application>OmegaT</application> also supports multi-word terms, but in
      a very basic manner: if both words of a term are found in current
      segment, the term will be displayed.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dictionaries">
      <title>Dictionaries</title>

      <para>Dictionaries are the electronic version of printed dictionaries
      like Merriam Webster, Duden, Larousse etc., you may keep on your
      desk.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Google.Translate">
      <title>Machine Translation</title>

      <para>Machine Translation pane, when opened, will contain the
      suggestions by machine translation tools for the current segment. Press
      <menuchoice>
          <shortcut>
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

              <keycap>M</keycap>
            </keycombo>
          </shortcut>
        </menuchoice>to replace the translation of the current segment with
      the suggested translation.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title id="main.menu">Main menu</title>

      <para>Obviously, you can use main menu to access all
      <application>OmegaT</application> functions. See the Main Menu appendix
      for a full description of all menu's and menu items. The most often used
      functions are accessible with keyboard shortcuts, so once you get
      accustomed to them, there will no longer be any need to browse through
      the menus while translating.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="status.bar">
      <title>Status bar</title>

      <para>The status bar displays work flow related messages at the bottom
      of the main window. This bar gives the user feedback messages about
      specific operations that are in progress. It also displays the number of
      fuzzy and glossary matches for the current segment.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="other.windows">
    <title>Other windows</title>

    <section>
      <title>Project files<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Windows in OmegaT</primary>

          <secondary>Project files</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Project Files window lists the project files and displays other
      project information. It is displayed automatically when
      <application>OmegaT</application> loads a project. To open it or bring
      it to the front use <guimenuitem>Ctrl+L</guimenuitem> and to close
      <keycap>esc</keycap>. Project Files Window dispalys the following
      information:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the list of all the translatable files in the project. These
          are the files present in the source files folder, that
          <application>OmegaT</application> can handle. Clicking on any file
          will open it for translation</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the file currently available in the Editor pane is highlighted
          with a blue background</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the number of segments in each file is shown next to file
          name.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the number of unique segments in the whole project.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the number of unique segments already translated. It is
          updated each time you translate a segment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The set of <emphasis role="bold">Unique </emphasis>segments is
      computed by taking all the segments and removing all the duplicate
      segments equal up to letter case ("Run" and "run" are thought to be
      different).</para>

      <para>The difference between "Number of segments" and "Number of unique
      segments" gives you a rough idea of the number of repetitions in the
      text. Note however, that the numbers do not say how relevant the
      repetitions are: it could mean relatively long sentences repeated a
      number of times (very lucky!) or it could describe a table of keywords
      (not as lucky...) The<filename> project_stats.txt</filename> located in
      the<filename>omegat</filename> folder of your project contains more
      detailed segment information per file.</para>

      <para>It is possible to modify the number of segments/unique segments by
      modifying the segmentation rules. This, however, should be avoided at
      all costs, once you have started translating the project. See the
      Segmentation rules for more information.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Adding files to the project: </emphasis>You
      may add source files to the project by clicking on the "Import Source
      Files..." button. It copies the selected files to the
      <filename>source</filename> folder and reloads the project to load the
      new files. You can also add source files from internet pages, written in
      MediaWiki, by clicking on "Import from MediaWiki" button and providing
      the corresponding URL.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Search window<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Windows in OmegaT</primary>

          <secondary>Search pane</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>You'll use search window to find specific segments in the project.
      There can be several search windows open simultaneously. To open a new
      one, use <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo> in main window. The search window consists of a text field
      for search string or keywords, flags and radio buttons for setting up
      the search and a display area containing the results of the search. See
      searching for more information about the search window.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tag validation<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Windows in OmegaT</primary>

          <secondary>Tag validation</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>The tag validation window detects the tag errors in the
      translation and lists them. To open the window, use <guimenuitem>Ctrl+T.
      </guimenuitem>The window features a 3 column table with a link to the
      segment and its source and target contents:</para>

      <para><figure id="tag.validator.window">
          <title><indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Tags</primary>

              <secondary>Tag validation window - figure</secondary>
            </indexterm>Tag validator window</title>

          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/TagValidator.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>The tags are highlighted in bold blue for easy comparison between
      the original and the translated contents. Click on the link to jump to
      the segment in the Editor pane. Correct the error if necessary and press
      <guimenuitem>Ctrl+T</guimenuitem> to return to the tag validation window
      to correct other errors. In the first and third case above tags are
      paired incorrectly, and in the second case the starting tag is missing
      the &lt; sign.</para>

      <para>Tag errors are tag manipulations in the translation that do not
      reproduce the same tag order and number as in the original segment. Some
      tag manipulations are necessary and are benign, some will cause problems
      when the translated document is created. Tags generally represent some
      kind of formatting in the original text. Simplifying the original text
      formating greatly contributes to reducing the number of tags.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Help browser</title>

      <para>The help browser (which displays this manual) can be called by
      pressing <keycap>F1</keycap> or calling <guimenuitem>Help → User
      Manual...</guimenuitem> in main menu.In the window you'll see the manual
      and two buttons: Back and Contents. The user manual is an HTML document
      with links to different chapters. Clicking on a link as you would do in
      a web browser brings the desired page to the front.</para>

      <para>The user manual is located in the docs subfolder under the
      <application>OmegaT</application> installation folder, so you may view,
      for instance, English documentation, by opening the
      <filename>docs/en/index.html</filename> file in your browser. This way
      you will be able to follow external links too, as the built-in help
      browser does not accept external Internet links.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
