<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch04.project.properties">
  <title>Project properties<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Project</primary>
      <secondary>Properties</secondary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para></para>

  <section id="properties.dialog">
    <title>Properties dialog</title>

    <para>The dialog <menuchoice>
        <shortcut>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>E</keycap>
          </keycombo>
        </shortcut>

        <guimenu>Project</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Properties...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> is used to modify the project folders and languages. It
    contains:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Area for setting project source and target languages with
        drop-down menus</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Segmentation settings flag</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Area for setting project folders</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>All the fields are editable. You can either enter the languages by
    hand or use the drop down menu. You can type names of folders that do not
    exist yet, and <application>OmegaT</application> will create them for
    you.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="language.modification">
    <title>Modifying project properties</title>

    <para>Note that changes to the project setup may have some unintended
    consequencesm especially so, when made when the project is already on the
    way.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Changing source or target
        languages:<indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Project</primary>

            <secondary>Source and target languages</secondary>
          </indexterm></emphasis></para>

        <para>You have to bear in mind that changing the languages may render
        the currently used translation memories useless since their language
        may not match new languages anymore.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Segmentation modifications:<indexterm
            class="singular">
            <primary>Project</primary>

            <secondary>Modifying segmentation</secondary>
          </indexterm></emphasis></para>

        <para>The segmentation settings only address the way the source files
        are handled by <application>OmegaT</application>. They do not modify
        the segmentation of already existing translation memories.</para>

        <para>If you change the segmentation settings, some already translated
        segments may get split or merged. This will practically return them to
        the "untranslated" status, as they will not match segments recorded in
        the project memory anymore, even though the old and now not matching
        translation is still there.</para>

        <para><application>OmegaT</application> may upgrade old translation
        memories that did not use sentence segmentation, but not vice versa.
        If you change your mind in the middle of the translation, the
        project's translation memory will not be changed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Changing the folder structure:<indexterm
            class="singular">
            <primary>Project</primary>

            <secondary>Changing the folder structure</secondary>
          </indexterm></emphasis></para>

        <para>In case you intend to modify project folders, remember that this
        will not move the contained files from old folders to new ones. You
        risk ending up in a situation neither you or
        <application>OmegaT</application> know what the folders really mean,
        and which of them are being used</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Modifying project properties during the
        session:<indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Project</primary>

            <secondary>Modifying during the session</secondary>
          </indexterm></emphasis></para>

        <para>It is possible to modify the project properties during a
        translation session. However, the safest way is to consider all
        settings as final once the translation has started - unless of course
        you realize a major blunder has been made. See the section Preventing
        data loss for ways and mean to protect your work.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
