<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch06.translation.editing">
  <title>Editing behaviour<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Menu options</primary>

      <secondary>Editing behaviour...</secondary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>The dialog in <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

      <guimenuitem>Editing Behaviour...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> enables the user to select, how the current segment in the
  editing field is to be initialized and handled:</para>

  <figure id="editing.behaviour.options">
    <title>Editing behaviour options</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="images/EditingBehaviourOptions.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <section id="automatic.match.insertion">
    <title>Automatic match insertion<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Automatic match insertion</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>You translate your files by moving from segment to segment, editing
    each current segment in turn. When moving between segments, you may wish
    to populate the editing field with an existing translation in the fuzzy
    match pane or with the source text. In Options <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Editing Behaviour...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> <application>OmegaT</application> offers you the following
    alternatives:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>The source text</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>you can have the source text inserted automatically into the
          editing field. This is useful for texts containing many trade marks
          or other proper nouns you which must be left unchanged.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Leave the segment empty</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>OmegaT leaves the editing field blank. This option allows you
          to enter the translation without the need to remove the source text,
          thus saving you two keystrokes (<emphasis role="bold">Ctrl+A
          </emphasis>and <emphasis role="bold">Del)</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Insert the best fuzzy match</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>OmegaT inserts the translation of the string most similar to
          the current source, if it is above the similarity threshold that you
          have selected in this dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="allow.translation.equal.to.source">
    <title>Allow the translation to be equal to source<indexterm
        class="singular">
        <primary>Translation equal to source</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Documents for translation may contain trade marks, names or other
    proper nouns that will be the same in translated documents. There are two
    strategies for segments that contain only such invariable text.</para>

    <para>You can decide not to translate such segments at all. OmegaT will
    then report these segments as not translated. This is the default. The
    alternative is to enter a translation that is identical to the source
    text. OmegaT is able to recognize that you have done this. To make this
    possible, go to select <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Editing Behaviour...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> and check the box <emphasis role="bold">Allow translation
    to be equal to source</emphasis>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="export.segment.to.text.files">
    <title>Export the segment to text files<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Exporting the current segment</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>The text export function exports data from within the current
    <application>OmegaT</application> project to plain-text files. The data
    are exported when the segment is opened. The files appear in the /script
    subfolder in the OmegaT user files folder, and include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The content of the segment source text
        (<filename>source.txt</filename>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The content of the segment target text
        (<filename>target.txt</filename>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The text highlighted by the user, when
        <keycap>Ctrl-Shift-C</keycap> is pressed or <guimenuitem>Edit &gt;
        Export Selection</guimenuitem> is
        selected<filename>(selection.txt)</filename></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The content of the files is overwritten either when a new segment is
    opened (source.txt and target.txt) or when a new selection is exported
    (selection.txt). The files are unformatted plain-text files. The whole
    process can be steered and controlled via Tck/Tcl-based scripting. See
    <ulink url="http://www.omegat.org/en/howtos/text_export.html">Using the
    OmegaT text export function</ulink> for specifics, examples and
    suggestions. </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
