<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch07.plain.text">
  <title>Working with plain text<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Source files</primary>

      <secondary>Plain text files</secondary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para></para>

  <section id="default.encoding">
    <title>Default encoding<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Default encoding</primary>

        <secondary>Plain text files</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Source files</primary>

        <secondary>Default encoding</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Plain text files - in most cases with a <filename>txt</filename>
    extension - contain exclusively textual information. There is no clearly
    defined way to inform the computer which language they contain. In (very)
    simple terms, that means the computer will per default assume the text is
    written in the same language the computer itself uses.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="garbled.displays">
    <title>Garbled displays<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Garbled displays</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>If you are Russian, it is very likely that your computer works in
    Russian too: the menus are in Russian, the files you open will be in
    Russian etc. In most cases, the computer makes the right assumption
    regarding the Contents of files in general: they all contain Russian and
    nothing Russian characters could not display.</para>

    <para>Now, if you are a Russian translator who translates from Japanese,
    the Japanese files you will get, if they are plain text files, will most
    probably be considered by the computer to be files containing Russian.
    Because there is no information in the file itself that indicates to the
    computer in which language they are written. The Japanese file contents
    could be:</para>

    <para>OmegaTとは、コンピュータを利用した翻訳ツールです。</para>

    <para>Because it expects the contents to be Russian, your text editor
    could very well display it like this:</para>

    <para>OmegaTВ∆ВЌБAГRГУГsГЕБ[Г^ВрЧШЧpВµВљЦ|ЦуГcБ[ГЛВ≈ВЈБB</para>

    <para>However, it is far from Russian: it is Japanese characters wrongly
    displayed using Russian alphabet.</para>

    <para>As any other application, <application>OmegaT</application> is
    subject to this problem too. It can only assume that per default plain
    text files can be displayed using the system defaults. That works well
    when the computer works in French for instance and the files are in
    English, or when the computer is German and you deal with get Italian
    files.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="character.sets.and.encoding">
    <title>Character sets and encoding<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Character sets</primary>
		<seealso>Default encoding</seealso>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Why would that work with English and French but not with Russian and
    Japanese? Because English and French share a common character set. Namely
    <emphasis role="bold">Latin-1,</emphasis> or some variation of it. Until
    recently, Russian and Japanese have not shared any character sets. Most
    current Russian characters sets do not cover Japanese and vice versa. The
    result is what you have seen above.</para>

    <para>The Japanese client works with a Japanese computer and creates text
    files that contain Japanese. The character set selected by the client
    computer will depend on the operating system and on other settings, but it
    is highly unlikely that the chosen (Japanese) character set will be
    correctly interpreted by the Russian computer.</para>

    <para>How the textual information in the specified character set is
    physically transmitted (i.e. what are the numeric codes the computer uses
    to interpret and display text) depends on the encoding. When the computer
    reads the file, it "decodes" the information according to the encoding and
    displays it according to the character set. Roughly speaking, one encoding
    corresponds to one character set...</para>
  </section>

  <section id="OmegaT.solution">
    <title>The <application>OmegaT</application> solution<indexterm
        class="singular">
        <primary>Default encoding</primary>

        <secondary>OmegaT solution</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>There are basically three ways to address this problem in
    <application>OmegaT</application>. They all involve the application of
    file filters in the<emphasis role="bold"> Options </emphasis>menu.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Either specify the encoding for your plain text files</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>- i.e. files with <filename>.txt </filename>extension - : in
          the <emphasis role="bold">Text files </emphasis>section of the file
          filters dialog, change the <emphasis role="bold">Source File
          Encoding </emphasis>from &lt;auto&gt; to the encoding that
          corresponds to your source<filename> .txt</filename> file.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>... or change the extensions of your plain text source
        files</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>for instance from <filename>.txt </filename>to <filename>.jp
          </filename>for Japanese plain texts: in the <emphasis
          role="bold">Text files</emphasis> section of the file filters
          dialog, add new <emphasis role="bold">Source Filename
          Pattern</emphasis> (<filename>*.jp</filename> for this example) and
          select the appropriate parameters for the source and target
          encoding</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>... or change the encoding of your files to Unicode</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>open your source file in a text editor that correctly
          interprets its encoding and save the file in the "<emphasis
          role="bold">UTF-8"</emphasis> encoding. Change the file extension
          from <literal>.txt </literal>to
          <literal>.utf8.</literal><application>OmegaT</application> will
          automatically interpret the file as a UTF-8 file</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para><application>OmegaT</application> has by default the following short
    list available to make it easier for you to deal with some plain text
    files:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>.txt</literal> files are automatically (&lt;auto&gt;)
        interpreted by <application>OmegaT</application> as being encoded in
        the computer's default encoding.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>.txt1 </literal>files are files in ISO-8859-1, covering
        most <emphasis role="bold">Western Europe</emphasis>
        languages.<indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Default encoding</primary>

            <secondary>Western</secondary>
          </indexterm></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>.txt2</literal> files are files in ISO-8859-2, that
        covers most <emphasis role="bold">Central and Eastern
        Europe</emphasis> languages<indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Default encoding</primary>

            <secondary>Central and Eastern European</secondary>
          </indexterm></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>.utf8</literal> files are interpreted by
        <application>OmegaT</application> as being encoded in UTF-8 (an
        encoding that covers almost all languages in the world).<indexterm
            class="singular">
            <primary>Default encoding</primary>

            <secondary>Unicode</secondary>
          </indexterm></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You can check that yourself by selecting the item <emphasis
    role="bold">File Filters</emphasis> in the menu <emphasis
    role="bold">Options</emphasis>. For example, when you have a Czech text
    file (very probably written in the <emphasis
    role="bold">ISO-8859-2</emphasis> code) you just need to change the
    extension<literal> .txt</literal> to <literal>.txt2 </literal>and
    <application>OmegaT</application> will interpret its contents correctly.
    And of course, if you want to be on the safe side, consider converting
    this kind of files to Unicode, i.e. to the <literal>.utf8 </literal>file
    format.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
