<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch07.translation.memories">
  <title>Translation memories<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Translation memories</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section id="OmegaT.and.tmx.files">
    <title>Translation memories in OmegaT</title>

    <section id="tmx.files.location.and.purpose">
      <title>tmx folders - location and purpose</title>

      <para><application>OmegaT</application> projects can have translation
      memory files - i.e. files with the extension tmx - in four different
      places:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Translation memories</primary>

              <secondary>Subfolder omegat</secondary>

              <seealso>Project files</seealso>
            </indexterm>omegat folder</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The omegat folder contains the project_save.tmx and possibly
            a number of backup TMX files. The
            <filename>project_save.tmx</filename>file contains all the
            segments that have been recorded in memory since you started the
            project. This file always exists in the project. Its contents will
            always be sorted alphabetically by the source segment.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Translation memories</primary>

              <secondary>Project main folder</secondary>
            </indexterm>main project folder</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The main project folder contains 3 tmx files,
            <filename>project_name-omegat.tmx</filename>,
            <filename>project_name-level1.tmx</filename> and
            <filename>project_name-level2.tmx</filename> (project_name being
            the name of your project).</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The level1 file contains only textual
                information.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The level2 file encapsulates
                <application>OmegaT</application> specific tags in correct tmx
                tags so that the file can be used with its formatting
                information in a translation tool that supports tmx level 2
                memories, or <application>OmegaT</application> itself.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <application>OmegaT</application> file includes
                <application>OmegaT</application> specific formatting tags so
                that the file can be used in other
                <application>OmegaT</application> projects</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>These files are copies of the file
            <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> . i.e. of the project's main
            translation memory, excluding the so-called orphan segments. They
            carry appropriately changed names, so that its contents still
            remain identifiable, when used elsewhere, for instance in
            the<filename> tm</filename> subfolder of some other project (see
            below).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename><indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Translation memories</primary>

              <secondary>Subfolder tm</secondary>

              <seealso>Project files</seealso>
            </indexterm>tm</filename> folder</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The /tm/ folder can contain any number of ancillary
            translation memories - i.e. tmx files. Such files can be created
            in any of the three varieties indicated above. Note that other CAT
            tools can export (and import as well) tmx files, usually in all
            three forms. The best thing of course is to use OmegaT-specific
            TMX files (see above), so that the in-line formatting within the
            segment is retained.</para>

            <para>The contents of translation memories in the tm subfolder
            serve to generate suggestions for the text(s) to be translated.
            Any text, already translated and stored in those files, will
            appear among the fuzzy matches, if it is sufficiently similar to
            the text currently being translated.</para>

            <para>If the source segment in one of the ancillary TMs is
            identical to the text being translated, OmegaT acts as defined in
            the <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

                <guimenuitem>Editing Behavior...</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> dialogue window. For instance (if the default is
            accepted), the translation from the ancillary TM is accepted and
            prefixed with<emphasis> [fuzzy]</emphasis>, so that the translator
            can review the translations at a later stage and check whether the
            segments tagged this way, have been translated correctly (see the
            <link linkend="ch06.translation.editing">Editing behavior</link>
            chapter) <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>.</guimenu>
              </menuchoice></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Translation memories</primary>

              <secondary>Subfolder tm/auto</secondary>

              <seealso>Project files</seealso>
            </indexterm>tm/auto folder<indexterm class="singular">
              <primary>Project</primary>

              <secondary>Pretranslation</secondary>
            </indexterm></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If it is clear from the very start, that translations in a
            given TM (or TMs) are all correct, one can put them into
            the<emphasis role="bold"> tm/auto</emphasis> folder and avoid
            confirming a lot of<emphasis> [fuzzy]</emphasis> cases. This will
            effectively <emphasis role="bold">pre-translate </emphasis>the
            source text: all the segments in the source text, for which
            translations can be found in those "auto" TMs, will land in the
            main TM of the project without any user intervention.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Optionally, you can let <application>OmegaT</application> have an
      additional tmx file (<application>OmegaT</application>-style) anywhere
      you specify, containing all translatable segments of the project. See
      pseudo-translated memory below.</para>

      <para>Note that all the translation memories are loaded into memory when
      the project is opened. Back-ups are produced regularly of the project
      translation memory (see next chapter), and project_save.tmx is also
      saved/updated when the project is closed or loaded again. This means for
      instance that you do not need to exit a project you are currently
      working on if you decide to add another ancillary TM to it: you simply
      reload the project, and the changes you have made will be
      included.</para>

      <para>The locations of the various different translation memories for a
      given project are user-defined (see Project dialog window in <link
      linkend="Ch02.instant.start.guide">Instant start guide)</link></para>

      <para>Depending on the situation, different strategies are thus
      possible, for instance:</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">several projects on the same subject:
      </emphasis>keep the project structure, and change source and target
      directories (Source = source/order1, target = target/order1 etc). Note
      that you segments from order1, that are not present in order2 and other
      subsequent jobs, will be tagged as orphan segments; however, they will
      still be useful for getting fuzzy matches.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">several translators working on the same
      project:</emphasis> split the source files into source/Alice,
      source/Bob... and allocate them to team members (Alice, Bob ...). They
      can then create their own projects and, deliver their
      own<filename>project_save.tmx,</filename> when finished or when a given
      milestone has been reached. The <filename>project_save.tmx</filename>
      files are then collected and possible conflicts as regards terminology
      for instance get resolved. A new version of the master TM is then
      created, either to be put in team members'
      <emphasis>tm/auto</emphasis>subdirectories or to replace their
      project_save.tmx files. The team can also use the same subfolder
      structure for the target files. This allows them for instance to check
      at any moment, whether the target version for the complete project is
      still OK</para>
    </section>

    <section id="tmx.backup">
      <title>tmx backup<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Translation memories</primary>

          <secondary>Backup</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>As you translate your files, <application>OmegaT</application>
      stores your work continually in <filename>project_save.tm</filename>x in
      the project's /<filename>omegat</filename> subdirectory.</para>

      <para><application>OmegaT</application> also backups translation memory
      to <filename>project_save.tmx.YEARMMDDHHNN.bak</filename> in the same
      subfolder whenever a project is opened or reloaded. YEAR is 4-digit
      year, MM is a month, DD day of the month, HH and NN are hours and
      minutes when the previous translation memory was saved.</para>

      <para>If you believe you have lost translation data, follow the
      following procedure:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Close the project</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Rename the current <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> file
          ( e.g. to <filename>project_save.tmx.temporary</filename>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the backup translation memory that is most likely -
          e.g. the most recent one, or the last version from the day before)
          to contain the data you are looking for</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Copy it to <filename>project_save.tmx </filename></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open the project</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="tmx.files.and.language">
      <title>tmx files and language<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Translation memories</primary>

          <secondary>Language</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>tmx files contain translation units, made of a number of
      equivalent segments in several languages. A translation unit comprises
      at least two translation unit variations (tuv). Either can be used as
      the source or target.</para>

      <para>The settings in your project indicate which is the source and
      which the target language. OmegaT thus takes the tuv segments
      corresponding to the project's source and target language codes and uses
      them as the source and target segments respectively. OmegaT recognizes
      the language codes using the following two standard conventions :</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>2 letters (e.g. JA for Japanese), or</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2- or 3-letter language code followed by the 2-letter country
          code (e.g. EN-US - See <link linkend="A2.languages">Appendix B.
          Languages - ISO 639.2 code list</link> for a partial list of
          language and country codes).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the project language codes and the tmx language codes fully
      match, the segments are loaded in memory. If languages match but not the
      country, the segments still get loaded. If neither the language code not
      the country code match, the segments will be ignored.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Orphan segments<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Translation memories</primary>

          <secondary>Orphan segments</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>The file <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> contains all the
      segments that have been translated since you started the project. If you
      modify the project segmentation or delete files from the source, some
      matches may appear as <emphasis role="bold">orphan strings</emphasis> in
      the Match Viewer: such matches refer to segments that do not exist any
      more in the source documents, as they correspond to segments translated
      and recorded before the modifications took place.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="using.translation.memories.from.previous.projects">
    <title>Reusing translation memories<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Translation memories</primary>

        <secondary>Import and export</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Translation memories</primary>

        <secondary>Reusing translation memories</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Initially, that is when the project is created, the main TM of the
    project, <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> is empty. This TM gradually
    becomes filled during the translation. To speed up this process, existing
    translations can be reused. If a given sentence has already been
    translated once, and translated correctly, there is no need for it to be
    retranslated. Translation memories may also contain reference
    translations: multinational legislation, such as that of the European
    Community, is a typical example.</para>

    <para>When you create the target documents in an
    <application>OmegaT</application> project, the translation memory of the
    project is outputted in the form of three files in the root folder of your
    <application>OmegaT</application> project (see the above description). You
    can regard these three tmx files (<filename>-omegat.tmx</filename>,
    <filename>-level1.tmx</filename> and <filename>-level2.tmx</filename>) as
    an "export translation memory", i.e. as an export of your current
    project's content in bilingual form.</para>

    <para>Should you wish to reuse a translation memory from a previous
    project (for example because the new project is similar to the previous
    project, or uses terminology which might have been used before), you can
    use these translation memories as "input translation memories", i.e. for
    import into your new project. In this case, place the translation memories
    you wish to use in the <emphasis>\tm</emphasis> or
    <emphasis>\tm</emphasis>\auto folder of your new project: in the former
    case you will get hits from these translation memories in the fuzzy
    matches viewer, and in the latter case these TMs will be used to
    pre-translate your source text.</para>

    <para>By default, the \tm folder is below the project's root folder (e.g.
    ...<emphasis>\MyProject\tm</emphasis>), but you can choose a different
    folder in the project properties dialog if you wish. This is useful if you
    frequently use translation memories produced in the past, for example
    because they are on the same subject or for the same customer. In this
    case, a useful procedure would be:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a folder (a "repository folder") in a convenient location
        on your hard drive for the translation memories for a particular
        customer or subject.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Whenever you finish a project, copy one of the three "export"
        translation memory files from the root folder of the project to the
        repository folder.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>When you begin a new project on the same subject or for the same
        customer, navigate to the repository folder in the
        <guimenuitem>Project &gt; Properties &gt; Edit Project
        dialog</guimenuitem> and select it as the translation memory
        folder.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>When you begin a new project on the same subject or for the same
    customer, navigate to the repository folder in the <guilabel>Project &gt;
    Properties &gt; Edit Project</guilabel> dialog and select it as the
    translation memory folder. Note that all the tmx files in the /tm
    repository are parsed when the project is opened, so putting everything
    you possibly can there, may slow OmegaT down unnecessarily. You may even
    consider removing those that are not required any more, once you have used
    their contents to fill up the <filename>project-save.tmx
    </filename>file.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Importing and exporting translation memories</title>

      <para>OmegaT supports imported tmx versions 1.1-1.4b (both level 1 and
      level 2). This enables the translation memories produced by other tools
      to be read by OmegaT. However, OmegaT does not fully support imported
      level 2 tmx files (these store not only the translation, but also the
      formatting). Level 2 tmx files will still be imported and their textual
      content can be seen in OmegaT, but the quality of fuzzy matches will be
      somewhat lower.</para>

      <para>OmegaT follows very strict procedures when loading translation
      memory (tmx) files. If an error is found in such a file, OmegaT will
      indicate the position within the defective file at which the error is
      located.</para>

      <para>Some tools are known to produce invalid tmx files under certain
      conditions. If you wish to use such files as reference translations in
      OmegaT, they must be repaired, or OmegaT will report an error and fail
      to load them. Fixes are trivial operations and OmegaT assists
      troubleshooting with the related error message. You can ask the user
      group for advice if you have problems.</para>

      <para><application></application>OmegaT exports version 1.4 TMX files
      (both level 1 and level 2). The level 2 export is not fully compliant
      with the level 2 standard, but is sufficiently close and will generate
      correct matches in other translation memory tools supporting TMX Level
      2. If you only need textual information (and not formatting
      information), use the level 1 file that OmegaT has created.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="pseudo.translated.memory">
    <title>Pseudo-translated memory<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Translation memories</primary>

        <secondary>Pseudotranslation</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <note>
      <para>Of interest for advanced users only!</para>
    </note>

    <para>Before segments get translated, you may wish to pre-process them or
    address them in some other way than is possible with OmegaT. For example,
    if you wish to create a pseudo-translation for testing purposes, OmegaT
    enables you to create an additional tmx file that contains all segments of
    the project. The translation in this tmx can be either</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>translation equals source (default)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>translation segment is empty</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The tmx file can be given any name you specify. A pseudo-translated
    memory can be generated with the following command line parameters:</para>

    <para><literal>java -jar omegat.jar --pseudotranslatetmx=&lt;filename&gt;
    [pseudotranslatetype=[equal|empty]]</literal></para>

    <para>Replace <literal>&lt;filename&gt;</literal> with the name of the
    file you wish to create, either absolute or relative to the working
    directory (the directory you start <application>OmegaT</application>
    from).The second argument <literal>--pseudotranslatetype</literal> is
    optional. Its value is either <literal>equal</literal> (default value, for
    source=target) or <literal>empty</literal> (target segment is empty) .You
    can process the generated tmx with any tool you want. To reuse it in
    <application>OmegaT</application> rename it to <emphasis>project_save.tmx
    </emphasis>and place it in the <literal>omegat</literal>-folder of your
    project.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="upgrading.translation.memories">
    <title>Upgrading translation memories<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Translation memories</primary>

        <secondary>Upgrading to sentence segmentation</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Very early versions of <application>OmegaT</application> were
    capable of segmenting source files into paragraphs only and were
    inconsistent when numbering formatting tags in HTML and Open Document
    files. <application>OmegaT</application> 2.2 can detect and upgrade such
    tmx files on the fly to increase fuzzy matching quality and leverage your
    existing translation better, saving you the work of doing this
    manually.</para>

    <para>A project's tmx will be upgraded only once, and will be written in
    upgraded form into the <filename>project-save.tmx</filename>; legacy tmx
    files will be upgraded on the fly each time the project is loaded. Note
    that in some cases changes in file filters in
    <application>OmegaT</application> 2.2 may lead to totally different
    segmentation; as a result, you will have to upgrade your translation
    manually in such rare cases.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
