<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch08.searches">
  <title>Searches</title>

  <section id="search.window">
    <title>Search window</title>

    <figure id="text.search.window">
      <title>Text search Window</title>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/TextSearch.png" />
        </imageobject>
    </figure>

    <section>
      <title>Calling up a search</title>

      <para><application>OmegaT</application> provides a powerful range of search functions. Call up the
      Search window with <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  <keycap>F</keycap>
</keycombo> and enter the word or phrase you wish to
      search for in the Search for box. Alternatively, in the Editor window,
      select a word or phrase in the editing field (target text of the active
      segment) and hit <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  <keycap>F</keycap>
</keycombo>. The word or phrase is entered in the Search for
      box automatically in this case. Every call of the Search window creates
      its own new window. Do not forget to close them, so that they do not
      clutter your desktop.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Search location</title>

      <para>Searches occur both in the source as well as in the target section
      of the project. You may search in</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the project only (default setting)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the project as well as in the reference translation memories
          in /tm/ (check <emphasis>Search TMs)</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>a single file or a folder containing a set of files (check
          <emphasis>Search files)</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>when searching through files, <application>OmegaT</application> will restrict the search to
      files in source file formats (See <ulink
      url="05_FilesToTranslate.xml">Files to translate -> File Formats</ulink>). For
      instance, while <application>OmegaT</application> is well able to handle TMX files, it will not
      include them in the search.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="search.methoids">
    <title>Search methods</title>

    <para>Select the method using the radio buttons. You can choose between
    two methods to search:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>exact search</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for segments containing of the string you specified. An
          exact search looks for a phrase, i.e. if several words are entered,
          they are found only if they occur in exactly the same sequence.
          Exact searches are similar to an "exact phrase" search in an
          Internet search engine such as Google.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>keyword search</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for segments containing all keywords you specified, in
          any order. Select keyword search to search for any number of
          individual words, separated by spaces and in any order. <application>OmegaT</application> will
          display a list of all segments in which all the words occur. Keyword
          searches are similar to a search "with all of the words" in an
          Internet search engine such as Google (AND logic).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>For either of these two methods you can select the following three
    options:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">case sensitive</emphasis>: the search will
        be performed for the exact string specified; otherwise capitals will
        be ignored.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">regular expressions:</emphasis>The search
        string will be treated as a regular expression. In case of a keyword
        search, however, it will be treated as multiple expressions.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">search TMs</emphasis>: all translation
        memories are included in the search.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="using.wild.cards">
    <title>Using wild cards</title>

    <para>In both exact and keyword searches, the wild card search characters
    '*' and '?' can be used. To use wild cards, make sure the option regular
    expressions is not selected, otherwise these characters are interpreted as
    special regular expression characters.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'*' matches zero or more characters. The search term<literal>
        'run*' </literal>for example would match <literal>'run', 'runs',
        </literal>and <literal>'running'.</literal></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'?' matches any single character. For instance, <literal>'run?'
        </literal>would match<literal> 'runs'</literal> and
        '<literal>rung'</literal>, but not <literal>'run' </literal>or
        '<literal>running'.</literal></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="using.regular.expressions">
    <title>Using regular expressions</title>

    <para>A regular expression search is a powerful way to look for instances
    of a string. It is similar to a wild card search, but allows far more
    flexibility. The regular expressions used in searches are those supported
    by Java. See more in the chapter on Regular expressions.</para>

    <para>You can find simple tutorials on the web, for example <ulink
    url="http://www.regular-expressions.info/quickstart.html">here.</ulink></para>
  </section>

  <section id="search.result.display">
    <title>Search results display</title>

    <para>Pressing the search button after entering a string in the search
    field will display all the segments in the project that include the
    searched string. As <application>OmegaT</application> handles identical segments as one single
    entity, only the first unique segment is shown.</para>

    <para>The segments are displayed in order of appearance in the project.
    Translated segments will be displayed with the original text at the top
    and the translated text at the bottom, untranslated segments will be
    displayed as the source only.</para>

    <para>Clicking on a segment will open it in the Editor for modifications.
    You may then switch back to Search window for the next found segment, for
    instance to control and if necessary correct the terminology.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
