<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch09.searches">
  <title>Searches<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Searches</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section id="search.window">
    <title>Search window</title>

    <figure id="text.search.window">
      <title>Text search Window<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Search window</primary>

          <secondary>Example</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/TextSearch.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <note>
      <para>The above search finds all target segments where two or more white
      spaces - \s\s+ - occur.</para>
    </note>

    <section>
      <title>Calling up a search<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Shortcuts</primary>

          <secondary>Ctrl+F - Search</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para><application>OmegaT</application> provides a powerful range of
      search functions. Call up the Search window with <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo> and enter the word or phrase you wish to search for in the
      Search for box. Alternatively, in the Editor window, select a word or
      phrase in the editing field (target text of the current segment) and hit
      <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo>. The word or phrase is entered in the Search for box
      automatically in this case. You can have several Search windows open at
      the same time, but close them when no longer needed so that they do not
      clutter your desktop.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Search location</title>

      <para>Searches are performed by default in both the source and target
      sections of the project, but you can configure your search to select in
      the source or the target text only. You may search in</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the project only (default setting)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>both the project and the reference translation memories in
          /tm/ (check <emphasis>Search TMs)</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>a single file or a folder containing a set of files (check
          <emphasis>Search files)</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>When searching through files (as opposed to translation
      memories),<application>OmegaT</application> restricts the search to
      files in source file formats (See <ulink
      url="05_FilesToTranslate.xml">Files to translate -&gt; File
      Formats</ulink>). Consequently, although OmegaT is quite able to
      handle<filename> tmx</filename> files, it does not include them in the
      Search files search. If you turn on <emphasis role="bold"><indexterm
          class="singular">
          <primary>Searches</primary>

          <secondary>Advanced Options</secondary>
        </indexterm>Advanced Options</emphasis>, you can combine the search
      with the name of the author of the translation and time of the last
      change made.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="using.wild.cards">
    <title>Using wild cards<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Searches</primary>

        <secondary>Using wild cards</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>In both exact and keyword searches, the wild card search characters
    '*' and '?' can be used. To use wild cards, the regular expressions option
    should not be selected, because '*' and '?' have special meaning in
    regulars.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'*' matches zero or more characters, from the current position
        in a given word to its end. The search term<literal> 'run*'
        </literal>for example would match words <literal>'run', 'runs',
        </literal>and <literal>'running'. </literal></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'?' matches any single character. For instance, <literal>'run?'
        </literal>would match<literal> the word 'runs'</literal> and
        '<literal>runn'</literal> in the word
        '<literal>running'.</literal></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The matches will be displayed in bold blue. </para>
  </section>

  <section id="search.methoids">
    <title>Search methods<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Searches</primary>

        <secondary>Methods</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Select the method using the radio buttons. You can choose between
    two methods to search:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>exact search</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for segments containing the string you specified. An
          exact search looks for a phrase, i.e. if several words are entered,
          they are found only if they occur in exactly the same sequence.
          Searching for <literal>open file</literal> will thus find all
          occurences of the string <emphasis><literal>open
          file</literal></emphasis>, but not <emphasis><literal>file
          opened</literal></emphasis> or <emphasis><literal>open input
          file</literal>.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>keyword search</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for segments containing all keywords you specified, in
          any order. Select keyword search to search for any number of
          individual full words, in any order. OmegaT displays a list of all
          segments containing all of the words specified. Keyword searches are
          similar to a search "with all of the words" in an Internet search
          engine such as Google (AND logic). Using keyword search with
          <emphasis><literal>open file</literal></emphasis> will thus find all
          occurences of the string <emphasis><literal>open
          file</literal>,</emphasis> as well as <emphasis><literal>file
          opened</literal>, <literal>open input file</literal>, <literal>file
          may not be safe to open</literal></emphasis><literal>,
          etc.</literal></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>For either of these two methods you can select the following three
    options:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">case sensitive</emphasis>: the search will
        be performed for the exact string specified; capitalization must be
        exactly as specified.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">regular expressions:</emphasis> The search
        string will be treated as a regular expression. A regular expression
        search is a powerful way to look for instances of a string. It is
        similar to a wild card search, but allows far more flexibility. The
        regular expressions used in searches are those supported by Java. See
        more in the chapter on <link linkend="ch09.regexp">Regular
        Expressions</link>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">search TMs</emphasis>: translation
        memories in the <filename>tm</filename> folder are included in the
        search.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="search.result.display">
    <title>Search results display</title>

    <para>Pressing the search button after entering a string in the search
    field displays all the segments in the project that include the searched
    string. As <application>OmegaT</application> handles identical segments as
    one single entity, only the first unique segment is shown.</para>

    <para>The segments are displayed in order of appearance in the project.
    Translated segments are displayed with the original text at the top and
    the translated text at the bottom, untranslated segments are displayed as
    the source only.</para>

    <para>Clicking on a segment opens it in the Editor for modifications. You
    can then switch back to the Search window for the next segment found, for
    instance to check and if necessary correct the terminology.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
