<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch10.glossaries">
  <title>Glossaries<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Windows and panes in OmegaT</primary>

      <secondary>Glossary pane</secondary>
    </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Glossaries</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>Glossaries are files created and updated manually for use in
  <application>OmegaT</application>.</para>

  <para>If an <application>OmegaT</application> project contains one or more
  glossaries, any terms in the glossary which are also found in the current
  segment will be automatically displayed in the Glossary viewer.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>To use an existing glossary, simply place it in the<indexterm
        class="singular">
        <primary>Project files</primary>

        <secondary>Glossary subfolder</secondary>
      </indexterm> <filename>/glossary </filename>folder after creating the
    project. <application>OmegaT</application> automatically detects glossary
    files in this folder when a project is opened. Terms in the current
    segment which <application>OmegaT</application> finds in the glossary
    file(s) are displayed in the Glossary pane:</para>

    <indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Glossary pane</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>Glossary pane</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../../OmegaT/doc_src/en/images/Glossary_pane.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The word before the = sign is the source term, and its translation
    is (or are) the words behind =. The vocabulary entry can have a comment
    added (see "transitive verb" for the second item). The glossary function
    only finds exact matches with the glossary entry (e.g. does not find
    inflected forms etc.). New terms can be added manually to the glossary
    file(s) during translation (for example in a text editor), but newly added
    terms will not be recognized until the project is reloaded.</para>

    <para>The source term does not have to be a single-word item, as the next
    example shows:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>multiple words entries in glossaries - example<indexterm
          class="singular">
          <primary>Glossary pane - multiple-words entries</primary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../../OmegaT/doc_src/en/images/MultiTerm_Glossary.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The underlined item "new preview screenshot", consists of three
    words and can be found in the glossary pane as "nov predogled posnetka
    zaslona". Note that parts of the multi-term items ("preview" in the above
    example</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>File format</secondary>
      </indexterm>File format<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Project files</primary>

        <secondary>User files</secondary>

        <seealso>Glossaries</seealso>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Glossary files are simply plain text files containing three-column,
    tab-delimited lists with the source and target terms in the first and
    second columns respectively. The third column can be used for additional
    information. Glossary files can be either in system default encoding (and
    indicated by the extension .tab) or in UTF-8 (the extension .utf8). The
    Unicode encoding (UTF8) is to be preferred for obvious reasons.</para>

    <para>Also supported is the CSV format. The format is the same as the tab
    separated one: source term, target term, comment Fields are separated by a
    comma ','. Strings can be enclosed by quotes ", which allows having a
    comma inside a string:</para>

    <para><literal>"This is a source term, which contains a comma",c'est un
    terme cible,this is a comment</literal></para>

    <para>Additional to the plain text format, TBX format is also supported.
    TBX - Term Base eXchange (TBX) is the open, XML-based standard for
    exchanging structured terminological data that has been approved as an
    international standard by LISA and ISO. If you have an existing
    terminology handling system - MultiTerm for example - It is quite possible
    it offers the export of terminology data via TBX format.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to create glossaries<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>Creating a glossary</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>The method here is foolproof, when followed in a reasonably careful
    fashion. You need OpenOffice.org Writer for it, so - if you haven't
    already done so - download and install OpenOffice.org. Launch
    OpenOffice.org and open a new text document or launch "OpenOffice.org
    Writer".</para>

    <para>In the empty document, enter your glossary terms as follows: a
    source-language term, tab space, the target-language term , tab space, a
    comment or explanation for the item, and a Return. Tab space is the
    tabulator key on the left hand side of the keyboard. If you do not wish to
    add any comments, you can drop the second tab space. A "term" can be a
    single word or a whole phrase. On the second line, enter the second term
    and its translation.</para>

    <para>When you have finished entering the terms, you will have two
    "columns" of terms, source-language terms on the left and their
    target-language terms on the right, and possibly a third column,
    containing you comments and explanations, The tab space (→ in the example
    below) and Enter (¶ ) characters can be made visible by clicking on the ¶
    icon in the Writer's Standard writer bar. Here's a few lines of an English
    -German glossary)</para>

    <para><literal> word →Wort→das (-/e/s, Wörter/-e)</literal></para>

    <para><literal> small house→Häuschen→das, (pl Häuschen)¶</literal></para>

    <para><literal> dog →Hund→m, f Hündin ¶</literal></para>

    <para><literal> horse→Pferd→n, m Hengst f Stute n Fohlen</literal>¶</para>

    <para>Do NOT use OpenOffice.org's "columns" function to create columns:
    just separate each source and target-language term pair with a single tab
    space.</para>

    <para>When you are finished with the entries, save file as Unicode-encoded
    file as follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select<literal> File &gt; Save As</literal></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the <emphasis>"File location"</emphasis> box, enter the name
        for your glossary file.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>For "Filter", select "<emphasis>Text Encoded
        (.txt.)</emphasis>"</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>make sure "<emphasis>Automatic file name extension</emphasis>"
        and <emphasis>"Edit filter settings". </emphasis>are unchecked.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="../../../OmegaT/doc_src/en/images/saveglossary.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Confirm with OK.</para>

    <para>After creating an <application>OmegaT</application> project, copy or
    move this file into the project's \glossary folder. If the project is
    already open, reload it after copying the glossary file. You can make
    changes to a glossary file whilst it is being used in project. Glossary
    changes are being detected approximately once every second and
    modifications loaded transparently in the background, so there's no need
    to reload the project after saving the new glossary file.</para>

    <para>When a segment containing a source-text term is opened, the glossary
    pane will display glossary entries for those items in the source segment
    that can be found in the glossary (or glossaries - you can have more than
    one available, and they can be stored in subfolders of <emphasis>glossary
    </emphasis>as well).</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note: </emphasis>Of course there's other ways
    and means to create a simple file with tab delimited entries, and they are
    all simpler, a lot of them much simpler, than the above suggestion. For
    instance, one can export the contents above as a <filename>CSV</filename>,
    instead of a <filename>UTF8</filename> text file. Note, however, that the
    above suggestion works for any target system, be it Windows, OS X or
    Linux. Nothing speaks against using Notepad++ on Windows or GEdit on Linux
    for instance: any text editor, that is knowledgeable about UTF8 and that
    can show white space, so that you do not miss the required
    <keycap>TAB</keycap> characters can be used.</para>

    <para>The contents of glossary files are kept in the memory and get
    loaded, when the project gets opened or reloaded. Updating of a glossary
    file is thus rather simple:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>keep the file opened in your selected editor</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>When you hit upon a new term, worth entering, enter the new
        term, its translation and any comments you may have (making sure, you
        press tab between the fields) and save the file. The contents of the
        glossary pane will be updated accordingly.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>Trados MultiTerm</secondary>
      </indexterm>Using Trados Multiterm</title>

    <para>Data exported from Trados MultiTerm can be used as
    <application>OmegaT</application> glossaries without further modification,
    provided they are given the file extension <filename>.tab </filename>and
    the source and target term fields are the first two fields
    respectively.</para>

    <para>If you export using the system option "Tab-delimited export", you
    will need to delete the first 5 columns (Seq. Nr, Date created etc). The
    newer versions of MultiTerm support export in TBX format..</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>Problems with glossaries</secondary>
      </indexterm>Common glossary problems</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Problem: No glossary terms are displayed -
    possible causes:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>No glossary file found in the "glossary" folder.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The glossary file is empty.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The items are not separated with a TAB character.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The glossary file does not have the correct extension (.tab or
        .utf8).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>There is no EXACT match between the glossary entry and the
        source text in your document - for instance when the item is in
        plural.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the glossary file does not have the correct encoding.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>There are no terms in the current segment which match any terms
        in the glossary.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One or more of the above problems may have been fixed, but the
        project has not been reloaded.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Problem: In the glossary pane, some characters
    are not displayed properly</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>...but the same characters are displayed properly in the Editing
        pane: the extension and the file encoding do not match.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
