<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch11.google.granslate">
  <title>Google Translate</title>

  <section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Google Translate is the service offered by Google, to translate
    sentences, web sites and complete texts between an ever-growing number of
    languages. At the time of writing the list includes more than 50
    languages, from Albanian to Yiddish, including of course all the major
    languages (see Languages available for translation). It's translation
    produced by state-of-the-art technology, without the intervention of human
    translators. Google's research group has developed its own statistical
    translation system for the language pairs now available on Google
    Translate. As opposed to user-generated translation memories on one side
    (like in the case of <application>OmegaT</application>) or rule-based systems (usually found under
    the name of "machine translation" or MT in short) Google can afford a
    different approach: they feed the computer billions of words of text, both
    monolingual text in the target language, and aligned text consisting of
    examples of human translations between the languages. Statistical learning
    techniques are then applied to build a translation model, achieving very
    good results in research evaluations.</para>

    <para>The quality of the translation of course depends on one side on the
    reservoir of target-language texts and the availability of their bilingual
    versions, on the other hand on the quality of the models built. It is
    pretty much certain that while the quality may be insufficient in some
    cases, it will definitely get better with time and not worse. Even today's
    most sophisticated software, however, doesn't approach the fluency of a
    native speaker or possess the skill of a professional translator.
    Automatic translation is very difficult due to context problems (the
    sentence "Time flies like an arrow" being just the best known example for
    it), it may be some time before anyone can offer human quality
    translations.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><application>OmegaT</application> user and Google Translate</title>

    <para>The <application>OmegaT</application> user is not forced to use Google Translate. If used,
    neither the user's decision to accept the translation nor the final
    translation are made available to Google. The following window shows an
    example of a) the English source b) Spanish and c) Slovenian Google
    Translate translation.</para>

    <figure id="moby.dick">
	<title>Google Translate - example</title>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/MobyDick.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Spanish translation is better than the Slovenian. Note
    <emphasis>interesar</emphasis> and<emphasis> navegar</emphasis> in
    Spanish, translating the verbs interest and sail correctly. In the
    Slovenian version both words have been translated as nouns. Remember
    however, that the difference is solely due to the fact that there's far
    more bilingual material available for the Spanish language than there is
    for Slovenian.</para>

    <para>From now on a suggestion for the translation will appear in the
    Google Translate pane for every new source segment opened. If you find the
    suggestion acceptable, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  <keycap>M</keycap>
</keycombo> to replace the target part of the opened segment with the suggestion. In the above segment, for
    instance, <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  <keycap>F</keycap>
</keycombo> would overwrite the Spanish
    version with the Slovenian suggestion.</para>

    <para>If you do not want <application>OmegaT</application> to send your source segments to Google to
    get translated, uncheck the Google Translate menu entry in Options.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Google.Translate.troubleshooting">
    <title>Google Translate trouble shooting</title>

    <para>If there's nothing appearing in the Google Translate pane, then
    check the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Are you online? You need to be online to be able to use Google
        Translate.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What is the source language? Google Translate may not as yet be
        able to offer its services for it.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Check Google Translate online for your language pair. Does it
        work</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
