<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch11.google.granslate">
  <title>Machine Translation<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Machine Translation</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>As opposed to user-generated translation memories on one side (like
    in the case of <application>OmegaT</application>) Machine translation
    tools use rule-based linguistic tools to create a translation of the
    source segment. Statistical learning techniques, based on source and
    target texts, can then be applied to build a translation model, achieving
    very good results in research evaluations. Even today's most sophisticated
    software, however, doesn't approach the fluency of a native speaker or
    possess the skill of a professional translator. Automatic translation is
    very difficult due to context problems (the sentence "Time flies like an
    arrow" being just the best known example for it), it may be some time
    before anyone can offer human quality translations.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="introduction">
    <title>Google Translate<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Google Translate</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Google Translate is the service offered by Google, to translate
    sentences, web sites and complete texts between an ever-growing number of
    languages. At the time of writing the list includes more than 50
    languages, from Albanian to Yiddish, including of course all the major
    languages (see Languages available for translation). It's translation
    produced by state-of-the-art technology, without the intervention of human
    translators. Google's research group has developed its own statistical
    translation system for the language pairs now available on Google
    Translate.</para>

    <para>The quality of the translation of course depends on one side on the
    reservoir of target-language texts and the availability of their bilingual
    versions, on the other hand on the quality of the models built. It is
    pretty much certain that while the quality may be insufficient in some
    cases, it will definitely get better with time and not worse.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><application>OmegaT</application> user and Google Translate</title>

    <para>The <application>OmegaT</application> user is not forced to use
    Google Translate. If used, neither the user's decision to accept the
    translation nor the final translation are made available to Google. The
    following window shows an example of a) the English source b) Spanish and
    c) Slovenian Google Translate translation.</para>

    <figure id="moby.dick">
      <title>Google Translate - example</title>

      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/MobyDick.png" width = "60%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="images/MobyDick.png" width = "40%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Spanish translation is better than the Slovenian. Note
    <emphasis>interesar</emphasis> and<emphasis> navegar</emphasis> in
    Spanish, translating the verbs interest and sail correctly. In the
    Slovenian version both words have been translated as nouns. It is actually
    quite probable, that the Spanish translation is based at least partially
    on the actual translation of the book.</para>

    <para>From now on a suggestion for the translation will appear in the
    Google Translate pane for every new source segment opened. If you find the
    suggestion acceptable, press <keycombo>
        <keycap><indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Shortcuts</primary>

            <secondary>Ctrl+M - Machine Translate</secondary>
          </indexterm>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>M</keycap>
      </keycombo> to replace the target part of the opened segment with the
    suggestion. In the above segment, for instance, <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>M</keycap>
      </keycombo> would overwrite the Spanish version with the Slovenian
    suggestion.</para>

    <para>If you do not want <application>OmegaT</application> to send your
    source segments to Google to get translated, uncheck the Google Translate
    menu entry in Options.</para>

    <para>Note that nothing but your source segment is sent to the MT service.
    On-line version of Google Translate allows the user to correct the
    suggestion and send the corrected segment in. This feature, however, is
    not implemented in OmegaT.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Belazar<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Belazar</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Machine language translation tool for the Russian-Belarusian
    language pair.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Apertium<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Apertium</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Apertium is a free/open-source machine translation platform,
    initially aimed at related-language pairs,like CA, ES, GA, PT, OC and FR
    but recently expanded to deal with more divergent language pairs (such as
    English-Catalan). Check the web site for the latest list of implemented
    language pairs. </para>

    <para>The platform provides </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>a language-independent machine translation engine</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>tools to manage the linguistic data necessary to build a machine
        translation system for a given language pair and</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>linguistic data for a growing number of language pairs</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Apertium uses a shallow-transfer machine translation engine which
    processes the input text in stages, as in an assembly line: de-formatting,
    morphological analysis, part-of-speech disambiguation, shallow structural
    transfer, lexical transfer, morphological generation, and re-formatting.
    </para>

    <para>The initial design was largely based upon that of systems already
    developed by the Transducens group at the Universitat d'Alacant, such as
    interNOSTRUM (Spanish-Catalan), and Traductor Universia
    (Spanish-Portuguese). </para>

    <para>It is possible to use Apertium to build machine translation systems
    for a variety of language pairs; to that end, Apertium uses simple
    XML-based standard formats to encode the linguistic data needed (either by
    hand or by converting existing data), which are compiled using the
    provided tools into the high-speed formats used by the engine.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Google.Translate.troubleshooting">
    <title>Machine translation - trouble shooting<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Troubleshooting</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>If there's nothing appearing in the Google Translate pane, then
    check the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Are you online? You need to be online to be able to use a MT
        tool..</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What is the language pair you need? It could be that the
        selected service does not offer it. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist></itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
