<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch11.google.translate">
  <title>Machine Translation<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Machine Translation</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>As opposed to user-generated translation memories (as in the case of
    <application>OmegaT</application>) Machine translation (MT) tools use
    rule-based linguistic tools to create a translation of the source segment
    without the need for a translation memory. Statistical learning
    techniques, based on source and target texts, are used to build a
    translation model. Machine translation services have been achieving good
    and steadfastly improving results in research evaluations.</para>

    <para>To activate any of the Machine Translation services, go to
    <guimenuitem>Options &gt; Machine Translate ... </guimenuitem> and
    activate the service desired. Note that they are all web-based: you will
    have to be on-line if you want to use them.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="introduction">
    <title>Google Translate<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Google Translate</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Google Translate is the service offered by Google, for translating
    sentences, web sites and complete texts between an ever-growing number of
    languages. At the time of writing the list includes more than 50
    languages, from Albanian to Yiddish, including of course all the major
    languages.</para>

    <para>The quality of the translation, of course, depends on one side on
    the reservoir of target-language texts and the availability of their
    bilingual versions, on the other hand on the quality of the models built.
    It is pretty much certain that while the quality may be insufficient in
    some cases, it will definitely get better with time and not worse.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><application>OmegaT</application> users and Google
    Translate</title>

    <para>The <application>OmegaT</application> user is not forced to use
    Google Translate. If used, neither the user's decision to accept the
    translation nor the final translation are made available to Google. The
    following window shows an example of a) the English source b) Spanish and
    c) Slovenian Google Translate translation.</para>

    <figure id="moby.dick">
      <title>Google Translate - example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/MobyDick.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/MobyDick.png" width="60%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Spanish translation is better than the Slovenian. Note
    <emphasis>interesar</emphasis> and<emphasis> navegar</emphasis> in
    Spanish, are correctly translated as the verbs interest and sail
    respectively. In the Slovenian version both words have been translated as
    nouns. It is actually quite probable that the Spanish translation is based
    at least partially on the actual translation of the book.</para>

    <para>Once you have activated the service, a suggestion for the
    translation will appear in the Google Translate pane every time a new
    source segment is opened. If you find the suggestion acceptable, press
    <keycombo>
        <keycap><indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Shortcuts</primary>

            <secondary>Ctrl+M - Machine Translate</secondary>
          </indexterm>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>M</keycap>
      </keycombo> to replace the target part of the opened segment with the
    suggestion. In the above segment, for instance, <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>M</keycap>
      </keycombo> would replace the Spanish version with the Slovenian
    suggestion.</para>

    <para>If you do not wish <application>OmegaT</application> to send your
    source segments to Google to get translated, untick the Google Translate
    menu entry in Options.</para>

    <para>Note that nothing but your source segment is sent to the MT service.
    The online version of Google Translate allows the user to correct the
    suggestion and send the corrected segment in. This feature, however, is
    not implemented in OmegaT.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Belazar<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Belazar</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><ulink url="http://belsoft.tut.by/belazar/">Belazar</ulink> is a
    Machine language translation tool for the Russian-Belarusian language
    pair.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Apertium<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Apertium</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><ulink url="???">Apertium</ulink> is a free/open-source machine
    translation platform, initially aimed at related-language pairs,like CA,
    ES, GA, PT, OC and FR but recently expanded to deal with more divergent
    language pairs (such as English-Catalan). Check the web site for the
    latest list of implemented language pairs.</para>

    <para>The platform provides</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>a language-independent machine translation engine</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>tools to manage the linguistic data necessary to build a machine
        translation system for a given language pair and</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>linguistic data for a growing number of language pairs</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Apertium uses a shallow-transfer machine translation engine which
    processes the input text in stages, as in an assembly line: de-formatting,
    morphological analysis, part-of-speech disambiguation, shallow structural
    transfer, lexical transfer, morphological generation, and
    re-formatting.</para>

    <para>It is possible to use Apertium to build machine translation systems
    for a variety of language pairs; to that end, Apertium uses simple
    XML-based standard formats to encode the linguistic data needed (either by
    hand or by converting existing data), which are compiled using the
    provided tools into the high-speed formats used by the engine.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Google.Translate.troubleshooting">
    <title>Machine translation - trouble shooting<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Machine Translation</primary>

        <secondary>Troubleshooting</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>If there's nothing appearing in the Google Translate pane, then
    check the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Are you online? You need to be online to be able to use an MT
        tool.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What is the language pair you need? Check if the selected
        service offers it.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
