<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"file:///C:/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch12.spellchecker">
  <title>Spell checker<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Spell checker</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>To correct the spelling mistakes during the translation, the spell
  checker can be installed and used to indicate words in the target text, that
  need to be corrected. This should come as no surprise:
  <application>OmegaT</application> uses the <ulink
  url="http://hunspell.sourceforge.net/">Hunspell</ulink> spell checker, used
  among others in OpenOffice.org, Firefox and Thunderbird. If you use any of
  these programs, you may already have the essentials of the spell checker
  installed and just need to get <application>OmegaT</application>
  connected.</para>

  <para>Once the spell checker has been activated and the vocabulary for the
  target language is available, the spell checker will monitor target
  segments, that are being displayed in the editing pane. Questionable words
  get underlined in wiggly red:</para>

  <figure id="spellchecker.in.action">
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Spell checker</primary>

        <secondary>Spell checker - figure</secondary>
      </indexterm>Spellchecker in action</title>

    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/SpellcheckingText.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/SpellcheckingText.png" width = "40%"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Right clicking on a highlighted word (<emphasis>Artund</emphasis>
  above) opens a drop-down menu, where the suggestions for the correction are
  listed (Art und) . Additionally you can ask the spell checker to <emphasis
  role="bold">ignore all</emphasis> the occurrences of the word or <emphasis
  role="bold">add</emphasis> it <emphasis role="bold">to the
  dictionary</emphasis>. Note that this is an online spell checker: if you
  have to do a global spell check of texts you will have to browse through the
  text yourself and watch for wiggly lines. The alternative is to spell check
  the target files with an editor, in other words outside of
  <application>OmegaT</application> so the changes you may make will not be in
  the translation memory.</para>

  <section id="spellchecker.options">
    <title>Spell checker options<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Spell checker</primary>

        <secondary>Installing</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Clicking on <guisubmenu><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Menu Options</primary>

        <secondary>Spell checking...</secondary>
      </indexterm>Options &gt; Spell checking...</guisubmenu> will open the
    window below:</para>

    <figure id="spellchecker.setup">
      <title>Spellchecker setup</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/SpellcheckerSetup2.png" /> 
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/SpellcheckerSetup2.png" width = "40%"/>
          </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The above example contains already the available vocabularies.
    Initially it will be unpopulated as you need to specify where
    <application>OmegaT</application> should look for the vocabularies. Click
    on <emphasis role="bold">Choose...</emphasis> to open a dialog window,
    where you can select a subfolder with existing OpenOffice.org or Mozilla
    vocabularies. The simplest way find them is to look for files with an
    extensions <emphasis>aff </emphasis>or <emphasis>dic</emphasis>.
    <application>OmegaT</application> will recognize all valid dictionaries
    available at that location and display them. If the dictionary you want to
    use is already there and visible to <application>OmegaT</application>,
    you're done.</para>

    <para>If there's no dictionaries to be found, you can select an
    appropriate place for them and then click <emphasis role="bold">Install
    </emphasis>to let <application>OmegaT</application> look for available
    vocabularies. Select the vocabularies that you need in the pop-up window
    and then click <emphasis role="bold">install.</emphasis> The selected
    languages will then get installed and will eventually appear in the spell
    checker setup window (this may take a while ).</para>

    <para>Please note that the installer depends on the Internet list of
    dictionaries. In case it is out of date or does not include the desired
    language, you will have to hunt for the vocabularies yourself. The
    OpenOffice.org contains probably the largest vocabulary collection at
    <ulink
    url="http://extensions.services.openoffice.org/dictionary">OpenOffice.org
    Extensions site</ulink>. After the dictionary extension has been
    downloaded and installed, the corresponding<emphasis> aff </emphasis>and
    <emphasis>dic </emphasis>will become available. The same can be achieved
    by adding a spell checker extension to the Firefox or Thunderbird; in this
    case the spell checker files will be stored in your (Firefox or
    Thunderbird) profile.</para>

    <para>Make sure the language code of target files corresponds to the
    dictionary's language code: an FR-FR dictionary will not work with an FR
    target setting. You need to change the setting to FR-FR to have the spell
    checker recognize the correct dictionary for your target. Look for files
    with the name, indicating the language used and having extensions
    <emphasis>aff </emphasis> and <emphasis>dic.</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="hints">
    <title>Hints<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Spell checker</primary>

        <secondary>Hints</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>If the spell checker is not working, then make sure first that the
    check box "Automatically check the spelling of text" in the spell checker
    dialogue (<guisubmenu>Options &gt; Spellchecking...)</guisubmenu> has been
    checked .</para>

    <para>Check also that the target language code of your project against the
    available vocabularies in the setup window. The spell checker determines
    the language to use from the target language code: if the target language
    is Brazilian Portuguese (PT_BR), the subfolder with vocabularies must
    contain the two vocabulary files, called <emphasis>pt_br.aff</emphasis>
    and<emphasis> pt_br.dic.</emphasis></para>

    <para>In case you have a large body of text already translated, but then
    realize the target language code of the project does not match the spell
    checker's language code (you specified pt_BR as the language, but there's
    no pt_BR vocabularies, for instance) you can simply copy the two
    corresponding files and rename them (from pt_PT.arr and pt_PT.dic to
    pt._BR.arr and pt_BR.dic). Of course it is much wiser, to take a short
    break and download the correct versions of the spell checker.</para>

    <para>Note that <filename>Uninstall </filename>physically deletes the
    highlighted vocabularies. If they are part of OpenOffice.org as in the
    above case, they will disappear from that application too. If for whatever
    reason you have to do that now and again, it may make sense to copy the
    files involved to a different folder, reserved just for
    <application>OmegaT</application> purposes.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
