<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="app.bidi">
  <title id="app.bidi.title">Directional Formatting Characters</title>

  <para>Bidi control characters can be found in the menu <link
  linkend="menus.edit" endterm="menus.edit.title"/><link
  linkend="menus.edit.insert.unicode.control.character"
  endterm="menus.edit.insert.unicode.control.character.title"/> and may be used
  to:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>insert an invisible character with a certain strong directionality
	  to force a specific position for a character with weak or neutral
	  directionality</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>create an embedding which works as a sort of protective environment
	  within which text can flow in the opposite direction of the
	  segment.</para>
	</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>These control characters can change directionality but are
  invisible. Use <link linkend="menus.view" endterm="menus.view.title"/><link
  linkend="menus.view.mark.bidirectional.algorithm.control.character"
  endterm="menus.view.mark.bidirectional.algorithm.control.character.title"/> to
  see a visual hint of where these characters are inserted.</para>

  <section id="app.bidi.marks">
	<title id="app.bidi.marks.title">Marks</title>

	<para>To change the position of a character with weak or neutral
	directionality (like punctuation symbols), insert a LRM or a RLM character
	after the character, depending on the directionality of the segment:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<para>Insert a LRM after a weak-directionality character that must run
		left-to-right in a right-to-left segment (e.g. an English excerpt inside
		Arabic text)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para>Insert a RLM after a weak-directionality character that must run
		right-to-left in a left-to-right segment (e.g. an Arabic excerpt inside
		English text)</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="app.bidi.embeddings">
	<title id="app.bidi.embeddings.title">Embeddings</title>

	<para>Embeddings can be used to create a longer portion of text (containing
	several words and spaces) that must run in the opposite directionality of
	that of the segment. You can create two kinds of embeddings depending on the
	directionality of the segment:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<para>To create a left-to-right embedding in a right-to-left segment,
		insert a left-to-right embedding (LRE) character, then type or insert
		the left-to-right text, then insert the pop directional formatting (PDF)
		character.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para>To create a
  right-to-left embedding in a left-to-right segment, you would insert a
  right-to-left embedding (RLE) character, then type or insert the right-to-left
		text, then insert the PDF character.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
