<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="app.segmentation">
  <title id="app.segmentation.title">Segmentation</title>

  <section id="dialog.preferences.segmentation.setup.type">
	<title id="dialog.preferences.segmentation.setup.type.title">Paragraph or
	sentence?</title>
	
	<para>Translation memory tools work with textual units called segments. When
	a translation is entered, the segment containing the source text is stored
	with its translation in the project memory, and subsequently used to match
	other source segments in the project.</para>

	<para>Use the <link
	linkend="dialogs.project.properties.options.segmentation"
	endterm="dialogs.project.properties.options.segmentation.title"/> project
	property to select the type of segmentation.</para>

	<para>Segments are by default <emphasis role="bold">paragraphs</emphasis>
	defined by the file format itself.</para>
	
	<para>Not using <emphasis role="bold">sentence</emphasis> segmentation on a
	document is equivalent to using <emphasis>paragraph</emphasis>
	segmentation. In that case, each paragraph (as defined in the original
	document format) is displayed as a single segment, and the translator is
	free to reorganize the sentences within the segment in the
	translation.</para>
	
	<para><emphasis>Paragraph segmentation</emphasis> works well with more
	literary or creative texts, as well as, more generally, with documents for
	which translation memory matches are not so important.</para>

	<para><emphasis>Sentence segmentation</emphasis> relies on a number of
	rules (called <emphasis>segmentation rules</emphasis>) that define what
	constitutes a sentence in the source language. This setting works well
	with documents where repetitions or similar sentences are common, such as
	technical or legal documents.</para>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry id="dialogs.preferences.segmentation.setup.structure.level.segmentation">
		<term
			id="dialogs.preferences.segmentation.setup.structure.level.segmentation.title">Paragraph-Level
		segmentation</term>

		<listitem>
		  <para>OmegaT first parses the text for paragraph-level
		  segmentation. This process relies only on the structure of the source
		  file to produce segments.</para>

		  <para>For example, text files may be segmented on line breaks, empty
		  lines, or not at all. Files containing formatting (ODF, HTML, or other
		  documents) are divided at block-level (paragraph) tags. Translatable
		  object attributes in XHTML or HTML files can be extracted as separate
		  "paragraphs".</para>
		</listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry id="dialogs.preferences.segmentation.rules.sentence.level.segmentation">
        <term
			id="dialogs.preferences.segmentation.rules.sentence.level.segmentation.title">Sentence-level
        segmentation</term>

        <listitem>
		  <para>After dividing the source file into structural units, OmegaT
		  further divides those units into segments.</para>

		  <para>You can visualize segmentation as the process of moving the
		  cursor along the text, one character at a time, and looking for the
		  position where a break will occur, or where a break will not be
		  allowed.</para>

		  <para>Each time the cursor moves to the next character, OmegaT checks
		  whether:</para>
		  
		  <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			  <para>the text before the location corresponds to a <emphasis
			  role="bold">Before</emphasis> rule,</para>
			</listitem>
			
			<listitem>
			  <para>and the text after the location corresponds to the associated <emphasis
			  role="bold">After</emphasis> rule.</para>
			</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>

		  <para>If the location matches both rules, it is considered either as a
		  break, or as a non-break, depending on what the rule defined.</para>
        </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  
  <section id="dialog.preferences.segmentation.setup.scope">
	<title id="dialog.preferences.segmentation.setup.scope.title">Global or
	local?</title>

	<note>
	  <para>The same mechanisms and dialogs are used to define global and local
	  segmentation rules.</para>
	</note>

	<para>By default, segmentation settings are global and shared by all
	projects.</para>

	<para>Use the <link linkend="dialogs.project.properties.local.segmentation"
	endterm="dialogs.project.properties.local.segmentation.title"/> project
	property to limit the scope of the segmentation rules to the current
	project.</para>

	<para>You can achieve a similar result by starting OmegaT from the command
	line. See the <link linkend="launch.with.command.line"
	endterm="launch.with.command.line.title"/> how-to for details.</para>
	
	<para>If you use local rules, you can still access the global rules, but
	modifying them will have no effect on your project.</para>
  </section>


  <section id="dialog.preferences.segmentation.setup.rules.based.segmentation">
	<title id="dialog.preferences.segmentation.setup.rules.based.segmentation.title">Rules</title>
	<para>OmegaT provides predefined segmentation rules, and the translator can
	use regular expressions to modify them. See the <link linkend="app.regex"
	endterm="app.regex.title"/> appendix for details.</para>

	<para>As a reminder, rules work the following way: when a rule matches,
	OmegaT puts a marker at the match location so that rules that come after
	ignore that location. That is the reason why exception rules must come
	before segmentation rules.</para>
	
	<warning>
	  <para>If you change the segmentation while translating, you will have to
	  reload the project for the new segmentation to take effect. This will
	  split or merge some previously translated segments, which will therefore
	  no longer be considered translated. Nonetheless, their original
	  translation will still be in the project memory.</para>
	</warning>

	<table id="segmentation.simple.examples">
	  <title id="segmentation.simple.examples.title">A few simple examples</title>
      <tgroup cols="5">
		<colspec align="left" colnum="1"/>
		<colspec align="left" colnum="2"/>
		<colspec align="center" colnum="3"/>
		<colspec align="center" colnum="4"/>
		<colspec align="left" colnum="5"/>
		<thead>
          <row>
			<entry>Category</entry>
			<entry>Intention</entry>
			<entry align="center">Before</entry>
			<entry align="center">After</entry>
			<entry>Explanation</entry>
          </row>
		</thead>
		<tbody>
		  <row>
			<entry>Exception rule, box unchecked, higher in the list</entry>
			<entry>Do not segment after Ms.</entry>
			<entry align="center">Ms\.</entry>
			<entry align="center">\s</entry>
			<entry>Ms, followed by a period, followed by a
			whitespace.</entry>
		  </row>
		  <row>
			<entry>Exception rule, box unchecked, higher in the list</entry>
			<entry>Excel cells with lines breaks that do not represent
			segments</entry>
			<entry align="center">\n</entry>
			<entry align="center">.</entry>
			<entry>Line break, followed by anything.</entry>
		  </row>
		  <row>
			<entry>Break rule, box checked, lower in the list</entry>
			<entry>Start a new segment start after a period followed by a
			space, tab, or other whitespace.</entry>
			<entry align="center">\.</entry>
			<entry align="center">\s</entry>
			<entry>A period followed by a whitespace</entry>
		  </row>
		  <row>
			<entry>Break rule, box checked, lower in the list</entry>
			<entry>Start a new segment after “。” (Japanese period).</entry>
			<entry align="center">。</entry>
			<entry align="center"/>
			<entry>Note that the <literal>Pattern After</literal> field can
			be empty.</entry>
		  </row>
		</tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
  </section>
</section>
