<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="appendix.legal.notices">
  <title><indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Legal notices</primary>
    </indexterm>Legal notices</title>

  <section id="legal.notices.for.documentation">
    <title>For the documentation<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Legal notices</primary>

        <secondary>For the documentation</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright</emphasis></para>

    <para>The documentation distributed with <application>OmegaT</application>
    2.5 includes the User Manual and the readme.txt document. The
    documentation is Copyright ©2012 Vito Smolej. The author of the Chapter
    <emphasis>Learn to use OmegaT in 5 minutes!</emphasis> is Samuel Murray,
    Copyright ©2005-2012.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Distribution and
    modifications</emphasis></para>

    <para>The documentation is a free document; you can redistribute it and/or
    modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
    by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (if
    you prefer) any later version.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Warranty</emphasis></para>

    <para>The documentation is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General
    Public License for more details.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="legal.ntices.for.application">
    <title>For the application<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Legal notices</primary>

        <secondary>For the application</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"><application>OmegaT</application>
    2.5</emphasis> is Copyright © 2000-2012 Keith Godfrey, Maxym Mykhalchuk,
    Zoltan Bartko, Didier Briel, Kim Bruning, Alex Buloichik, Thomas
    Cordonnier, Sandra Jean Chua, Martin Fleurke, Phillip Hall,
    Jean-Christophe Helary, Thomas Huriaux, Hans-Peter Jacobs, Ibai Lakunza Velasco, 
    Guido Leenders, Aaron Madlon-Kay, Fabián Mandelbaum, John Moran, Arno Peters, Henry Pijffers, 
    Briac Pilpré, Tiago Saboga, Andrzej Sawuła, Benjamin Siband, Yu Tang, Rashid Umarov, Antonio
    Vilei, Martin Wunderlich and Michael Zakharov.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Distribution and
    modifications</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">O</emphasis><emphasis role="bold">megaT
    2.5</emphasis> is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
    Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (if you prefer)
    any later version.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Warranty</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"> <application>OmegaT</application> 2.5
    </emphasis>is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
    ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
    more detail.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
