<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="appendix.ScriptingPlugin.inOmegaT">
  <title>Scripting plugin<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Plugins</primary>

      <secondary>Scripting</secondary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>OmegaT-Scripting allows to run scripts written in different
    scripting languages in OmegaT.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installation and Use</title>

    <para>The Scripting plugin for OmegaT can be downloaded from the <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/omegat-plugins/files">OmegaT plugins
    download site</ulink>. Unzip the files, and put them all in the "plugins"
    folder located in OmegaT installation folder, that is the folder that
    contains the OmegaT.jar. Create the "plugins" folder first, if it does not
    exist.</para>

    <para>This adds a new submenu<guisubmenu> Tools &gt;
    </guisubmenu><guisubmenu>Scripting.</guisubmenu> Below the
    <guisubmenu>Scripting</guisubmenu> submenu , there's five place holders
    available for scripts. Clicking <guisubmenu>Scripting</guisubmenu> opens
    the Scripting dialog:<screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Scripting dialog</screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/ScriptingDialog.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>

    <para>The Scripting dialog allows you to load an existing script into the
    text area and run it against the current opened project. To customize the
    script feature, do the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Load a script into the editor by clicking on its name in the
        list on the left panel.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Right-click on a button from "&lt;1&gt;" to "&lt;5&gt;" in the
        bottom panel and select "Add". In the above example, two scripts
        (position 1 and 2) have already been added.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>When you left-click on the number, the selected script will run.
        You can start the selected macros from the main menu as well by using
        their entries in the <guisubmenu>Tools </guisubmenu>menu or by
        pressing<keycap> Ctrl+Alt+F#</keycap> (# 1 to 5).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following scripting languages have been implemented:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">NetRexx</emphasis>
          (http://www.netrexx.org/): it supports a classic REXX syntax, with
          no reserved keywords, along with considerable additions to support
          object-oriented programming in a manner compatible with Java's
          object model. All existing Java class libraries can be used
          unchanged and without special setup; at the same time, a Java
          programmer can opt to just use the Rexx class from the runtime
          package for improved string handling in Java syntax source
          programs.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">XSLT</emphasis> (Extensible Stylesheet
          Language Transformations): is a declarative, XML-based language used
          for the transformation of XML documents. The original document is
          not changed; rather, a new document is created based on the content
          of an existing one. The new document may be serialized (output) by
          the processor in standard XML syntax or in another format, such as
          HTML or plain text. XSLT is most often used to convert data between
          different XML schemas or to convert XML data into web pages or PDF
          documents.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Groovy</emphasis>
          (http://groovy.codehaus.org): is a dynamic language for the Java
          Virtual machine. It builds upon the strengths of Java but has
          additional power features inspired by languages like Python, Ruby
          and Smalltalk.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">JavaScript</emphasis> (sometimes
          abbreviated JS, not to be confused with Java): is a prototype-based
          scripting language that is dynamic, weakly typed and has first-class
          functions. It is a multi-paradigm language, supporting
          object-oriented, imperative, and functional programming styles.
          Being the language behind popular software such as Firefox it is a
          familiar and preferred programming tool in the open-source
          domain.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>All the languages have access to the OmegaT object model,
    with the project as the top object. The following code snippet in groovy
    for instance scans through all the segments in all files in the current
    project and, if the translatione xists, prints out the source and the
    target of the segment:</para>

    <programlisting>    files = project.projectFiles;
    for (i in 0 ..&lt; files.size())
    {
        for (j in 0 ..&lt; files[i].entries.size())
        {
            currSegment = files[i].entries[j];
            if (project.getTranslationInfo(currSegment))
            {
                source = currSegment.getSrcText();
                target = project.getTranslationInfo(currSegment).translation;
                console.println(source + " &gt;&gt;&gt;&gt; " + target);
            }     
        }
    }</programlisting>
  </section>
</appendix>
