<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.translation.editing">
  <title>Editing behavior<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Menu</primary>

      <secondary>Options</secondary>

      <tertiary>Editing behavior...</tertiary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>The dialog in <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

      <guimenuitem>Editing Behavior...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> enables the user to select, how the current segment in the
  editing field is to be initialized and handled:</para>

  <figure id="editing.behavior.options">
    <title>Editing behavior options</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="images/EditingBehaviourOptions25.png"/>
      </imageobject>
	  <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="images/EditingBehaviourOptions25.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para/>

  <para>You translate your files by moving from segment to segment, editing
  each current segment in turn. When moving between segments, you may wish to
  populate the editing field with an existing translation in the fuzzy match
  pane or with the source text. In <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

      <guimenuitem>Editing Behavior...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> <application>OmegaT</application> offers you the following
  alternatives:</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>The source text</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can have the source text inserted automatically into the
        editing field. This is useful for texts containing many trade marks or
        other proper nouns you which must be left unchanged.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Leave the segment empty<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Menu Options</primary>

          <secondary>Editing behaviour</secondary>

          <tertiary>Empty translation</tertiary>
        </indexterm></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>OmegaT leaves the editing field blank. This option allows you to
        enter the translation without the need to remove the source text, thus
        saving you two keystrokes (<emphasis role="bold">Ctrl+A </emphasis>and
        <emphasis role="bold">Del). </emphasis> Empty translations are now
        allowed. They are displayed as &lt;EMPTY&gt; in the Editor. To create
        one, right-click in a segment, and select "<emphasis role="bold">Set
        empty translation</emphasis>". The entry <emphasis role="bold">Remove
        translation</emphasis> in the same pop up menu also allows to delete
        the existing translation of the current segment. You achieve the same
        by clearing the target segment and pressing
        <guibutton>Enter.</guibutton></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Insert the best fuzzy match<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Menu Options</primary>

          <secondary>Editing behaviour</secondary>

          <tertiary>Inserting fuzzy matches</tertiary>
        </indexterm></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>OmegaT inserts the translation of the string most similar to the
        current source, if it is above the similarity threshold that you have
        selected in this dialog. The prefix (per default empty) can be used to
        tag translations, done via fuzzy matches. If you add a prefix (for
        instance [fuzzy]), you can trace those translations later to see they
        are correct.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>The check boxes in the lower half of the dialog window serve the
  following purpose:</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Attempt to convert numbers when inserting a fuzzy match<indexterm
          class="singular">
          <primary>Menu Options</primary>

          <secondary>Editing behaviour</secondary>

          <tertiary>Converting numbers</tertiary>
        </indexterm></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>If this option is checked, when a fuzzy match is inserted,
        either manually or automatically, OmegaT attempts to convert the
        numbers in the fuzzy matches according to the source contents. There
        are a number of restrictions:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The source segment and the fuzzy matches must contain the same
            list of numbers</para>
          </listitem>
        
          <listitem>
            <para>The numbers must be exactly the same between the source and the target matches.</para>
          </listitem>
        
          <listitem>
            <para>Only integers and simple floats (using the period as a decimal
            character, e.g. 5.4, but not 5,4 or 54E-01) are considered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Allow the translation to be equal to source<indexterm
          class="singular">
          <primary>Menu Options</primary>

          <secondary>Editing behaviour</secondary>

          <tertiary>Translation equal to source</tertiary>
        </indexterm></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Documents for translation may contain trade marks, names or
        other proper nouns that will be the same in translated documents.
        There are two strategies for segments that contain only such
        invariable text.</para>

        <para>You can decide not to translate such segments at all. OmegaT
        will then report these segments as not translated. This is the
        default. The alternative is to enter a translation that is identical
        to the source text. OmegaT is able to recognize that you have done
        this. To make this possible, go to <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

            <guimenuitem>Editing Behavior...</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice> and check the box <emphasis role="bold">Allow
        translation to be equal to source</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Export the segment to text files<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Menu Options</primary>

          <secondary>Editing behaviour</secondary>

          <tertiary>Exporting the current segment</tertiary>
        </indexterm></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>The text export function exports data from within the current
        <application>OmegaT</application> project to plain text files. The
        data are exported when the segment is opened. The files appear in the
        /script subfolder in the OmegaT user files folder, and include:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The content of the segment source text
            (<filename>source.txt</filename>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The content of the segment target text
            (<filename>target.txt</filename>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The text highlighted by the user, when
            <keycap>Ctrl-Shift-C</keycap> is pressed or <guimenuitem>Edit &gt;
            Export Selection</guimenuitem> is selected
            (<filename>selection.txt</filename>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The content of the files is overwritten either when a new
        segment is opened (source.txt and target.txt) or when a new selection
        is exported (selection.txt). The files are unformatted plain text
        files. The whole process can be steered and controlled via
        Tck/Tcl-based scripting. See <ulink
        url="http://www.omegat.org/en/howtos/text_export.html">Using the
        OmegaT text export function</ulink> for specifics, examples and
        suggestions.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Go To Next Untranslated Segment stops where there is at least one
      alternative translation<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Menu Options</primary>

          <secondary>Editing behaviour</secondary>

          <tertiary>Segments with alternative translation</tertiary>
        </indexterm></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>If we want to avoid any mis-translations in case of segments
        with several possible target contents, checking this check box will
        cause <emphasis role="bold"> Go To Next Untranslated
        Segment</emphasis>stop on the next such segment, irrespective of
        whether it has already been translated or not.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</chapter>
