<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.files.and.directories">
  <title><application>OmegaT</application> Files and Directories</title>

  <para><application>OmegaT</application> works with three types of
  files.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Translation project files: These constitute a translation project.
      Losing them may affect the project's integrity and your ability to
      complete a job. Project files are the most important files in
      <application>OmegaT</application>. They are the files you deal with on a
      daily basis while translating.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>User settings files: These are created when OmegaT's behavior is
      modified by user preference settings. Losing them usually results in
      OmegaT reverting to its "factory settings". This can sometimes cause a
      little trouble when you are in the middle of a translation.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Application files: These are included in the package you download.
      Most of them are required in order for OmegaT to function properly. If
      for some reason these files are lost or corrupted, simply download
      and/or reinstall OmegaT to restore them all.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section id="translation.project.files">
    <title>Translation project files</title>

    <para>An <application>OmegaT</application> translation project consists of
    a number of files and directories.</para>

    <section id="translation.project.files.location">
      <title><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>Location</secondary>
        </indexterm>Translation project files location</title>

      <para>When you create a translation project, OmegaT automatically
      creates a list of folders that will later serve as files repositories,
      and a number of files that are used to set certain project preferences
      and to hold the project translation memory. By default, a translation
      project's folders are all grouped under the main project folder.
      Alternate locations for some of the folders can be chosen at project
      creation or during the translation. It is therefore possible to select
      existing folders or create folders in locations that reflect your work
      flow and project management habits. To change the location of folders
      after a project has been created, open <guimenuitem>Project &gt;
      Properties...</guimenuitem> in the menu or with
      <guibutton>Ctrl+E</guibutton> and make the necessary changes.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="translation.project.files.list">
      <title><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>List</secondary>
        </indexterm>Translation project files list</title>

      <para>When you open a file dialog opened by
      <application>OmegaT</application>, a translation project will look like
      a file with an <application>OmegaT</application> icon associated with
      it. From within a file manager, however, a translation project looks and
      acts just like any other folder.</para>

      <figure id="OmegaT.projects.and.subdirectories">
        <title>OmegaT projects and subdirectories</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/OmegaT_projects_and_subdirectories.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Double clicking the item with the OmegaT icon is sufficient to
      open the project. A translation project <emphasis
      role="bold">Example_Project</emphasis> created with the default settings
      will be created as a new subfolder with the following structure:</para>

      <figure id="OmegaT.project">
        <title>OmegaT project</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/Omegatproject.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>All the subdirectories will be initially empty.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="folder.OmegaT">
      <title>Omegat<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>Subfolder omegat</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">omegat</emphasis> subfolder contains at
      least one and possibly several other files. The most important file is
      the translation memory file, <emphasis role="bold">project_save.tmx
      </emphasis>(...). The project_save.tmx file is the working translation
      memory for the project. With the autosave function activated, it will be
      automatically updated when you quit. It is the translation memory used
      to create the translated files. A number of TMX files with names of the
      form <emphasis role="bold">project_save.tmx.&lt;date and
      time&gt;.bak</emphasis> (...) are added progressively to this subfolder
      as the translation progresses. They serve as a backup for the project
      TM. A new one is created each time you reopen a project, thus
      reflecting its contents before the current session has changed
      them.</para>

      <para>The project <indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>statistics file</secondary>
        </indexterm><emphasis role="bold">stats.txt</emphasis> file (...)
      contains the statistics of the current project and can be opened in a
      spreadsheet application to display segment and word count information.
      The file contains the number of segments for each file to be translated
      - Total and Remaining - the number of Unique segments per file, the
      number of Unique words and the number of Unique Characters with /
      without spaces per file.</para>

      <para>Note that Unique segments per file provides the number of unique
      segments in a given file that do not appear anywhere else in the
      project. The unique words or characters per file have a similar
      definition. Note that in a multi-file project the sum of unique segments
      per file will not necessary be equal to the grand total of unique
      segments in the project.</para>

      <para>The<emphasis role="bold"> <indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>ignore_word and learned_word</secondary>
        </indexterm>Ignore_words.txt</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="bold">learned_word.txt</emphasis>files are used by the spell
      checker. Note that they are specific for a given project, so if you have
      already amassed words you wish the spell checker to ignore / accept, you
      just need to copy the corresponding two files into the 
      <filename>omegat</filename>subfolder of your current project.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="folder.source">
      <title>Source files<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>Source subfolder</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>The source subfolder is the location for project files that need
      to be translated. You can specify a new subfolder and add the files to
      it later. Note that the structure of the source subfolder may take any
      form you like. If the files to be translated are parts of a tree
      structure (as in a website), you need only specify the top-level
      subfolder and OmegaT will maintain the entire contents, while keeping
      the tree structure intact.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="folder.target">
      <title>Target files<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>Target subfolder</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>When <menuchoice>
          <shortcut>
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

              <keycap>D</keycap>
            </keycombo>
          </shortcut>

          <guimenu>Project</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Create Translated Documents</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> is selected, all the files within the
      <filename>source</filename> directory, whether translated or not, are
      reproduced in the target directory with the same folder hierarchy to
      reflect the current state of the translation. In practical terms, OmegaT
      merges the translation information saved in <emphasis
      role="bold">/omegat/project_save,tmx</emphasis> with the source
      documents to produce the target contents.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="file.omegat.project">
      <title>omegat.project<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>File omegat.project</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para><application>OmegaT</application> automatically creates this file
      when the project is created and contains the project parameters. The
      parameters included in this file can be modified from the Project
      properties window.</para>

      <para><filename>project_name-omegat.tmx (...)</filename></para>

      <para><filename>project_name-level1.tmx</filename></para>

      <para><filename>project_name-level2.tmx</filename></para>

      <indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Project files</primary>

        <secondary>Files project_name....tmx</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>These files contain the source and target segments corresponding
      to the contents of the <filename>source</filename> folder at the time of
      their creation (usually when the translated files have been created).
      They constitute the exported translation memories that you can use in
      future projects.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="user.files">
    <title>User files<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Project files</primary>

        <secondary>User files</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <section>
      <title id="user.files.location">User files location <indexterm
          class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>User files</secondary>

          <tertiary>Location</tertiary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>User files are stored in a separate location where they can be
      accessed by any version of <application>OmegaT</application>. The
      location depends upon the platform you use:</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="2" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="left" colnum="1" colwidth="100" />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Windows 2000 and XP</entry>

              <entry><literal>Documents and Settings\&lt;User
              Name&gt;\Application
              Data\<application>OmegaT</application></literal></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Windows Vista and 7</entry>

              <entry><literal>Users\&lt;User
              Name&gt;\AppData\Roaming\<application>OmegaT</application></literal></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Windows other</entry>

              <entry><literal>&lt;Something&gt;\<application>OmegaT</application></literal>
              (&lt;Something&gt; corresponds to the location of the "home"
              folder as determined by Java)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Linux/Solaris/FreeBSD</entry>

              <entry><literal>&lt;User Home&gt;/.omegat </literal>(.omegat is
              a directory, the dot preceding its name makes it invisible
              unless you type ls -a or an equivalent command)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>MAC OSX</entry>

              <entry><filename>&lt;User
              Home&gt;/Library/Preferences/<application>OmegaT</application></filename></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Other</entry>

              <entry><filename>&lt;User Home&gt;</filename></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section id="user.files.list">
      <title>User files list<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project files</primary>

          <secondary>User files list</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="2" rowsep="1">
          <colspec align="left" colnum="1" colwidth="100" />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>logs/OmegaT.log</entry>

              <entry>This file records Java error messages while
              <application>OmegaT</application> is running. Should OmegaT
              appear to be behaving erratically, it is important to include
              this file or the relevant part in any bug report</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>omegat.prefs</entry>

              <entry>An xml file with all the GUI accessible option
              settings</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>uiLayout.xml</entry>

              <entry>An xml file with window position data</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>filters.xml</entry>

              <entry>An xml file with all the data set by the file filter
              preferences</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>segmentation.conf</entry>

              <entry>An xml file containing segmentation rules</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="application.files">
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Project files</primary>

        <secondary>Application folders</secondary>
      </indexterm>Application files<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Project files</primary>

        <secondary>Application files</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>OmegaT is supplied as a package that can be downloaded from
    SourceForge. This chapter will consider the platform-independent package
    that contains the application in a standard Java form. Other packages
    include a Linux .tar package, a Windows installer – with or without a Java
    Runtime Environment –, a MacOSX installer, and a source code package for
    developers. The platform-independent package can be used on any platform
    with a working Java 1.5 runtime environment, including the platforms for
    which a specific package also exists. The platform-independent package is
    supplied as a compressed file (zip or tar archive) that you must extract
    to the folder of your choice for installation. The file can usually be
    extracted by double-clicking on the downloaded package. Once the archive
    has been extracted, a folder containing the following contents is
    created:</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup align="left" cols="2" rowsep="1">
        <colspec align="left" colnum="1" colwidth="100" />

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">File/ subfolder</emphasis></entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Contents</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>/docs/</entry>

            <entry>All the user manual files can be found in this folder. You
            can open them in An Internet browser to obtain access to external
            links.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>/images/</entry>

            <entry>Icons and logo graphics are included here.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>/lib/</entry>

            <entry>Contains Java files, necessary to the operation of
            <application>OmegaT</application>.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>join.html</entry>

            <entry>This is an ordinary html file that, when opened in your
            Internet browser, directs you to the OmegaT user group hosted on
            Yahoo Groups. Joining is not necessary, but will provide you with
            access to additional services, such as files, questionnaires, and
            the opportunity to take part in OmegaT-related discussions. The
            group archives are public and can be viewed without subscription
            to the group.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><filename>changes.txt</filename></entry>

            <entry>A relatively detailed list of modifications between this
            version and the preceding versions.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><filename>license.txt</filename></entry>

            <entry>The GNU GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE. This license allows you to
            do certain things with <application>OmegaT</application>,
            including modifying and distributing it. If you are interested in
            modifying or distributing <application>OmegaT</application>, read
            this document carefully and ensure you understand its implications
            before doing anything. If in doubt, don't hesitate to ask project
            members directly either by sending them an e-mail from the
            SourceForge page or by sending a public mail to the user
            group.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><filename>doc-license.txt</filename></entry>

            <entry>The GNU GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE. This license covers the
            documentation. See above.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><filename>readme.txt</filename></entry>

            <entry>This file is very important and you should make sure you
            read it before launching OmegaT. It includes general information
            on OmegaT, where to find more information, how to contribute, etc.
            It has been translated into a number of languages.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry rowsep="0"><application>OmegaT</application></entry>

            <entry rowsep="0">A text file containing two lines:</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry rowsep="0"></entry>

            <entry rowsep="0"><literal>#!/bin/bash java</literal></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry rowsep="0"></entry>

            <entry rowsep="0"><literal>java -jar
            <application>OmegaT</application>.jar $*</literal></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry></entry>

            <entry>Linux and OSX users may find this file useful. Make it
            executable (chmod +x OmegaT) from the command line after making
            sure you are in the /OmegaT_2.5/ directory. You will then be able
            to launch OmegaT by executing this file from the command
            line</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry rowsep="0"><application>OmegaT</application>.bat</entry>

            <entry rowsep="0">A batch file, used to launch
            <application>OmegaT</application> from the Windows command line.
            It contains just the following line:</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry></entry>

            <entry><literal>java -jar <application>OmegaT</application>.jar
            %*</literal></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><application>OmegaT</application>.jar</entry>

            <entry>The main OmegaT application. To launch OmegaT, you must
            launch this file either from the command line or from your file
            manager, usually by double-clicking it.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</chapter>
