<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % manualvariables SYSTEM "manualvariables.mod"> %manualvariables;]>
<article lang="en" id="first.steps">
  <title>OmegaT &vernb;</title>
  <section>
	<title id="first-steps">First steps</title>
	<para>Hit <keycap>F1</keycap> or access the <guimenu>> Help</guimenu> menu
	to open the user manual. It comes with a thorough introduction to OmegaT. To
	start using OmegaT with minimal settings, do this:
	
	<orderedlist id="first-step-list">
	  <listitem>
		<para>Use <guimenu>> Project</guimenu> <guimenuitem>>
		New...</guimenuitem> to create a new project.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para>Change the language codes to reflect your source and target
		languages. Click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

		<para>→ OmegaT will create a folder set that contains your files. It
		will also create an empty translation memory that it will fill in the
		background, one segment at as time as you type your translation. Matches
		for that memory will eventually appear in the <guilabel>Fuzzy
		Match</guilabel> pane.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para>Click on <guibutton>Add Files...</guibutton> and add the files
		that you want to translate. Dismiss the window.</para>

		<para>→ OmegaT will copy the selected files into the project that you
		created in the previous step. It now displays them segment per segment
		for you to translate them.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<para>Type the translation of the first segment. Hit
		<keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>

		<para>→ OmegaT will register that segment into the project translation
		memory and will move the cursor to the next segment.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
		<para>Use <guimenu>> Project</guimenu ><guimenuitem>> Create Translated
		Files</guimenuitem> to create the translated document at any
		time.</para>

		<para>→ OmegaT will store the translated files into the
		<guilabel>target</guilabel> folder of the project that was created in
		the first step. Use <guimenu>> Project</guimenu> <guisubmenu>> Access
		Project Contents</guisubmenu> to access the
		files.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
		<para>If you want to know more, read the user manual.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	</para>
  </section>

  <section>
	<title id="freedoms">Freedoms</title>
	<para>OmegaT is a free computer-assisted translation (CAT) solution for
	professional translators. It is distributed under the terms of the
	<emphasis>GNU General Public License, version 3.0</emphasis>. See
	<guimenu>> Help</guimenu> <guimenu>> About</guimenu>. The license grants you
	the following freedoms:
	
	<itemizedlist id="freedoms.list">
	  <listitem>
		<para>The freedom to run OmegaT as you wish, for any purpose.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
		<para>The freedom to study how OmegaT works, and change it so it does
		your computing as you wish.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
		<para>The freedom to redistribute copies so you can help others.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
		<para>The freedom to distribute copies of your modified versions to
		others.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
  </section>
</article>
