<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch07.formatted.text">
  <title>Working with formatted text<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Target files</primary>

      <secondary>Formatted text</secondary>
    </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Source files</primary>

      <secondary>Formatted text</secondary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>Formatting information present in the source file usually needs to be
  reproduced in the target file. The in-line formatting information made
  possible by the supported formats (in particular DocBook, HTML, XHTML, Open
  Document (OpenOffice.org) and Office Open XML (MS Office 2007 and later) at
  the time of writing) is presented as tags in OmegaT. Normally tags are
  ignored when considering the similarity between different texts for matching
  purposes. Tags reproduced in the translated segment will be present in the
  translated document.</para>

  <section id="formatting.tags">
    <title>Formatting tags<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><application><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Naming</secondary>
      </indexterm><emphasis role="bold">Tag
    naming:</emphasis></application></para>

    <para><application>The tags consist of one to three characters and a
    number. Unique numbering allows tags, corresponding to each other to be
    grouped together and differentiates between tags, that have the same
    shortcut character, but are in fact different. The shortcut characters
    used try to reflect the underlying meaning of the tag (e.g. b for bold, i
    for italics, etc.)</application></para>

    <para><application><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Numbering</secondary>
      </indexterm><emphasis role="bold">Tag
    numbering:</emphasis></application></para>

    <para><application>Tags are numbered incrementally by tag group. "Tag
    groups" in this context are a single tag (such as &lt;i0&gt; and
    &lt;/i0&gt;). Within a segment, the first group (pair or single) receives
    the number 0, the second the number 1 etc. The first example below has 3
    tag groups (a pair, a single, and then another pair), the second example
    has one group only (a pair).</application></para>

    <para><application><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Pairs and singles</secondary>
      </indexterm><emphasis role="bold">Pairs and
    singles:</emphasis></application></para>

    <para><application>Tags are always either singles or paired. Single tags
    indicate formatting information that does not affect the surrounding text
    (an extra space or line break for example).</application></para>

    <para><application><literal> &lt;segment
    2132&gt;&lt;b0&gt;&lt;Ctr+N&gt;&lt;/b0&gt;,
    &lt;br1&gt;&lt;b2&gt;&lt;Enter&gt;&lt;/b2&gt;&lt;end segment&gt;
    </literal></application></para>

    <para><application>&lt;br1&gt; is a single tag and does not affect any
    surrounding text. Paired tags usually indicate style information that
    applies to the text between the opening tag and the closing tag of a pair.
    &lt;b0&gt; and &lt;/b0&gt; below are paired and affect the text log.txt.
    Note that the opening tag must always come before the corresponding
    closing tag:</application></para>

    <para><application>&lt;<literal>segment 3167&gt;Log file
    (&lt;b0&gt;log.txt&lt;/b0&gt;) for tracking operations and errors.&lt;end
    segment&gt;</literal></application></para>

    <para><application>OmegaT</application> creates its tags before the
    process of sentence segmenting. Depending upon the segmenting rules, the
    pair of tags may get separated into two consecutive segments and the tag
    validation will err on the side of caution and mark the two
    segments.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tag.operations">
    <title>Tag operations<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Operations</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Care must be exercised with tags. If they are accidentally changed,
    the formatting of the final file may be corrupted. The basic rule is that
    the sequence of tags must be preserved in the same order. However, it is
    possible, if certain rules are strictly followed, to deviate from this
    basic rule.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Duplication</secondary>
      </indexterm>Tag duplication: </emphasis></para>

    <para>To duplicate tag groups, just copy them in the position of your
    choice. Keep in mind that in a pair group, the opening tag must come
    before the closing tag. The formatting represented by the group you have
    duplicated will be applied to both sections.</para>

    <para>Example:</para>

    <para><literal> &lt;segment 0001&gt;&lt;b0&gt;This formatting&lt;/b0&gt;
    is going to be duplicated here.&lt;end segment&gt; </literal></para>

    <para>After duplication:</para>

    <para><literal>&lt;segment 0001&gt;&lt;b0&gt;This formatting&lt;/b0&gt;
    has been &lt;b0&gt;duplicated here&lt;/b0&gt;.&lt;end segment&gt;
    </literal></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Group deletion</secondary>
      </indexterm>Tag group deletion:</emphasis></para>

    <para>To delete tag groups, just remove them from the segment. Keep in
    mind that a pair group must have both its opening and its closing tag
    deleted to ensure that all traces of the formatting are properly erased,
    otherwise the translated file may become corrupted. By deleting a tag
    group you will remove the related formatting from the translated
    file.</para>

    <para>Example:</para>

    <para><literal>&lt;segment 0001&gt;&lt;b0&gt;This formatting&lt;/b0&gt; is
    going to be deleted.&lt;end segment&gt; </literal></para>

    <para>After deletion:</para>

    <para><literal>&lt;segment 0001&gt;This formatting has been
    deleted.&lt;end segment&gt; </literal></para>
  </section>

  <section id="tag.group.nesting">
    <title>Tag group nesting<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Group nesting</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Modifying tag group order may result in the nesting of a tag group
    within another tag group. This is acceptable, provided the enclosing group
    totally encloses the enclosed group. In other words, when moving paired
    tags, ensure that both the opening and the closing tag are both either
    inside or outside other tag pairs, or the translated file may be corrupted
    and fail to open.</para>

    <para>Example:</para>

    <para><literal>&lt;segment 0001&gt;&lt;b0&gt;Formatting&lt;/b0&gt;
    &lt;b1&gt;one&lt;/b1&gt; is going to be nested inside formatting
    zero.&lt;end segment&gt; </literal></para>

    <para>After nesting:</para>

    <para><literal>&lt;segment 0001&gt;&lt;b0&gt;Formatting
    &lt;b1&gt;one&lt;/b1&gt;&lt;/b0&gt; has been nested inside formatting
    zero.&lt;end segment </literal></para>
  </section>

  <section id="tag.group.overlapping">
    <title>Tag group overlapping<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Group overlapping</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Overlapping is the result of bad manipulations of tag pairs and is
    guaranteed to result in formatting corruption and sometimes in the
    translated file not opening at all.</para>

    <para>Example:</para>

    <para><literal>&lt;segment 0001&gt;&lt;b0&gt;Formatting&lt;/b0&gt;
    &lt;b1&gt;one&lt;/b1&gt; is going to be messed up.&lt;end segment&gt;
    </literal></para>

    <para>After a bad manipulation:</para>

    <para><literal>&lt;segment 0001&gt;&lt;b0&gt;Formatting
    &lt;b1&gt;one&lt;/b0&gt; &lt;/b1&gt;is very messed up now.&lt;end
    segment&gt; </literal></para>
  </section>

  <section id="tag.group.validation">
    <title>Tag group validation<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Group validation</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>The validate tags function detects changes to tag sequences (whether
    deliberate or accidental), and shows the affected segments. Launching this
    function – <guimenuitem>Ctrl+T<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Shortcuts</primary>

        <secondary>Ctrl+T - Tag validation</secondary>
      </indexterm></guimenuitem> - opens a window containing all segments in
    the file containing suspected broken or bad tags in the translation.
    Repairing the tags and recreating the target documents is easy with the
    validate tags function. The window that opens when
    <guimenuitem>Ctrl+T</guimenuitem> is pressed features a 3-column table
    with a link to the segment, the original segment and the target
    segment</para>

    <figure id="tag.validation">
      <title>Tag validation entry</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/TagValidation.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/TagValidation.png" width="90%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The tags are highlighted in bold blue for easy comparison between
    the original and the translated contents. Click on the link to activate
    the segment in the Editor. Correct the error if necessary (in the case
    above it is the missing &lt;i2&gt;&lt;/i2&gt; pair) and press
    <guimenuitem>Ctrl+T</guimenuitem> to return to the tag validation window
    to correct other errors. Tag errors are tag sequences in the translation
    in which the same tag order and number as in the original segment is not
    reproduced. Some tag manipulations are necessary and are benign, others
    will cause problems when the translated document is created.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="hints.for.tag.management">
    <title>Hints for tags management<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Tags</primary>

        <secondary>Hints</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Simplify the original text</emphasis></para>

    <para>Tags generally represent formatting in some form of the original
    text. Simplifying the original formatting greatly contributes to reducing
    the number of tags. Where circumstances permit, unifying used fonts, font
    sizes, colors, etc. should be considered, as it could simplify the
    translation and reduce the potential for tag errors. Read the tag
    operations section to see what can be done with tags. Remember that if you
    find tags a problem in OmegaT and formatting is not extremely relevant for
    the current translation, removing tags may be the easiest way out of
    problems.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Pay extra attention to tag
    pairs</emphasis></para>

    <para>If you need to see tags in OmegaT but do not need to retain most of
    the formatting in the translated document you are free not to include tags
    in the translation. In this case pay extra attention to tag pairs since
    deleting one side of the pair but forgetting to delete the other is
    guaranteed to corrupt your document's formatting. Since tags are included
    in the text itself, it is possible to use segmentation rules to create
    segments with fewer tags. This is an advanced feature and some experience
    is required in order for it to be applied properly.</para>

    <para>OmegaT is not yet able to detect mistakes in formatting fully
    automatically, so it will not prompt you if you make an error or change
    formatting to fit your target language better. Sometimes, however, your
    translated file may look strange, and – in the worst case – may even
    refuse to open.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
