<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.glossaries">
  <title>Glossaries<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Windows and panes in OmegaT</primary>

      <secondary>Glossary pane</secondary>
    </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Glossaries</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>Glossaries are files created and updated manually for use in
  <application>OmegaT</application>.</para>

  <para>If an <application>OmegaT</application> project contains one or more
  glossaries, any terms in the glossary which are also found in the current
  segment will be automatically displayed in the Glossary viewer.</para>

  <para>You define its location and name in the project properties dialog. The
  extension must be <filename>.txt</filename>(if not, it will be added). The
  location of the file must be within the <filename>/glossary</filename>folder, 
  but it can be in a deeper directory (e.g.,
  <filename>glossary/sub/glossary.txt</filename>). The file does not need to
  exist when setting it, it will be created (if necessary) when adding a
  glossary entry. If the file already exists, no attempt is done to verify the
  format or the character set of the file: the new entries will always be in
  tab-separated format and UTF-8. As the existing content will not be touched,
  damage to an existing file would be limited.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>To use an existing glossary, simply place it in the<indexterm
        class="singular">
        <primary>Project files</primary>

        <secondary>Glossary subfolder</secondary>
      </indexterm> <filename>/glossary</filename> folder after creating the
    project. <application>OmegaT</application> automatically detects glossary
    files in this folder when a project is opened. Terms in the current
    segment which <application>OmegaT</application> finds in the glossary
    file(s) are displayed in the Glossary pane:</para>

    <indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Glossaries, Glossary pane</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>Glossary pane</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/GlossaryPane_25.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/GlossaryPane_25.png" width="60%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The word before the = sign is the source term, and its translation
    is (or are) the words after =. The vocabulary entry can have a comment
    added. The glossary function only finds exact matches with the glossary
    entry (e.g. does not find inflected forms etc.). New terms can be added
    manually to the glossary file(s) during translation, for example in a text
    editor. Newly added terms will not be recognized once the changes in the
    text file have been saved.</para>

    <para>The source term does not have to be a single-word item, as the next
    example shows:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>multiple words entries in glossaries - example<indexterm
          class="singular">
          <primary>Glossaries</primary>

          <secondary>Glossary pane</secondary>

          <tertiary>multiple-words entries</tertiary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/MultiTerm_Glossary_25.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/MultiTerm_Glossary_25.png" width="80%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The underlined item "pop-up menu" can be found in the glossary pane
    as "pojavni menu". Highlighting it in the Glossary pane and then
    rightclicking insets at the cursor position in the target
    segment.<footnote>
        <para>Note that in the above case, this is just half (or even less) of
        the story, as the target language (Slovenian) uses declension. So the
        inserted "pojavni meni" in the nominative form - has to be changed to
        "pojavnem meniju" , i.e. to the locative. So it is probably faster to
        type the term correctly right away without bothering with the glossary
        and its shortcuts.</para>
      </footnote></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>File format</secondary>
      </indexterm>File format<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Project files</primary>

        <secondary>User files</secondary>

        <seealso>Glossaries</seealso>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Glossary files are simple plain text files containing three-column,
    tab-delimited lists with the source and target terms in the first and
    second columns respectively. The third column can be used for additional
    information. You can have entries with the target column missing, i.e.
    just containing the source term and the comment.</para>

    <para>Glossary files can be either in system default encoding (and
    indicated by the extension .tab) or in UTF-8 (the extension .utf8). The
    Unicode encoding (UTF8) is preferred for obvious reasons. Also supported
    is the CSV format. This format is the same as the tab separated one:
    source term, target term. Comment fields are separated by a comma ','.
    Strings can be enclosed by quotes ", which allows having a comma inside a
    string:</para>

    <para><literal>"This is a source term, which contains a comma","c'est un
    terme, qui contient une virgule"</literal></para>

    <para>In addition to the plain text format, TBX format <indexterm
        class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>TBX format</secondary>
      </indexterm> is also supported. TBX - Term Base eXchange - is the open,
    XML-based standard for exchanging structured terminological data, TBX has
    been approved as an international standard by LISA and ISO. If you have an
    existing terminology handling system - MultiTerm for example - it is quite
    possible it offers the export of terminology data via TBX format. <ulink
    url="http://www.microsoft.com/Language/en-US/Terminology.aspx">Microsoft
    Terminology Collection</ulink> <indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>Microsoft Terminology collection</secondary>
      </indexterm> can be downloaded in nearly 100 languages and can serve as
    a cornerstone IT glossary.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to create glossaries<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>Creating a glossary</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>The project setting allows one can enter a name for a writable
    glossary file (see beginning of this chapter). Right-click in the glossary
    pane or press <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+G</keycap> to add a new entry. A dialog
    opens, allowing you to enter the source term, target term and any comments
    you may have:</para>

    <mediaobject role="html">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/GlossaryEntry_25.png"/>
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="images/GlossaryEntry_25.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The contents of glossary files are kept in memory and are loaded
    when the project is opened or reloaded. Updating a glossary file is thus
    rather simple: press <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+G</keycap> and enter the new
    term, its translation and any comments you may have (ensuring you press
    tab between the fields) and save the file. The contents of the glossary
    pane will be updated accordingly.</para>

    <para><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>Location of the writable glossary file</secondary>
      </indexterm>The location of the writable glossary file can be set in the
    <guimenuitem>Project &gt; Properties ... </guimenuitem>dialog. The
    recognized extensions are <filename>TXT</filename> and
    <filename>UTF8</filename></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note: </emphasis>Of course there are other
    ways and means to create a simple file with tab delimited entries. Nothing
    speaks against using Notepad++ on Windows, GEdit on Linux for instance or
    some spreadsheet program for this purpose: any application, that can
    handle UTF8 and that can show white space (so that you do not miss the
    required <keycap>TAB</keycap> characters) can be used.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>Trados MultiTerm</secondary>
      </indexterm>Using Trados MultiTerm</title>

    <para>Data exported from Trados MultiTerm can be used as
    <application>OmegaT</application> glossaries without further modification,
    provided they are given the file extension <filename>.tab</filename> and
    the source and target term fields are the first two fields respectively.
    If you export using the system option "Tab-delimited export", you will
    need to delete the first 5 columns (Seq. Nr, Date created etc). The newer
    versions of MultiTerm support exporting to TBX format.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Glossaries</primary>

        <secondary>Problems with glossaries</secondary>
      </indexterm>Common glossary problems</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Problem: No glossary terms are displayed -
    possible causes:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>No glossary file found in the "glossary" folder.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The glossary file is empty.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The items are not separated with a TAB character.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The glossary file does not have the correct extension (.tab or
        .utf8).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>There is no EXACT match between the glossary entry and the
        source text in your document - for instance plurals.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The glossary file does not have the correct encoding.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>There are no terms in the current segment which match any terms
        in the glossary.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One or more of the above problems may have been fixed, but the
        project has not been reloaded.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Problem: In the glossary pane, some characters
    are not displayed properly</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>...but the same characters are displayed properly in the Editing
        pane: the extension and the file encoding do not match.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
