<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % manualvariables SYSTEM "manualvariables.mod">
]>
<section id="launch.with.command.line">
  <title id="launch.with.command.line.title">Start OmegaT from the command
  line</title>

  <para>Using the command line allows you to set various options that control or modify the behaviour of the application. You can also define and save sets of options in scripts that you can then use to launch OmegaT for a particular purpose.</para>


  <section id="launch.with.command.line.tutorial">
		<title id="launch.with.command.line.tutorial.title">Very simplified overview of the command line</title>

		<para>Before graphical interfaces became common, users interacted with computers via a  command line interface (CLI), which requires typing commands to give instructions to the computer. On modern systems, the CLI is accessed through an application generally called a &quot;terminal&quot; or &quot;console&quot;. For the sake of simplicity, this manual refers to it as the terminal.</para>
		
		<note><para>On Windows, you can use either the <application>Command Prompt</application> or <application>Powershell</application> as a terminal. Both are available from the <guilabel>System Tools</guilabel> folder of the <guilabel>Start Menu</guilabel>. The macOS equivalent is the <application>Terminal</application> application located in the <filename>Utilities</filename> folder of the <filename>Applications</filename> main folder. On Linux, the default terminal application for your distribution should be available from the application menu or one of its submenus.</para></note>

		<para>In the terminal, you type commands and their associated parameters to perform tasks. This makes it easy to perform certain tasks that would be difficult to perform using a graphical interface.</para>

		<para>A key concept to remember when using the command line for OmegaT is that you typically have to type the full location to the OmegaT program on your system as the command, because the system does not know where to find it by default. </para>

		<note>
			<para>The syntax used to specify the location of an application or folder depends on the platform. On Windows, the (<code>\</code> character is used  to separate folder and file names, while macOS and Linux  the <code>/</code> to do so. The typical default locations for each major platform are presented below.
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>Windows</term>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>C:\Program Files\OmegaT</filename></para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>macOS</term>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/Applications/OmegaT</filename></para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>Linux</term>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/opt/omegat</filename></para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</para>
		</note>	
  </section>

  <section id="launch.with.command.line.omegat.terminal.command.syntax">
		<title id="launch.with.command.line.omegat.terminal.command.syntax.title">OmegaT terminal command syntax</title>

		<para>The syntax to launch OmegaT from the terminal is:
			<programlisting>java -jar &lt;java parameters&gt; OmegaT.jar &lt;OmegaT parameters&gt; </programlisting></para>
		<para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><literal>java -jar</literal></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>This  command starts the Java Virtual Machine (JVM) and runs the .jar package specified after, OmegaT in this example.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><emphasis>&lt;java parameters&gt;</emphasis></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Optional parameters accepted by the <command>java</command> command. The parameters relevant to running OmegaT are described  <link linkend="launch.with.command.line.java.parameters">below</link></para>
					</listitem>					
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><literal>OmegaT.jar</literal></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>The OmegaT java executable.</para>
						
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><emphasis>&lt;OmegaT parameters&gt;</emphasis></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>The options specific to OmegaT are described <link linkend="launch.with.command.line.omegat.parameters">later in this section</link></para>
					</listitem>					
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
	</section>

  <section id="launch.with.command.line.java.parameters">
		<title id="launch.with.command.line.java.parameters.title">Java parameters relevant to OmegaT</title>

		<para>The list below presents parameters for the <command>java</command> that can be useful when working with OmegaT.
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>User interface language</term>
					<listitem>
						<para><code>-Duser.country=LL</code></para>
						<para>Replace <code>LL</code> with the desired two-letter language code from the <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_ISO_639-1_codes">ISO 639.1</ulink> list.</para>
						<para>Using this option will launch OmegaT with the user interface in that language, if available (even partially). If the language is not available, OmegaT defaults to English even if the system uses a different default language.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>User country</term>
					<listitem>
						<para><code>-Duser.country=CC</code></para>
						<para>Replace <code>CC</code> with the desired two-letter country code from the <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISO_3166-1_alpha-2">ISO 3166-1 alpha-2</ulink> list.</para>
						<para>This option combines with the previous user interface language parameter to specify a regional variant. If that variant is not available, the user interface follows the same priority as above.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>Maximum memory assignment</term>
					<listitem>
						<para><code>-XmxSIZE</code></para>
						<para>Replace <code>SIZE</code> is a number of bytes in multiples of 1024 and at least 2 MB, followed by <code>k</code> for kilobyte, <code>m</code> for megabyte,  or <code>g</code> for gigabyte.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>Proxy host IP address</term>
					<listitem>
						<para><code>-Dhttp.proxyHost=...</code></para>
						<para>Replace <code>...</code> with the IP address of your proxy server, if your system uses one.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>Proxy host port number</term>
					<listitem>
						<para><code>-Dhttp.proxyPort=...</code></para>
						<para>Replace <code>...</code> with the port number your system uses to access the proxy server.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Google Translate V2</term>
					<listitem>
						<para><code>-Dgoogle.api.key=...</code></para>
						<para>Replace <code>...</code> with your private Google API key.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Microsoft Translator</term>
					<listitem>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para><code>-Dmicrosoft.api.client_id=...</code></para>
								<para>Replace <code>...</code> with your client ID</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para><code>-Dmicrosoft.api.client_secret=...</code></para>
								<para>Replace <code>...</code> with your client secret</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>The ID and secret can be found in your account page under Primary account key and Customer-ID.</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>Yandex Translate</term>
					<listitem>
						<para><code>-Dyandex.api.key=...</code></para>
						<para>Replace <code>...</code> with your Yandex Translate API key.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>

				<note>
					<para>
						It should go without saying that you must have signed up for the appropriate service to use the machine translation options.
					</para>
				</note>
			</section>

  <section id="launch.with.command.line.omegat.parameters">
		<title id="launch.with.command.line.omegat.parameters.title">OmegaT options</title>

		<para>You can also get a list of these options in the terminal with the <command>java -jar OmegaT.jar <parameter>--help</parameter></command> command. The OmegaT GUI is launched if no option is specified.</para>

		<para>		
			<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>General options:</term>
				<listitem>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>-h, --help</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Show usage information.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Path to an OmegaT project</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Launch the GUI and load the specified project</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--remote-project &lt;path-to-omegat-project-file&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Download the OmegaT project from the specified URL specified in &lt;path-to-omegat-project-file&gt;, and load it.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--no-team</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Disable team project functionality. Use this option if you want to prevent OmegaT from synchronizing the project contents.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>team init SL TL</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Initialize a team project using SL and TL as the source and target two-letter language codes, respectively. </para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--disable-project-locking</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Do not lock the omegat.project file.</para>
								<para>By default, the omegat.project  is locked under Windows and attempting to open an already open project in another instance of OmegaT results in an error. This option prevents that error.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--disable-location-save</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Do not remember the last directory opened in the file picker.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--ITokenizer=&lt;classname&gt;</term>
							<term>--ITokenizerTarget=&lt;classname&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Specify a source- or target-language tokenizer (using this option overrides project settings). See OmegaT.jar/META-INF/MANIFEST.MF for valid values.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--config-dir=&lt;path&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>The directory used to read and write OmegaT configuration files.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--config-file=&lt;path&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>A Java .properties file from which to load default settings.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--resource-bundle=&lt;path&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>A Java .properties file to use for interface text</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>--mode=[console-translate|console-pseudotranslatetmx|console-align]</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Specify a mode other than the GUI default. See below for details.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--mode=console-translate</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>In this mode, OmegaT will attempt to translate the files in the source folder with the available translation memories. This is useful if OmegaT is run on a server with TMX files automatically fed to a project.
						<variablelist>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>--source-pattern=&lt;pattern&gt;</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>A whitelist of regular expressions defining the source files to process. Remember that in regular expressions, the period and backslash character must be escaped: &quot;\.&quot; and &quot;\\&quot;.</para>
									<para>Here are some typical examples:
										<variablelist>
											<varlistentry>
												<term>.*\.html</term>
												<listitem>
													<para>Translate all HTML files.</para>
												</listitem>
											</varlistentry>
											<varlistentry>
												<term>test\.html</term>
												<listitem>
													<para>Only translate <filename>test.html</filename> file in the source folder itself. Any files also named test.html in other subfolders will be ignored.</para>
												</listitem>
											</varlistentry>
											<varlistentry>
												<term>dir-10\\test\.html</term>
												<listitem>
													<para>Only translate the <filename>test.html</filename> file in the <filename class="directory">dir-10</filename> folder.</para>
												</listitem>
											</varlistentry>
										</variablelist>
										See <link linkend="appendix.regexp" endterm="appendix.regexp.title"/> for details.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>--mode=console-pseudotranslatetmx</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>In this mode OmegaT will create a TMX for the whole project using only the source files. Specify the TMX file to be created with:
						<variablelist>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>--pseudotranslatetmx=&lt;path&gt;</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>The output pseudotranslated TMX file.</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>--pseudotranslatetype=[equal|empty]</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>What to fill the pseudotranslated TMX with.</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--mode=console-align --alignDir=&lt;path&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>In this mode, OmegaT will align the files in the /source folder of the project with those at the location specified by the --alignDir parameter. The resulting TMX file is is saved in the /omegat folder as align.tmx. The file types that can be aligned depend whether alignment is supported by the file filter . Supported filters include: ILIAS Language File, Java(TM) Resource Bundles, Key=Value Text, Magento CE Locale CSV, MoodlePHP, Mozilla DTD, Mozilla FTL, PO, RC, SubRip Subtitles, and Windows Resources.</para>
					<para>The --alignDir parameter is used to specify the location of the data in the target language, which must be a folder containing the translated files.</para>
					<para>That folder must contain a translation in the target language of the project. For instance, if the project is EN-to-FR, the folder must contain a bundle ending with _fr. The resulting TMX file is is saved in the /omegat folder as align.tmx.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
				<varlistentry><term>Non-GUI mode options:</term>
					<listitem>
						<variablelist>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>--quiet</term>
								<listitem><para>Minimize the output shown on the command line.</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>--script=&lt;path&gt;</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>A script file to run when a project event is triggered.</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>--tag-validation=[abort|warn]</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>Validate tags. Abort: Exit with an error if tags there are invalid tags. Note: Invalid tags reports are sent to stdout.</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
	</section>
</section>