<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="howto.reusetm">
  <title>Reuse Translation Memories</title>

  <para>Initially, that is when the project is created, the main TM of the
  project, <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> is empty. This TM gradually
  becomes filled during the translation. To speed up this process, existing
  translations can be reused. If a given sentence has already been translated
  once, and translated correctly, there is no need for it to be retranslated.
  Translation memories may also contain reference translations: multinational
  legislation, such as that of the European Community, is a typical
  example.</para>

  <para>When you create the target documents in an
  <application>OmegaT</application> project, the translation memory of the
  project is output in the form of three files in the root folder of your
  <application>OmegaT</application> project (see the above description). You
  can regard these three tmx files (<filename>-omegat.tmx</filename>,
  <filename>-level1.tmx</filename> and <filename>-level2.tmx</filename>) as an
  &quot;export translation memory&quot;, i.e. as an export of your current project's
  content in bilingual form.</para>

  <para>Should you wish to reuse a translation memory from a previous project
  (for example because the new project is similar to the previous project, or
  uses terminology which might have been used before), you can use these
  translation memories as &quot;input translation memories&quot;, i.e. for import into
  your new project. In this case, place the translation memories you wish to
  use in the <emphasis>/tm</emphasis> or <emphasis>/tm</emphasis>/auto folder
  of your new project: in the former case you will get hits from these
  translation memories in the fuzzy matches viewer, and in the latter case
  these TMs will be used to pre-translate your source text.</para>

  <para>By default, the /tm folder is below the project's root folder (e.g.
  ...<emphasis>/MyProject/tm</emphasis>), but you can choose a different
  folder in the project properties dialog if you wish. This is useful if you
  frequently use translation memories produced in the past, for example
  because they are on the same subject or for the same customer. In this case,
  a useful procedure would be:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Create a folder (a &quot;repository folder&quot;) in a convenient location
      on your hard drive for the translation memories for a particular
      customer or subject.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Whenever you finish a project, copy one of the three &quot;export&quot;
      translation memory files from the root folder of the project to the
      repository folder.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>When you begin a new project on the same subject or for the same
      customer, navigate to the repository folder in the <guimenuitem>Project
      &gt; Properties &gt; Edit Project dialog</guimenuitem> and select it as
      the translation memory folder.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Note that all the tmx files in the /tm repository are parsed when the
  project is opened, so putting all different TMs you may have on hand into
  this folder may unnecessarily slow OmegaT down. You may even consider
  removing those that are not required any more, once you have used their
  contents to fill up the <filename>project-save.tmx</filename> file.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Importing and exporting translation memories</title>

    <para>OmegaT supports imported tmx versions 1.1-1.4b (both level 1 and
    level 2). This enables the translation memories produced by other tools to
    be read by OmegaT. However, OmegaT does not fully support imported level 2
    tmx files (these store not only the translation, but also the formatting).
    Level 2 tmx files will still be imported and their textual content can be
    seen in OmegaT, but the quality of fuzzy matches will be somewhat
    lower.</para>

    <para>OmegaT follows very strict procedures when loading translation
    memory (tmx) files. If an error is found in such a file, OmegaT will
    indicate the position within the defective file at which the error is
    located.</para>

    <para>Some tools are known to produce invalid tmx files under certain
    conditions. If you wish to use such files as reference translations in
    OmegaT, they must be repaired, or OmegaT will report an error and fail to
    load them. Fixes are trivial operations and OmegaT assists troubleshooting
    with the related error message. You can ask the user group for advice if
    you have problems.</para>

    <para>OmegaT exports version 1.4 TMX files (both level 1 and level 2). The
    level 2 export is not fully compliant with the level 2 standard, but is
    sufficiently close and will generate correct matches in other translation
    memory tools supporting TMX Level 2. If you only need textual information
    (and not formatting information), use the level 1 file that OmegaT has
    created.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating a translation memory for selected documents</title>

    <para>In case translators need to share their TMX bases while excluding
    some of their parts or including just translations of certain files,
    sharing the complete <filename>ProjectName-omegat.tmx</filename> is out of
    question. The following recipe is just one of the possibilities, but
    simple enough to follow and without any dangers for the assets.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a project, separate for other projects, in the desired
        language pair, with an appropriate name - note that the TMXs created
        will include this name.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Copy the documents, you need the translation memory for, into
        the source folder of the project.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Copy the translation memories, containing the translations of
        the documents above, into <filename>tm/auto</filename> subfolder of
        the new project.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Start the project. Check for possible Tag errors with
        <keycap>Ctrl+T </keycap>and untranslated segments with
        <keycap>Ctrl+U</keycap>. To check everything is as expected, you may
        press <keycap>Ctrl+D</keycap> to create the target documents and check
        their contents.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>When you exit the project. the TMX files in the main project
        folder (see above) now contain the translations in the selected
        language pair, for the files, you have copied into the source folder.
        Copy them to a safe place for future referrals.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To avoid reusing the project and thus possibly polluting future
        cases, delete the project folder or archive it away from your
        workplace.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Sharing translation memories</title>

    <para>In cases where a team of translators is involved, translators will
    prefer to share common translation memories rather than distribute their
    local versions.</para>

    <para>OmegaT interfaces to SVN and Git, two common team software
    versioning and revision control systems (RCS), available under an open
    source license. In case of OmegaT complete project folders - in other
    words the translation memories involved as well as source folders, project
    settings etc - are managed by the selected RCS. see more in Chapter</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using TMX with alternative language</title>

    <para>There may be cases where you have done a project with e.g. Dutch
    sources, and a translation in say English. Then you need a translation in
    e.g. Chinese, but your translator does not understand Dutch; she, however,
    understands perfectly English. In this case, the NL-EN translation memory
    can serve as a go-between to help generate NL to ZH translation.</para>

    <para>The solution in our example is to copy the existing translation
    memory into the tm/tmx2source/ subfolder and rename it to ZH_CN.tmx to
    indicate the target language of the tmx. The translator will be shown
    English translations for source segments in Dutch and use them to create
    the Chinese translation.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Important: </emphasis>the supporting TMX must
    be renamed XX_YY.tmx, where XX_YY is the target language of the tmx, for
    instance to ZH_CN.tmx in the example above. The project and TMX source
    languages should of course be identical - NL in our example. Note that
    only one TMX for a given language pair is possible, so if several
    translation memories should be involved, you will need to merge them all
    into the XX_YY.tmx.</para>
  </section>
</section>