<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="how.to.use.team.project">
  <title id="how.to.use.team.project.title">Use a team project</title>

  <para>Team projects use synchronization mechanisms between project members.</para>

  <para>Once a OmegaT team project is installed on a server, the administrator
  sends members the information they need to access it: a URL indicating the
  location of the project, or an <filename>omegat.project</filename>
  file.</para>

  <para>After the project is downloaded, it is installed locally and only needs
  to be opened locally to synchronize with the server.</para>

  <para>Repository credentials are stored in the <link
  linkend="configuration.folder.extra.contents.repositories"
  endterm="configuration.folder.extra.contents.repositories.title"/> file and
  can be deleted from the <link
  linkend="dialog.preferences.team.title.repository.credentials"
  endterm="dialog.preferences.team.title.repository.credentials.title"/>
  preferences.</para>

  <para>Since synchronization takes place by default every three minutes, 
  project members will sometime translate or modify a segment that has already
  been translated by another member but not synchronized yet. When that happens,
  members have to select the appropriate translation.</para>

  <para>Members can take turns translating and reviewing the files. The Search
  function allows them to filter the Editor pane on contents translated by a
  given person, or on contents translated after or before a given time,
  for example.</para>
  
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Downloading the project</term>
      <listitem>
		<orderedlist>
		  <listitem>
			<para>From a URL</para>

			<para>Use <link endterm="menus.project.title"
			linkend="menus.project"/><link
			endterm="menus.project.download.team.project.title"
			linkend="menus.project.download.team.project"/> to bring up the
			<guilabel>Download Team Project</guilabel> dialog.</para>

			<para>Enter the URL provided by the team project administrator in the
			<guilabel>Repository URL:</guilabel> field at the top of the dialog,
			and specify a folder for the project in the <guilabel>New Local
			Project Folder:</guilabel> field. Leave the <guilabel>Default
			branch</guilabel> option checked unless the project administrator
			has provided instructions for using a custom branch.</para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
			<para>From an <filename>omegat.project</filename> file</para>

			<para>Put the <filename>omegat.project</filename> file in an empty
			folder, and open it in OmegaT. The project will automatically be
			downloaded to the folder containing that file.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<note>
		  <para>Servers generally use two main types of authentication: entering
		  a <emphasis>username/password</emphasis>, or
		  <emphasis>SSH</emphasis>.</para>

		  <para>If the server relies on username/password authentication, OmegaT
		  will present you with an <guilabel>Authentication</guilabel> dialog to
		  enter your username and password either when you first download the
		  project or later on in the process. OmegaT will then remember your
		  credentials for that specific project unless you explicitly delete
		  them. See the <link
		  linkend="dialog.preferences.team.title.repository.credentials"
		  endterm="dialog.preferences.team.title.repository.credentials.title"/>
		  preferences for details.</para>

		  <para>If the server uses SSH authentication, make sure you update your
		  SSH configuration to include that server before attempting to download
		  the project, otherwise you will get an authentication error and the
		  project will fail to load.</para>

		  <para>If you use multiple projects on the same server, credentials
		  will only be asked once for that server.</para>
		</note>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Synchronization</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Synchronizing the project adds translations made by all team
        members to local copies of the project. Only the contents of the two
        following files are synchronized:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
			<para><filename>project.save</filename></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
			<para><filename>glossary.txt</filename></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>During synchronization, all other local files are overwritten
        with the versions on the remote server, exept for
        <filename>omegat.project</filename> (see below).</para>

        <para>OmegaT synchronizes a team project when it is opened, reloaded,
        closed or saved. This means the automatic save function also regularly
        synchronizes local versions with the version on the server at the
        interval specified in the <link
        endterm="dialog.preferences.saving.and.output.interval.title"
        linkend="dialog.preferences.saving.and.output.interval"/>
        preference.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Team project configuration</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>As in regular local projects, the configuration of the team
        project is defined by the contents <filename>omegat.project</filename>
        file and the optional use of special files for project-specific
        filters or segmentation rules.</para>

        <para>The first time the project is downloaded, OmegaT retrieves the
        <filename>omegat.project</filename> file from the server. This file
        defines the following parameters:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Basic project configuration:</emphasis> Source and
            languages, tokenizers, and the project folder hierarchy.</para>

			<para>In a team project, the basic configuration parameters of the
			local project are always overridden by the configuration on the
			server originally set by the project administrator.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Repository mappings</emphasis></para>

            <para>See the <link
            linkend="how.to.setup.team.project.mapping.parameters"
            endterm="how.to.setup.team.project.mapping.parameters.title"/>
            how-to for details.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>If no custom mappings have been defined for the remote
                project, but local mappings have been customized, the local
                settings are preserved without affecting the settings on the
                server.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If the remote project contains custom mappings, but the
                local project does not, the mappings from the server are applied
                to the local project.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If the remote project specifies a URL protocol and you
                download it using a different protocol, your local configuration
                will be preserved.</para>

                <para>For example, many hosting services support access to the
                same repository using either the SSH +Git or https protocol.
                OmegaT will respect the local protocol selection.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you first download the remote project using an
                <filename>omegat.project</filename> file provided by the project
                administrator, OmegaT will use the mappings in that file, if
                any.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If there is a conflict between the remote and local
                versions of the <filename>omegat.project</filename> and the
                local version is overwritten, OmegaT creates a backup file
                called <filename>omegat.project.YYYYMMDDhhmm.bak</filename>.
                The backup files are kept for a least ten days, and older
                backups are automatically deleted.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

        <warning>
          <para>Remember that any modifications to the local project
          configuration files will be overwritten by the versions on the server
          when the project is synchronized.</para>
        </warning>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Source files</term>

      <listitem>
        <warning>
		  <para>Only the project administrator should use <link
		  endterm="menus.project.title" linkend="menus.project"/><link
		  endterm="menus.project.commit.source.files.title"
		  linkend="menus.project.commit.source.files"/>.</para>
		</warning>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Target files</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>After you generate the target files use
        <link endterm="menus.project.title"
        linkend="menus.project"/><link
        endterm="menus.project.commit.target.files.title"
        linkend="menus.project.commit.target.files"/> to add them to the
        server, if the project administrator has requested you to do so.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Deleting files</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Files in a team project cannot be deleted from OmegaT or the local
        file system. They will be restored the next time the project is
        synchronized. This task is normally performed by the project
        administrator.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Working offline</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can open a team project and work on it offline. All changes
        will be synchronized the next time a connection is available.</para>

        <para>There are two ways work offline:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Disconnect from the network before opening the
            project.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Open the project from the command line with the
            <parameter>--no-team</parameter> option. See the <link
            linkend="launch.with.command.line"
            endterm="launch.with.command.line.title"/> section for
            details.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>
