<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="how.to.create.new.project">
  <title id="how.to.create.new.project.title">Create a New Project</title>

    <para>To start using OmegaT, you first have to create a project to hold all your files, such as your source files, translation memories, glossaries, and eventually your translated files. To create a new project, select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>New...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the <guimenu>Project</guimenu> menu (or press <keycombo><keycap>C</keycap><keycap>S</keycap><keycap>n</keycap></keycombo>), select a folder, and type a name for your project.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Since an OmegaT project is simply a set of folders and subfolders, you are entering the name of the folder that will hold your project. Alternatively, you can choose an existing <emphasis>empty</emphasis> folder created beforehand. Keep in mind that OmegaT cannot create a project in a folder that already contains files or subfolders.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Remember where you are creating the project, because you will need to return to it later.</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Create New Project</guilabel> dialog opens after you have named your project. At the top of that dialog, select the languages of your source and translated files, and click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button to continue.</para>

    <para>If you are interested in other settings in this dialog, you can return
    to it any time by pressing
    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>.</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Project Files</guilabel> dialog opens next. Click on <guibutton>Copy Files to Source Folder...</guibutton> and select your source files. OmegaT will then copy the selected files to the <filename class="directory">source</filename> subfolder of your newly created project. You can close the <guilabel>Project Files</guilabel> dialog after the source files have loaded in the <guilabel>Editor</guilabel> pane,.</para>
  </section>