<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="howto.managerighttoleft">
  <title>Manage Right-To-Left languages</title>

   <para>Justification of source and target segments depends upon the project
    languages. By default, left justification is used for Left-To-Right (LTR)
    languages and right justification for Right-To-Left (RTL) languages. You
    can toggle between different display modes by pressing <keycombo>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>

        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>O</keycap>
      </keycombo> (this is the letter O and not the numeral 0). The <keycombo>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>

        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>O</keycap>
      </keycombo> toggle has three states:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>default justification, that is as defined by the language</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>left justification</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>right justification</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Using the RTL mode in <application>OmegaT</application> has no
    influence whatsoever on the display mode of the translated documents
    created in <application>OmegaT</application>. The display mode of the
    translated documents must be modified within the application (such as
    Microsoft Word) commonly used to display or modify them (check the
    relevant manuals for details). Using <keycombo>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>

        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>O</keycap>
      </keycombo> causes both text input and display in
    <application>OmegaT</application> to change. It can be used separately for
    all three panes (Editor, Fuzzy Matches and Glossary) by clicking on the
    pane and toggling the display mode. It can also be used in all the input
    fields found in <application>OmegaT</application> - in the search window,
    for segmentation rules etc.</para>

    <para>Mac OS X users, note: use <keycombo>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>

        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>O</keycap>
      </keycombo> shortcut and <emphasis role="bold">not
    </emphasis>cmd+Ctrl+O.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Mixing RTL and LTR strings in segments</title>

      <para>When writing purely RTL text, the default (LTR) view may be used.
      In many cases, however, it is necessary to embed LTR text in RTL text.
      For example, in OmegaT tags, product names that must be left in the LTR
      source language, place holders in localization files, and numbers in
      text. In cases like these it becomes necessary to switch to RTL mode, so
      that the RTL (in fact bidirectional) text is displayed correctly. It
      should be noted that when <application>OmegaT</application> is in RTL
      mode, both source and target are displayed in RTL mode. This means that
      if the source language is LTR and the target language is RTL, or vice
      versa, it may be necessary to toggle back and forth between RTL and LTR
      modes to view the source and enter the target easily in their respective
      modes.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><application>OmegaT</application> tags in RTL segments</title>

      <para>As stated above, OmegaT tags are LTR strings. When translating
      between RTL and LTR languages, correctly reading the tags from the
      source and entering them properly in the target may require the
      translator to toggle between LTR and RTL modes numerous times.</para>

      <para>If the document allows, the translator is strongly encouraged to
      remove style information from the original document so that as few tags
      as possible appear in the OmegaT interface. Follow the indications given
      in Hints for tags management. Frequently validate tags (see Tag
      validation) and produce translated documents (see below and Menu) at
      regular intervals to make it easier to catch any problems that arise. A
      hint: translating a plain text version of the text and adding the
      necessary style in the relevant application at a later stage may turn
      out to be less hassle.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating translated RTL documents</title>

      <para>When the translated document is created, its display direction
      will be the same as that of the original document. If the original
      document was LTR, the display direction of the target document must be
      changed manually to RTL in its viewing application. Each output format
      has specific ways of dealing with RTL display; check the relevant
      application manuals for details.</para>

      <para>For .docx files, a number of changes are however done
      automatically: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            Paragraphs, sections and tables are set to bidi
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            Runs (text elements) are set to RTL
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>To avoid changing the target files display parameters each time
      the files are opened, it may be possible to change the source file
      display parameters such that such parameters are inherited by the target
      files. Such modifications are possible in ODF files for example.</para>

  </section>
</section>
