<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="howto.translatepdf">
  <title>Translate a PDF file</title>

<para>PDF files are a special case. They contain text formatting
  information, but such information cannot be reused by
  <application>OmegaT</application> in order to create target files.
  Thus, PDF files are handled as plain text files, and output files are
  plain text files.</para>
  <para>If you need to reproduce text formatting (as well as other
  things such as drawings) in your translation, there are three ways
  to try:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Use <application>OmegaT’s</application> default filter
      (PDF input), translate, create a target file (it will be a plain
      text file), add relevant formatting and items manually.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Use the Iceni Infix filter.
      See <ulink url="https://omegat.org/howtos/iceni_infix.html">Howto - Translating PDF files with Iceni Infix and OmegaT</ulink>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Import the source file to
      <ulink url="https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/draw/">LibreOffice Draw</ulink>,
      save it as an ODG file, translate, export to PDF as needed.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> the above information
  applies only to PDF files with a text layer. If you have a PDF file
  made of scanned pages (sometimes such files are referred to as ‘dead’
  PDFs), you need to use an OCR (optical character recognition) program
  to recognize the text and convert it to a format that can be handled
  by OmegaT.</para>



  <section id="other.file.formats">
    <title>Other file formats</title>

    <para>Other plain text or formatted text file formats suitable for
    processing in OmegaT may also exist.</para>

    <para>External tools can be used to convert files to supported
    formats. The translated files will then need to be converted back to the
    original format. For example, if you have an outdated Microsoft Word
    version, that does not handle the ODT format, here's a round trip for Word
    files with the DOC extension:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>import the file into ODF writer</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>save the file in ODT format</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>translate it into the target ODT file</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>load the target file in ODF writer</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>save the file as a DOC file</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The quality of formatting of the translated file will depend on the
    quality of the round-trip conversion. Before proceeding with such
    conversions, be sure to test all options. Check the <ulink
    url="http://www.omegat.org">OmegaT home page</ulink> for an up-to-date
    listing of auxiliary translation tools.</para>
</section>
</section>