<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="howto.preventdataloss">
  <title>Prevent data loss</title>

  <para><application>OmegaT</application> is a robust application. However,
  you should take precautions against data loss when using
  <application>OmegaT</application>, just as with any other application. When
  you translate your files, <application>OmegaT</application> stores all your
  progress in the translation memory <literal>project_save.tmx</literal> that
  resides in the project's <literal>/omegat</literal> subfolder.</para>

  <para>OmegaT also backs up the translation memory to
  project_save.tmx.YEARMMDDHHNN.bak in the same subfolder each time a project
  is opened or reloaded. YEAR is the 4-digit year, MM is the month, DD the day
  of the month, and HH and NN are the hours and minutes when the previous
  translation memory was saved.</para>

  <para>If you believe that you have lost translation data, you can use the
  following procedure to restore the project to its most recently saved state,
  usually not older than approximately 10 minutes or so:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>close the project</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>rename the current <filename>project_save.tmx </filename>file
      (e.g. to <filename>project_save.tmx.temporary</filename>)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>select the backup translation memory that is the most likely to
      contain the data you are looking for</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>rename it <literal>project_save.tmx</literal></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>open the project</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>To avoid losing important data:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Make regular copies of the file /omegat/project_save.tmx to backup
      media, such as CD or DVD.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Until you are familiar with <application>OmegaT</application>,
      create translated files at regular intervals and check that the
      translated file contains the latest version of your translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Take particular care when making changes to the files in
      <literal>/source</literal> while in the middle of a project. If the
      source file is modified after you have begun translating,
      <application>OmegaT</application> may be unable to find a segment that
      you have already translated.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Use these Help texts to get started. Should you run into problems,
      post a message in the <ulink url="https://omegat.org/support"><application>OmegaT</application>
      user group</ulink>. Do not hesitate to post in the language you feel the
      most familiar with.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
