<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="how.to.restore.your.data">
  <title id="how.to.restore.your.data.title">Restore your data</title>

  <warning><para>OmegaT is a robust and trustworthy application, but even so, it is smart take precautions to guard against data loss when using it, just as with any other application.</para></warning>

  <para>When you translate the documents in a project, OmegaT stores all your progress in the <link linkend="project.folder.project.save.tmx"
  endterm="project.folder.project.save.tmx.title"/>,
  file located in the project’s <link linkend="project.folder.omegat"
  endterm="project.folder.omegat.title"/> folder. That file is in fact a translation memory and is automatically saved at regular intervals. You can also use <link linkend="menus.project.save" endterm="menus.project.save.title"/> discretionally to make sure that your valuable work is saved.</para>

  <para>Beside of that, OmegaT also backs-up that file, by automatically creating a sequential number of copies (up to ten), marked with a timestamp, every time you open or reload your project.</para>

  <para>These backup filenames’ follow the pattern <filename>project_save.tmx.YYYYMMDDhhmm.bak</filename> where the final part is the time stamp indicating when the file was created: <code>YYYY</code>
  represents the 4-digit year, <code>MM</code> the month, <code>DD</code> the day of the month, and <code>hh</code>
  and <code>mm</code> indicate the hours and minutes.</para>

  <para>The file <filename>project_save.tmx.bak</filename> is automatically created when you open the project and is a copy of <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> at that moment.</para>
  
  <para>The file <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> always contains the most recent data.</para>
  
  <para>Consequently, if you believe that you have lost translation data, it might probably be safely stored in your most recent backup memory, which is usually less than ten minutes old or so.</para>

  <para>Proceed as follows:
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Close the project, preventing on any modification on the current status of the backup files.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Rename the current <filename>project_save.tmx </filename>file (to
      <filename>project_save.tmx.tmp</filename>, for example).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Select the backup translation memory most likely to contain the data
      you are looking for.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Rename it <filename>project_save.tmx</filename>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Reopen the project.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  </para>

  <para>This action will restore the status of the translation to the moment on which the selected backup was created. You may repeat this operation as needed for locating older situations. Keep an eye on safely storing all the different files you are renaming for eventual reuse. Also remember not modifying the project configuration or adding TMX files on the meantime, as that may affect the results.</para>

  <para>As a summary:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>To avoid losing important data, make regular copies of the file
      <filename>/omegat/project_save.tmx</filename> to a backup media, such as a
      USB key or an external hard drive, or to a cloud service.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Practice regularly "emergency" measures, like restoring translations
      from a project, to make sure you won't lose too much time the day you need
      to use those skills.</para>
    </listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>You can control the frequence on the file saving in the Preferences – <link linkend="dialogs.preferences.saving.and.output" endterm="dialogs.preferences.saving.and.output.title"/>.</para>
	</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <note><para>Be very cautious about making changes to the files in the source
  folder, to the segmentation rules, or to the file filters, partway through
  a project. Modifying either after you have started your translation could
  result in OmegaT becoming unable to find a segment that you have already
  translated.</para></note>
  
</section>
