<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="how.to.manage.right.to.left">
  <title id="how.to.manage.right.to.left.title">Manage RTL Languages</title>

   <para>The justification of source and target segments depends on the project languages. By default, left justification is used for left-to-right (LTR) languages and right justification for right-to-left (RTL) languages. You can toggle between the following three justification modes by pressing <keycombo><keycap>C</keycap><keycap>S</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo>: </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Default, as defined by the language</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Left</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Right</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Switching between modes changes both how the text is entered and displayed. Each mode can be used separately in the <guilabel>Editor</guilabel>, <guilabel>Fuzzy Matches</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Glossary</guilabel> panes by selecting the desired pane and toggling the justification mode. It can also be used in all OmegaT input fields, such as the <guilabel>Text Search</guilabel> window or the segmentation rules dialog, for example.</para>

    <para></para>

    <section id="how.to.manage.right.to.left.mixing.rtl.and.ltr">
      <title id="how.to.manage.right.to.left.mixing.rtl.and.ltr.title">Mixing RTL and LTR</title>

      <para>You can use the default (LTR) mode to write purely RTL text. However, it is often necessary to include LTR text, such as  OmegaT tags, product names that must retain their original LTR language direction, or placeholders in localization files, within an RTL document.  In such cases, you must switch to RTL mode to ensure the RTL (or, more precisely, bidirectional) text is displayed correctly. Note that OmegaT shows both the source and target in the same mode. Consequently,  if the source language is LTR and the target language is RTL, or vice versa, you will need to toggle back and forth between the two modes to read the source and enter the target easily.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="how.to.manage.right.to.left.omegat.tags.and.rtl">
      <title id="how.to.manage.right.to.left.omegat.tags.and.rtl.title">Tags in RTL Segments</title>

      <para>OmegaT tags are LTR strings. When translating between RTL and LTR languages, correctly reading the tags from the source and entering them properly in the target may require the translator to toggle between LTR and RTL modes numerous times.</para>

      <para>Therefore, translators are encouraged to remove style information from the original document whenever possible to limit the number of tags displayed in the editor.  Validate tags (using the <link linkend="menus.tools.check.issues" endterm="menus.tools.check.issues.title"></link> command) and produce translated documents regularly to catch any problems quickly. Hint: it may be simpler to  translate a plain text version of the document and add any necessary styling in the relevant application at a later stage.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="how.to.manage.right.to.left.creating.translated.rtl.documents">
      <title id="how.to.manage.right.to.left.creating.translated.rtl.documents.title">Translated Documents</title>

      <para>The translated document will be created in the same display direction as the original. You will have to change the text direction of the target document in its own application. </para>

      <para>Note that in Microsoft Word .docx files, a number of changes are made automatically:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Paragraphs, sections and tables are set to bidirectional text.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Runs (short sections of text in the same style) are set to RTL.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>With some file formats, such as ODF, it is also possible to modify the settings in the source file so that they are automatically applied to the target file, eliminating the need to set them every time you open it. </para>
    </section>
</section>
