<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="how.to.restore.your.data">
  <title id="how.to.restore.your.data.title">Restore your data</title>

  <warning><para>Although OmegaT is a robust application, you should take
  precautions to guard against data loss when using it, just as with any other
  application.</para>
  <para>Make regular and automatic backups of all your projects and files and
  regularly practice "emergency" measures, like restoring translations from a
  project, to make sure you won't lose too much time the day you need to use
  those skills.</para></warning>

  <para>When you translate the documents in a project, OmegaT stores all
  your progress in the <link linkend="project.folder.project.save.tmx"
  endterm="project.folder.project.save.tmx.title"></link> translation memory
  file located in the <link linkend="project.folder.omegat"
  endterm="project.folder.omegat.title"/> folder. That file is saved at regular intervals, and you can also use <link linkend="menus.project.save" endterm="menus.project.save.title"/> to make sure important data in the meanwhile.</para>

  <para>In that folder, OmegaT also automatically creates backup files of that translation memory  every time you open or reload a project. OmegaT stores up to 10 backup files there with names like <filename>project_save.tmx.YYYYMMDDhhmm.bak</filename> where the final part is the time stamp indicating when the file was created: <code>YYYY</code>
  represents the 4-digit year, <code>MM</code> the month, <code>DD</code> the day of the month, and <code>hh</code>
  and <code>mm</code> indicate the hours and minutes.</para>

  <para>The first backup is <filename>project_save.tmx.bak</filename>, which is a copy of <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> created when the project was opened. Then come the incremental backup files that are created as your translation progresses. <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> is always the file with the most recent data.</para>

  <para>If you believe that you have lost translation data, follow the steps
  below to restore the project to the most recent backup memory, which is
  usually less than ten minutes old or so.</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Close the project.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Rename the current <filename>project_save.tmx </filename>file (to
      <filename>project_save.tmx.tmp</filename>, for example).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Select the backup translation memory most likely to contain the data
      you are looking for.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Rename it <filename>project_save.tmx</filename>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Reopen the project.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>To avoid losing important data:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Make regular copies of the file
      <filename>/omegat/project_save.tmx</filename> to a backup media, such as a
      USB key or an external hard drive, or to a cloud service.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>While you are still familiarizing yourself with OmegaT, create
      translated files at regular intervals to make sure they contain the latest
      version of your translation.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Be very cautious about making changes to the files in the <link
      linkend="project.folder.source" endterm="project.folder.source.title"/>
      folder, or to the <link linkend="segmentation.rules"
      endterm="segmentation.rules.title">segmentation rules</link>, partway
      through a project. Modifying either source files or the segmentation rules
      after you have started your translation could result in OmegaT becoming
      unable to find a segment that you have already translated.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Consult the <link linkend="chapter.instant.start.guide"
      endterm="chapter.instant.start.guide.title">Instant Start Guide</link> and
      other sections of this manual to get started. Should you run into
      problems, post a message in the <ulink
      url="https://omegat.org/support">OmegaT user group</ulink>. Do not
      hesitate to post in the language you are most comfortable using.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
