<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="how.to.use.team.project">
  <title id="how.to.use.team.project.title">Use a Team Project</title>

  <para>After <link linkend="how.to.setup.team.project">setting up</link> the
  OmegaT team project on a server, the administrator will send you the
  information you need to access it.</para>

  <para>In most cases, this will consist of a URL indicating the location of
  the project, but in some cases it may be an
  <filename>omegat.project</filename> file containing the location of the
  project and, possibly <link
  linkend="how.to.setup.team.project.mapping.parameters">mappings</link>.
  The first time you access the project, you will have to download it and
  create a local copy on your system.</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>From a URL</para>

      <para>Click the <link
      endterm="menus.project.download.team.project.title"
      linkend="menus.project.download.team.project"/> command in the <link
      endterm="menus.project.title" linkend="menus.project"/> menu. This will
      bring up the <guilabel>Download Team Project</guilabel> dialog.</para>

      <para>Enter the URL provided by the team project manager in the
      <guilabel>Repository URL:</guilabel> field at the top of the dialog, and
      specify a folder for the project in the <guilabel>New Local Project
      Folder:</guilabel> field. Leave the <guilabel>Default branch</guilabel>
      option ticked unless the project administrator has provided instructions
      for using a custom branch.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>From an <filename>omegat.project</filename> file</para>

      <para>Put the <filename>omegat.project</filename> file in an empty
      folder, and open it in OmegaT. The project will automatically be
      downloaded to the folder containing that file.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <note>
    <para>Servers generally use two main types of authentication: entering a
    <emphasis>username/password</emphasis>, or
    <emphasis>SSH</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>If the server relies on username/password authentication, OmegaT
    will present you with an <guilabel>Authentication</guilabel> dialog to
    enter your username and password either when you first download the
    project from the <guilabel>Download Team Project</guilabel> dialog (if
    accessing from a URL), or when data is synchronized to the server for the
    first time (if accessing from an <filename>omegat.project</filename>
    file). OmegaT will then remember your credentials for that specific
    project unless you explicitly delete them.</para>

    <para>If the server uses SSH authentication, make sure you update your SSH
    configuration to include that server before attempting to download the
    project, otherwise you will get an authentication error and the project
    will fail to load.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Using a team project requires keeping a few differences from regular
  local projects in mind.</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Synchronization</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Synchronizing the project adds translations made by other team
        members to your local copy of the project, and makes your own
        translations available to the rest of the team. Only the contents of
        the two following files are synchronized: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><filename>project.save</filename></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><filename>glossary.txt</filename></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>

        <para>Although the <filename>omegat.project</filename> file is subject
        to special handling, described under <emphasis>Team project
        configuration</emphasis> below, all other files are overwritten with
        the version on the server.</para>

        <para>OmegaT synchronizes a team project when it is opened, reloaded,
        closed or saved. This means the automatic save function also regularly
        synchronizes your local project with the version on the server at the
        interval specified in the <link
        endterm="dialogs.preferences.saving.and.output.interval.title"
        linkend="dialogs.preferences.saving.and.output.interval"/> section of
        the <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem> dialog in the
        <guimenu>Options</guimenu> menu.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Team project configuration</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>As in regular local projects, the configuration of the team
        project is defined by the contents <filename>omegat.project</filename>
        file and the optional use of special files to for project-specific
        filters or segmentation rules.</para>

        <para>The first time the project is downloaded, OmegaT retrieves the
        <filename>omegat.project</filename> file from the server. This file
        defines the following parameters:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Basic project configuration:</emphasis> Source and
            languages, tokenizers, and the project folder hierarchy. In a team
            project, the basic configuration parameters of the local project
            are always overriden by the configuration on the server that was
            set by the project administrator.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Repository mappings</emphasis></para>

            <para>Details on mappings can be found in the <link
            linkend="how.to.setup.team.project.mapping.parameters">section 
            on setting up team projects</link>. From a user standpoint, the
            following rules apply to repository mappings.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>If no custom mappings have been defined for the remote
                project, but local mappings have been customized, the local
                settings are preserved without affeting the settings on the
                server</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If the remote project contains custom mappings, but the
                local project does not, the mappings from the server are
                applied to the local project.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If the remote project specifies a URL protocol and you
                download it using a different protocol, your local
                configuration will be preserved.</para>

                <para>For example, many hosting services support access to the
                same repository using either the SSH +Git or https protocol.
                OmegaT will respect the local protocol selection.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you first download the remote project using an
                <filename>omegat.project</filename>file provided by the
                project administrator, OmegaT will use the mappings in that
                file, if any.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If there is a conflict between the remote and local
                versions of the <filename>omegat.project</filename> and the
                local version is overwritten, OmegaT creates a backup file
                called <filename>omegat.project.YYYYMMDDhhmm.bak</filename>.
                The backup files are kept for a least ten days, and older
                backups are automatically deleted.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Optional project-specific settings:</emphasis> It
            is possible to customize the <link
            linkend="dialogs.project.properties.filters">file filters</link>
            and <link
            linkend="dialogs.project.properties.segmentation">segmentation
            rules</link> for the project. Such customized rules are stored in
            the <link endterm="project.folder.omegat.filters.title"
            linkend="project.folder.omegat.filters"/> and <link
            endterm="project.folder.omegat.segmentation.title"
            linkend="project.folder.omegat.segmentation"/> files in the <link
            linkend="project.folder.omegat.folder"><filename
            class="directory">omegat</filename> folder</link>.</para>

            <para>If the remote project contains either or both of those
            files, any local version of those files is always overwritten by
            the version from the remote project.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <warning>
          <para>Remember that any modifications to the local project
          configuration files will be overwritten by the versions on the
          server when the project is synchronized.</para>
        </warning>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Source files</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can use the following procedure to add or modify source
        files:</para>

        <para><orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Copy the new files to the <filename
              class="directory">source</filename> folder, or modify an
              existing file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use the <link
              endterm="menus.project.commit.source.files.title"
              linkend="menus.project.commit.source.files"/> command to upload
              the files to the server.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist> When you modify a source file you must execute the
        <command>Commit</command> command before the project is saved
        (automatically or manually), reloaded, or closed..</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Target files</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>After you generate the target files, You can use the <link
        endterm="menus.project.commit.target.files.title"
        linkend="menus.project.commit.target.files"/> command to add them to
        the server.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Deleting files</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Files in a team project cannot be deleted from OmegaT or the
        local file system. (They will be restored the next time the project is
        synchronized. This task is normally performed by the project
        administrator.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Working offline</term>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can open a team project and work on it offline. All changes
        will be synchronized the next time a connection is available.</para>

        <para>There are two ways work offline:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Disconnect from the network before opening the
            project.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Open the project from the command line with the
            <parameter>--no-team</parameter> option.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>
