<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="how.to.create.new.project">
  <title id="how.to.create.new.project.title">Create a New Project</title>

    <para>To start using OmegaT, you first have to create a project to hold all
    your files, such as your source files, translation memories, glossaries, and
    eventually your translated files. To create a new project, use <link
    linkend="menus.project.new"
    endterm="menus.project.new.title"/>, select a folder, and type a
    name for your project.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Since an OmegaT project is simply a set of folders and subfolders,
      you are entering the name of the folder that will hold your
      project. Alternatively, you can choose an existing
      <emphasis>empty</emphasis> folder created beforehand. Keep in mind that
      OmegaT cannot create a project in a folder that already contains files or
      subfolders.</para>
    </note>

    <para>If you don't remember where your project is, you can use <link
    linkend="menus.project.open.recent"
    endterm="menus.project.open.recent.title"/>.</para>

    <para>The <guilabel>Create New Project</guilabel> dialog opens after you
    have named your project. The dialog is identical to the <link
    linkend="dialogs.project.properties"
    endterm="dialogs.project.properties.title"/> dialog that you access with
    <link linkend="menus.project.properties"
    endterm="menus.project.properties.title"/>. At the top of that dialog,
    select the languages of your source and translated files, and click the
    <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button to continue.</para>

    <para>Once you have created the project, you can return to this dialog at
    any time by using <link linkend="menus.project.properties"
    endterm="menus.project.properties.title"/>.</para>

	<note><para>The structure of a project can be modified at any moment during
	translation. You can point at new resource folders from that dialog and
	OmegaT will just ask you to reload the project to take the new locations
	into account.</para></note>
	
    <para>The <link linkend="windows.project.files"
    endterm="windows.project.files.title"/> dialog opens next.</para>

	<para>Click on <link linkend="windows.project.files.copy.files"
	endterm="windows.project.files.copy.files.title"/> or <link
	linkend="windows.project.files.download.page"
	endterm="windows.project.files.download.page.title"/> and select your source
	files. OmegaT will then copy the selected files to the <link
	linkend="project.folder.source" endterm="project.folder.source.title"/>
	folder of your newly created project. You can close the <link
	linkend="windows.project.files" endterm="windows.project.files.title"/>
	dialog after the source files have loaded in the <link
	linkend="panes.editor" endterm="panes.editor.title"/> pane.</para>
  </section>
