<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.instant.start.guide">
  <title>Learn to use OmegaT in 5 minutes!</title>

  <section id="create.and.open.new.project">
    <title>Set up a new project
    <indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Project</primary>
        <secondary>Create / open new</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><remark>Note:</remark> On an Apple Mac, use the <keycap>Command</keycap> 
    key instead of the <keycap>Control</keycap> key.</para>

      <indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Menu Project</primary>
        <secondary>New...</secondary>
      </indexterm>

    <para>To start using OmegaT, first create a project that will hold all
    your files, such as your source file, translation memories, glossaries,
    and eventually your translated file. In the <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    menu, select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>New...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> 
    and type a name for your project. Remember where you are
    creating the project, because you will need to return to it later.</para>

    <para>After you give your project a name, the <guilabel>Create New Project</guilabel> dialog
    will open. At the top of that dialog, select your source file's language
    and the language that your translated file will be, and click
    <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to continue.</para>

    <para>If you are interested in other settings of this dialog,
    you can return to it any time by pressing <keycap>Ctrl+E.</keycap></para>

    <para>Next, the <guilabel>Project Files</guilabel> dialog opens. Click on <guibutton>Copy Files to Source Folder...</guibutton> to select your source files. OmegaT will then copy the selected
    files to the <filename>/source/</filename> subfolder of your newly created
    project. After the source files have loaded in the <guilabel>Editor</guilabel> pane, you can
    close the <guilabel>Project Files</guilabel> dialog.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="translate.the.segments.one.by.one">
    <title>Translate the file</title>

    <para>OmegaT will present one segment at a time for you to translate.
    After you have translated each segment, press <keycap>Ctrl+U</keycap> to
    move to the next untranslated segment (or <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+U</keycap> to
    move to the next translated segment). Whenever you want to see what your
    translation will look like in its final format, press
    <keycap>Ctrl+D</keycap> to generate the translated documents, which will be
    created in the <filename>/target/</filename> subfolder of your project folder. During
    translation, use the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> and <guimenu>Go To</guimenu>
    menus to perform various useful functions.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Validate your tags</title>

    <para>If your source files are formatted files, e.g. Microsoft Word,
    LibreOffice Writer or HTML, OmegaT will convert the formatting into tags
    that surround the text that you translate. Often documents will also have
    tags that have nothing to do with formatting, but which are also
    important in the source files (and in the translated files). A source
    sentence might look like:
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="justify" fileref="images/InstantGuide_1.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="justify" fileref="images/InstantGuide_1.png"
                   width="40%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </para>

    <para>OmegaT, however, will present this sentence in the following
    fashion:
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="justify" fileref="images/InstantGuide_2.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="justify" fileref="images/InstantGuide_2.png"
                   width="45%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </para>
    
    <para>The tags in OmegaT are greyed, so they are easy to recognise. They
    are not protected, so that you can delete them, enter them by hand or move
    them around in the target sentence. However, if you made mistakes when you
    typed the formatting tags, your translated files might fail to open.
    Therefore, press <keycap>Ctrl+T</keycap> before you generate your
    translated files, to validate that your tags are correct.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Generate the translated file</title>

    <para>Once you have made certain that there are no tag errors in your
    translation, press <keycap>Ctrl+D</keycap> to generate the target files,
    which will be created in the <filename>/target/</filename> subfolder of
    your project folder.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Few more things to remember</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If a file does not load into the <guilabel>Editor</guilabel> pane, then it could be that it is in a format that doesn't work in OmegaT. See
        <link linkend="chapter.file.filters">File Filters</link> for a list of file formats that OmegaT can handle.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can create a new project for each new job, and you can add
        new source files to a project at anytime time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To remind yourself of the project's initial settings, open the
        project settings dialog by pressing <keycap>Ctrl+E</keycap>. To see a
        list of files in the project, open the <guilabel>Project Files</guilabel> dialog by
        pressing <keycap>Ctrl+L</keycap>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>At the end of your translation, OmegaT exports three translation
        memories called <filename>level1</filename>, <filename>level2</filename> and <filename>omegat</filename> to your project
        folder. The <filename>level1</filename> and <filename>level2</filename> memories can be shared with users of
        other translation programs. The memory named <filename>omegat</filename> can be used by
        OmegaT itself, in future projects that you create. If you place such
        translation memory files in the <filename>/tm/</filename> subfolder of a project,
        OmegaT will automatically search them for similar segments, called
        "fuzzy matches".</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can add a new term to the glossary by pressing
        <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+G</keycap>, or copy existing glossaries to
        the <filename>/glossary/</filename> subfolder of your project folder,
        and OmegaT will automatically look up words in them.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>It is often useful to search for words and phrases in the source
        text and in your translation, so press <keycap>Ctrl+F</keycap> for the
        <guilabel>Text Search</guilabel> dialog at any time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>For a more comprehensive introduction see <ulink
        url="http://www.omegat.org/en/tutorial/OmegaT%20for%20Beginners.pdf">OmegaT
        for beginners</ulink> on the OmegaT web site. If you need assistance
        with any aspect of OmegaT, feel free to join the <ulink
        url="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/OmegaT/">OmegaT users
        group.</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
