<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="panes">
  <title>Panes</title>

  <para>The main window consists of several panes, the main menu and a status
  bar. You can change the position of any pane or even undock it to a separate
  window by clicking and dragging the pane by its name. Depending on the pane
  status, different signs can appear at its top right corner:</para>

  <note>
    <para>If you can not see all the panes (be it opened or minimized),
    pressing <guisubmenu> Options &gt; Restore Main Window </guisubmenu>will
    restore them to the state, defined in the installation.</para>
  </note>

  <table>
    <title>Pane widgets</title>

    <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec align="left" colnum="1"/>

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject role="html">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Minimize.png" width="60%"/>
              </imageobject>

              <imageobject role="fo">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Minimize.png" width="40%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></entry>

          <entry>minimizes the pane, so that only its name is shown at the
          bottom of the window</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject role="html">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Maximize.png" width="60%"/>
              </imageobject>

              <imageobject role="fo">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Maximize.png" width="40%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></entry>

          <entry>maximizes the pane</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject role="html">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Restore.png" width="60%"/>
              </imageobject>

              <imageobject role="fo">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Restore.png" width="40%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></entry>

          <entry>restores the layout before the maximizing step</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject role="html">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Undock.png" width="60%"/>
              </imageobject>

              <imageobject role="fo">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Undock.png" width="40%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></entry>

          <entry>undocks the pane from the main window</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject role="html">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Dock.png" width="60%"/>
              </imageobject>

              <imageobject role="fo">
                <imagedata fileref="images/Dock.png" width="40%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></entry>

          <entry>puts the pane back within the main window</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>You can overlap panes if desired. When this is done the panes display
  a tab at the top. The separators between the panes can be dragged to resize
  panes. Should you lose track of your changes to the user interface, you can
  use <guimenuitem> Options → Restore the main window</guimenuitem> any time to
  return to the original layout.</para>

  <para>It is possible to drag and drop files to each pane, which will react
  accordingly. <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Editor pane: If an OmegaT project file
        (<filename>omegat.project</filename>) is dropped on this pane, the
        corresponding project will be opened, closing first any opened
        project. Other dropped files will be copied to the
        <filename>source</filename> folder. This applies also to the <link linkend="windows.projectfiles">Project files</link> window.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fuzzy Matches pane: Dropped <filename>.tmx</filename> files will
        be copied to the <filename>tm</filename> folder.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Glossary pane: Dropped files with known glossary extensions
        (<filename>.txt</filename>, <filename>.tab</filename>, etc.) will be
        copied to the <filename>glossary</filename> folder.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <section id="editor.pane">
    <title>Editor</title>

    <para>This is where you type and edit your translation. The Editor pane
    displays the text of the partially translated document: the text already
    translated is displayed in translation while the untranslated text is
    displayed in the original language. The displayed text is split into
    segments and you may scroll through the document and double-click on any
    segment to open and edit it. In the above case, the segments already
    translated are shown in yellow.</para>

    <para>One of the above segments is the current segment. It is the segment
    that is displayed in two parts. The upper part is in the source language,
    in bold characters with a green background color, the lower part is the
    editing field, ended by a marker: the marker is <literal>&lt;segment nnnn&gt;</literal> where
    nnnn is a number of the segment in the project. Use the upper part as a
    reference and replace or modify the contents of the editing field with
    your translation.</para>

    <para>Note: the segment marker displays <literal>&lt;segment
    nnnn +yy more&gt; when the segment is non-unique. In that case, yy is the
    number of other occurrences of the segment in the
    project.</literal></para>

    <para>Depending upon the preferred editing behavior, the editing field for
    the untranslated segment may be empty, contain the source text, or contain
    the translation of the string most similar to the one to be translated.
    When you move to another segment, the translation is validated and stored.
    If you want the translation to be the same as the source, simply make the
    editing field empty by removing all the text (select all with
    <keycap>Ctrl+A</keycap> and delete with <keycap>Del</keycap>). OmegaT is
    able to store translations that are identical to the source. This is
    useful for documents that contain trade marks, names or other proper
    nouns, or parts in a third language that do not require translation. See
    <emphasis>Translation editing</emphasis> for more details.</para>

    <para>If you right click on the Editor pane, a pop-up menu opens,
    offering<emphasis role="bold"> Cut, Copy, Paste</emphasis> (i.e. same
    functions as <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>X</keycap>
      </keycombo>, <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>C</keycap>
      </keycombo> and <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>V</keycap>
      </keycombo>), <emphasis role="bold">GoTo segment</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="bold">Add glossary entry</emphasis> functions. In
    addition, when the right click occurs on an opened segment, other options
    concerning <emphasis role="bold">Alternative translations</emphasis> are
    proposed, for example to to jump to another instance of non-unique
    segments.</para>

    <para>It is possible to drag text from anywhere in the main window and to
    drop it within the segment. Texted dragged from outside the target segment
    is copied, while text dragged from within the segment is moved.</para>

    <para>By default, it is not possible to select words in the source segment
    using the keyboard rather than the mouse. Pressing <keycap>F2</keycap> key
    allows to move the cursor into the source segment (or anywhere in the
    editor) with the keyboard arrows. In this mode, &quot;<guilabel>Cursor lock
    off</guilabel>&quot; is displayed at the bottom of the pane. To come back to
    the standard mode &quot;<guilabel>Cursor lock on</guilabel>&quot;, press
    <keycap>F2</keycap> again.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fuzzy Matches</title>

    <para>The match viewer shows the most similar segments from translation
    memories, both from internal project translation memory created in real
    time as you translate your project and from ancillary translation memories
    you have imported from your earlier jobs, or received from your client or
    translation agency.</para>

    <para>When you move to the next segment, the first fuzzy match (the one
    with the best matching percentage) is automatically selected. You may
    select a different match by pressing <guimenuitem>Ctrl+2, 3, 4, or
    5</guimenuitem>. Of course, pressing <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>5</keycap>
      </keycombo> will have no effect, if there is no match #5. To use the
    selected match in your translation, use
    <guimenuitem>Ctrl+R</guimenuitem> to replace the target field with the match or use
    <guimenuitem>Ctrl+I </guimenuitem> to insert it at the cursor position.</para>

    <para>The matching percentage is roughly equivalent to taking the number
    of common words in the matched and the matching segment and dividing by
    the number of words in the longer of the two. The selected fuzzy match is
    highlighted in bold, words that are missing in the segment you are
    translating are colored blue and words adjacent to the missing parts
    green. In the above example the source segment is <emphasis role="bold">Context menu command</emphasis>. The top match is 100%,
    because all words match. So do the next two matches, and the match #4 is
    similar, but different. The line with the matching percentage also
    includes the name of the translation memory containing the match. If there's no file name displayed,
    the source is the internal project translation memory. Orphan
    segments (the match #2) describe segments in the default project
    translation memory that have no corresponding source segment.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Glossary</title>

    <para>The Glossary pane allows you to access your own collection of
    expressions and specialist terminology which you have built up in your
    glossary files. It shows translation of terms found in the current
    segment. The source segment in the example below was “<emphasis>Context
    menu command</emphasis>”, as in the Fuzzy Matches example above, and the
    terms shown were found in the glossaries, available (Microsoft's Term
    collection and Slovenian Linux User group Glossary).</para>

    <para>If you have TransTips option activated (<guimenuitem>Options →
    TransTips</guimenuitem>), you can right click on the highlighted word in
    the source segment to open a pop-up menu with suggested translation, as
    offered by your glossary. Selecting one of them will insert it at the
    current cursor position into the target segment. You can also highlight
    your preferred alternative in the glossary pane and insert it into the
    target by right clicking on the selection.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Dictionary</title>

    <para>Dictionaries are the electronic equivalents of printed dictionaries
    like Merriam Webster, Duden, Larousse etc., that you may have on your
    desk. See more about them in the chapter on <link linkend="appendix.dictionaries">Dictionaries</link></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Machine Translation</title>

    <para>The machine translation pane, when opened, contains the suggestions
    by machine translation tools for the current segment. Press
    <keysym>Ctrl+M</keysym> to replace the translation of the current segment
    with the suggested translation.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multiple Translations</title>

    <para>A given source segment may require several different translations,
    depending on the context. If the current translation of the segment does
    not fit, the user can select <guisubmenu>Edit → Create Alternative
    Translation</guisubmenu>. The target text entered after that will be
    treated as an alternative translation of the source segment. You can
    define one of the alternative - for instance the most probable among them
    - as default translation by selecting <guisubmenu>Edit → Use as Default
    Translation</guisubmenu></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Notes</title>

    <para>The translator can add notes to the opened segment, for instance to
    come back later to the segment and redo the translation, check that
    alternative translations are correct or to ask colleagues for their
    opinion. You can browse through notes using <guisubmenu>GoTo → Next
    Note</guisubmenu> and <guisubmenu>GoTo → Previous
    Note</guisubmenu>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Comments</title>

    <para>Some of the file formats, specialized for translation work, for
    instance PO, allow the inclusion of comments. This way the translator can
    be provided the context about the segment to be translated. In the example
    below, the author of the PO file included a warning for the translator to
    check the length of the translation:</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Status bar</title>

    <para>The status bar displays work-flow related messages at the bottom of
    the main window. This bar gives the user feedback on specific operations
    that are in progress. It also displays the number of fuzzy and glossary
    matches for the current segment.</para>

    <para>The counters in the lower right corner keep track of the progress of
    the translation (numbers in the left hand column refer to the figure
    above):</para>

    <table>
      <title>Main Window - counters</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="left" colnum="1"/>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>27/27</entry>

            <entry>number of segments - translated vs total for the current
            file</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>9319/16338</entry>

            <entry>number of unique segments - translated vs total in the
            project</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>31175</entry>

            <entry>total number of segments (including repeats) in the
            project</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>103/114</entry>

            <entry>number of source and target characters in the current
            segment</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>From a practical point of view, the most important pair of numbers
    is the second pair: it tells, how much you have done so far, in relation
    to the total or second number. The project in the example is evidently
    finished, as all the unique segments have been translated.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
