<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="project.folder">
  <title id="project.folder.title">Project Folder</title>

  <para>An OmegaT project consists of a set of folders and files that contain the resources used for translating.</para>
  <para>A project is a folder containing, at a minimum, the following files and folder:</para>
  
  <variablelist>
	<varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat">
	  <term id="project.folder.omegat.title">omegat/</term>
	  <listitem><para>This is the project folder that always contains <link linkend="project.folder.project.save.tmx" endterm="project.folder.project.save.tmx.title"/>, the project translation memory, and <link linkend="project.folder.project.stats" endterm="project.folder.project.stats.title"/>, the statistics data file for the project.</para>
	  <para>Other files will be added over the course of a translation project.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.project.file">
	  <term id="project.folder.omegat.project.file.title">omegat.project</term>
	  <listitem><para>This file contains the properties of the project and also acts as an <emphasis>address book</emphasis> that specifies where project resources are located. By default, a newly created project will contain all the required resources within its folder, and those resources are assigned the default names below.
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><link linkend="project.folder.source" endterm="project.folder.source.title"/>: the folder that contains the source files</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para><link linkend="project.folder.target" endterm="project.folder.target.title"/>: the folder where the target files are created</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para><link linkend="project.folder.glossary" endterm="project.folder.glossary.title"/>: the folder that contains the glossaries</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para><link linkend="project.folder.glossary.txt" endterm="project.folder.glossary.txt.title"/>: the project writable glossary</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para><link linkend="project.folder.tm" endterm="project.folder.tm.title"/>: the folder that contains the reference translation memories</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para><link linkend="project.folder.dictionary" endterm="project.folder.dictionary.title"/>: the folder that contains the dictionaries</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	  The information contained in <filename>omegat.project</filename> also includes the source and target languages, their respective tokenizers, the type of segmentation used, etc.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>You can assign locations other than the default ones to the various resources either when you create the project, or later on.</para>

  <para>For example, you can

  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>instruct OmegaT to create the translated files in a shared folder outside the project folder, in a location easily accessible to your reviewer, or</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>instruct OmegaT to use a glossary folder from a separate but related project, or</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>instruct OmegaT to use a reference translation memory folder that you have set up for related projects,</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  and so on.</para>

  <para>You can access the project folder and its folders with the <link linkend="menus.project.access.project.contents" endterm="menus.project.access.project.contents.title"/> command in the <link linkend="menus.project" endterm="menus.project.title"/> menu.</para>

  <para>Creating a project gives it a core hierarchy, but its final structure is not fixed. You can always remove or add files and folders to the project.</para>

  <note><para>You can also create OmegaT projects either manually or with scripts by copying a set of prewritten files to a new folder:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Any given folder that contains a valid <filename>omegat.project</filename> file will be recognized by OmegaT as being a translation project.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
  <para>If the folder is an empty repository and the <filename>omegat.project</filename> file contains remote repository information, the project will be recognized by OmegaT as being a team project:
	<programlisting>...
    &lt;external_command&gt;&lt;/external_command&gt;
    &lt;repositories&gt;
        &lt;repository type="git" url="https://URL/OF/THE/REMOTE/PROJECT/REPOSITORY"&gt;
            &lt;mapping local="/" repository="/"/&gt;
        &lt;/repository&gt;
    &lt;/repositories&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;</programlisting>
  See <link linkend="how.to.setup.team.project" endterm="how.to.setup.team.project.title"/> for details.</para>
	</listitem>
  </itemizedlist></note>
  
  <section id="project.folder.source">
    <title id="project.folder.source.title">source</title>
    <para>The source folder contains the files to translate.</para>
	<para>The contents of the files in a format that OmegaT supports will be displayed in the <link linkend="panes.editor" endterm="panes.editor.title"/> pane. See Preferences – <link linkend="dialogs.preferences.file.filters" endterm="dialogs.preferences.file.filters.title"/> for details.</para>

	<para>You can freely add or remove files from that folder at any time. You can also structure the source folder in any form you like.</para>
	<para>If your translation project involves a number of folders and you feel like working on one folder at a time, change the <link linkend="dialogs.project.properties.file.locations.source.files" endterm="dialogs.project.properties.file.locations.source.files.title"/> as you wish.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="project.folder.target">
    <title id="project.folder.target.title">target</title>
    <para>This folder is initially empty. It is populated every time you use <link linkend="menus.project.create.translated.documents" endterm="menus.project.create.translated.documents.title"/> or <link linkend="menus.project.create.current.translated.document" endterm="menus.project.create.current.translated.document.title"/>. The files in the <link linkend="project.folder.source" endterm="project.folder.source.title"/> folder, whether fully translated or not, are then generated here, using the same hierarchy as in the source contents.</para>
	<para>The files created here will reflect the current state of the translation. Untranslated segments will remain in the source language.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="project.folder.tm">
    <title id="project.folder.tm.title">tm</title>
    <para>This folder can contain any number of bilingual reference documents (TMX files, but also any file in a bilingual format supported by OmegaT).</para>
	
	<para>To remind you that a match was inserted by OmegaT and not by you, set a prefix in Preferences – <link linkend="dialogs.preferences.editor.insert.the.best.fuzzy.match" endterm="dialogs.preferences.editor.insert.the.best.fuzzy.match.title"/>. OmegaT will add that prefix to the inserted match.</para> 
    <para>The contents of the translation memories present suggestions for the text to translate. Any text with a translation in those files will show up in the Fuzzy Matches pane, if it is sufficiently similar to the text in the current segment.</para>
    <para>TMX files are read in the order of their names, and the segments within a file are read sequentially.</para>
    <note><para>TMX files compressed in the gzip format can also be read by OmegaT.</para></note>

<variablelist>
    <varlistentry id="project.folder.tm.auto">
      <term id="project.folder.tm.auto.title">tm/auto</term>
	  <listitem>
	  <para>This folder is made for reliable references files that can automatically fill exactly matching and not yet translated segments.</para>
      <para>Translations from TMX files placed in this folder are automatically inserted in matching segments without the automatic prefix, making it unnecessary to confirm these segments. Translations coming from this folder are considered to be <emphasis>as</emphasis> reliable as the current project memory.</para>

	  <note><para>Only the <filename>tm/auto</filename> folder is automatically generated at project creation. You must manually create and fill any other <filename>tm</filename> folder that you want to use.</para></note>

	  <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Put the applicable memories in the <filename class="directory">tm/auto</filename> folder.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open the project. You will see that segments identical to source segments in those memories are already filled in. They will be highlighted in orange if you have checked the <link linkend="menus.view.mark.auto.populated.segments" endterm="menus.view.mark.auto.populated.segments.title"/> option in the <link linkend="menus.view" endterm="menus.view.title"/> menu.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make a minor change anywhere in the project and save it. This will add the translations loaded from the tm/auto folder to the main <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> file.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
	  
      <warning><para>If you remove a TMX file from <filename class="directory">tm/auto</filename> before Step 3, none of its automatically inserted translations will be kept.</para></warning>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

    <varlistentry id="project.folder.tm.enforce">
      <term id="project.folder.tm.enforce.title">tm/enforce</term>
	  <listitem>
	  <para>This folder is made for reliable references files that will automatically overwrite or fill exactly matching segments.</para>

      <para>Translations from TMX files placed in this folder are automatically inserted in matching segments without the automatic prefix, making it unnecessary to confirm these segments. Translations coming from this folder are considered to be <emphasis>more</emphasis> reliable than the current project memory.</para>

      <para>If you have no doubt that a given TMX contains more accurate translations than the current <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> file, put that TMX in the <filename class="directory">tm/enforce</filename> folder to overwrite the existing translations unconditionally.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Put the applicable memories in the <filename class="directory">tm/enforce</filename> folder.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open the project. You will see that segments identical to source segments in those memories are already filled in.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make a minor change anywhere in the project and save. This updates the <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make a decision about the immutability of the enforced segments:
		  <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
              <para>If they <emphasis>don't need</emphasis> to remain immutable to further changes,  remove the TMX from <filename class="directory">tm/enforce</filename>.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
              <para>If they <emphasis>do need</emphasis> to remain immutable to further changes, leave the TMX in <filename class="directory">tm/enforce</filename>. Any modification to the segments that come from these memories will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be taken into account.</para>
			</listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
	  
      <warning><para>If  you remove a TMX file from <filename class="directory">tm/enforce</filename> before Step 3, none of the enforced translations will be kept.</para></warning>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

    <varlistentry id="project.folder.tm.mt">
      <term id="project.folder.tm.mt.title">tm/mt</term>
	  <listitem>
      <para>The background of the active segment changes to red when a match is inserted from a TMX contained in the <filename class="directory">mt</filename> folder. The background is restored to normal when you leave the segment or when you modify the segment.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
    <varlistentry id="project.folder.tm.penalty">
      <term id="project.folder.tm.penalty.title">tm/penalty-xxx</term>
	  <listitem>
		<para>It can be useful to distinguish between high-quality translation memories and other memories that, due to the subject matter, client, revision status, or other factors,are less reliable. The score of matches from translation memories in folders named <filename class="directory">penalty-xxx</filename> (where xxx is a number between 0 and 100), is decreased by an amount corresponding to the value in the name of the folder. For example, a 100% match in a TMX, stored in a folder called <filename class="directory">penalty-30</filename> becomes a 70% match. The penalty applies to all three match percentages. Scores of 75, 80 and 90 for a match are lowered to 45, 50 and 60.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

    <varlistentry id="project.folder.tm.tmx2source">
      <term id="project.folder.tm.tmx2source.title">tm/tmx2source</term>
	  <listitem>
  <para>OmegaT displays fuzzy matches in the <link linkend="panes.fuzzy.matches"
  endterm="panes.fuzzy.matches.title"/> pane. Such matches are by default
  limited to the source and target languages defined in <link
  linkend="dialogs.project.properties"
  endterm="dialogs.project.properties.title"/>, but you can also add matches in languages that are not the target language. See <link linkend="dialog.preferences.tm.matches.other.languages" endterm="dialog.preferences.tm.matches.other.languages.title"/> for details.</para>

  <para>With OmegaT, you can display a third language <emphasis>right
  under</emphasis> the source segment to use as a third language reference. See
  <link linkend="how.to.tm.bridge.two.languages"
  endterm="how.to.tm.bridge.two.languages.title"/> for details.</para>
      </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
	
	<note><para>You can combine folders to create new functions. For example, a 10% penalty folder within the machine translation folder: <filename>tm/mt/penalty-010</filename> would never generate 100% matches that could otherwise be automatically inserted by OmegaT, and would always set a red background to the match whenever it is inserted.</para></note>
  </section>

  <section id="project.folder.dictionary">
    <title id="project.folder.dictionary.title">dictionary</title>
    <para>This folder is initially empty, and is used to store any dictionaries you add to the project.</para>

	<para>Dictionary terms that match parts of the segment are displayed in the
	<link linkend="panes.dictionary" endterm="panes.dictionary.title"/> pane. See
	Preferences – <link linkend="dialogs.preferences.dictionary"
	endterm="dialogs.preferences.dictionary.title"/> for details.</para>

    <para>OmegaT supports dictionaries in the StarDict or in the Lingvo DSL
    format. You can find some dictionaries on the <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/p/omegat/wiki/Reference%20Material/">OmegaT
        Wiki</ulink>. To install the dictionaries:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>download the file - it should be a tarball archive (extension
        <filename>tar.bz</filename> or <filename>tar.bz2</filename>),</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>extract its contents into this folder. There should be three files
        per dictionary, with extensions <filename>dz</filename>,
        <filename>idx</filename> and <filename>ifo</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
	<para>If you want to remove words from potential dictionary matches, add an
	<filename>ignore.txt</filename> encoded in UTF-8 to the folder. The file
	must have one word per line. All the words contained in that list will be
	ignored by OmegaT when matching segment terms in the installed
	dictionaries.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="project.folder.glossary">
    <title id="project.folder.glossary.title">glossary</title>
    <para>This folder is initially empty. It is used to store the default writable glossary and any other glossaries you use in the project. See <link linkend="app.glossaries" endterm="app.glossaries.title"/> for details.</para>

	<variablelist>
      <varlistentry id="project.folder.glossary.txt">
        <term id="project.folder.glossary.txt.title">glossary.txt</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the project writeable glossary. It is created the first
          time you use <link linkend="menus.edit.create.glossary.entry"
          endterm="menus.edit.create.glossary.entry.title"/>.</para>
		  <para>You can access it with <link
		  linkend="menus.project.access.project.contents.title"
		  endterm="menus.project.access.project.contents.title"/>, open it in a
		  text editor, modify it with a text editor. As soon as you have saved
		  your modifications, they will be taken into account by OmegaT.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="project.folder.omegat.folder">
    <title id="project.folder.omegat.folder.title">omegat</title>
    <para>The <filename class="directory">omegat</filename> folder contains, at a minimum, the <link linkend="project.folder.project.save.tmx" endterm="project.folder.project.save.tmx.title"/> and <link linkend="project.folder.project.stats" endterm="project.folder.project.stats.title"/> files. It may also include several other files.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry id="project.folder.project.save.tmx">
        <term id="project.folder.project.save.tmx.title">project_save.tmx</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the most important file in the project. An empty file is automatically generated when you create a new project, and is gradually filled with the translations of the text in files located in the <link linkend="project.folder.source" endterm="project.folder.source.title"/> folder.</para>
		  <para>It constitutes the working translation memory of the project.</para>
		  <para>OmegaT regularly backs-up that file. See <link linkend="how.to.restore.your.data" endterm="how.to.restore.your.data.title"/> for details.</para>
		          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	  
	<varlistentry id="project.folder.project.save.tmx.bak">
	  <term id="project.folder.project.save.tmx.bak.title">project_save.tmx.bak</term>
	  <listitem><para>This file is a backup of <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> and is automatically recreated everytime <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> has been modified: either after using <link linkend="menus.project.save" endterm="menus.project.save.title"/>, or as a regular backup every 3 minutes by default. See <link linkend="dialog.preferences.saving.and.output.interval" endterm="dialog.preferences.saving.and.output.interval.title"/> for details.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry id="project.folder.project.save.tmx.timestamp.bak">
	  <term id="project.folder.project.save.tmx.timestamp.bak.title">project_save.tmx.timestamp.bak</term>
	  <listitem><para>Every time a project is loaded, OmegaT creates a backup of <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> with the name <filename>project_save.tmx.[time stamp].bak</filename>. OmegaT keeps up to 10 of those files.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="project.folder.project.stats">
        <term id="project.folder.project.stats.title">project_stats.txt</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the statistics file for the whole project. It is updated each time the project is reloaded.</para>
		  <para>You can also update it with the <link linkend="menus.tools.statistics" endterm="menus.tools.statistics.title"/> command in the <link linkend="menus.tools" endterm="menus.tools.title"/> menu.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	  
      <varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.project.stats.match">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.project.stats.match.title">project_stats_match.txt</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This file contains the latest project match statistics, which are generated by the <link linkend="menus.tools.match.statistics" endterm="menus.tools.match.statistics.title"/> command in the <link linkend="menus.tools" endterm="menus.tools.title"/> menu.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.project.stats.match.per.file">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.project.stats.match.per.file.title">project_stats_match_per_file.txt</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This file contains the latest project match statistics by file, which are generated by the <link linkend="menus.tools.match.statistics.per.file" endterm="menus.tools.match.statistics.per.file.title"/> command in the <link linkend="menus.tools" endterm="menus.tools.title"/> menu.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="
						project.folder.omegat.spellcheck">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.ignored.words.title">ignored_words.txt</term>
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.learned.words">learned_words.txt</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>These files are created and used by the spellchecker. You can
          add terms  by right-clicking on a word marked as incorrect and
          selecting <guimenuitem>Ignore All</guimenuitem> (for words to skip
          during spellchecking), or <guimenuitem>Add to Dictionary</guimenuitem>
          (for words to accept as correct), respectively, from the <link
          linkend="panes.editor.context.menu"
          endterm="panes.editor.context.menu.title"/>.</para>

		  <para>If you already have a collection of words you want the
		  spellchecker to ignore or accept, simply save them in text files with
		  the corresponding names, and copy the files to the <link
		  linkend="project.folder.omegat.folder"
		  endterm="project.folder.omegat.folder.title"/> folder of your current
		  project.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.segmentation">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.segmentation.title">segmentation.conf</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This file contains the project-specific segmentation rules.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.filters">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.filters.title">filters.xml</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This file contains the project-specific file filters.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
	  
      <varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.uiLayout">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.uiLayout.title">uiLayout.xml</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This file contains the project-specific GUI settings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.finder">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.finder.title">finder.xml</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This file contains the project-specific external searches.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.file.order">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.file.order.title">files_order.txt</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This file is created if you manually change the order of the files in the <link linkend="windows.project.files" endterm="windows.project.files.title"/> window.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="project.folder.omegat.last.entry">
        <term id="project.folder.omegat.last.entry.title">last_entry.properties</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This file keeps a record of the last segment you visited, including its number, its source contents, the file name and the date, so that you can come back to it when you reload/relaunch the project.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>	  
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="project.folder.omegat.project">
    <title id="project.folder.omegat.project.title">omegat.project</title>
    <para>This file contains the project parameters defined in the <link linkend="dialogs.project.properties" endterm="dialogs.project.properties.title"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="project.folder.repositories">
    <title id="project.folder.repositories.title">.repositories</title>
    <para>In a team project, this folder contains a versioned copy of the
    project tree structure linked directly to the remote server.</para>
    <para>You can make changes to the remote files (such as deleting or replacing them) by making your changes in this folder and using a Git or SVN client to synchronize them with the remote server. See <link linkend="how.to.setup.team.project" endterm="how.to.setup.team.project.title"/> for details.</para>
    <para>In some operating systems, this folder is hidden by default. Turn on the option to show hidden files in your system to make it visible.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
