<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="project.folder">
  <title>Project folder</title>

  <para>An OmegaT project is a folder containing files and subfolders.</para>

  <section>
    <title>source</title>

    <para>The source subfolder contains files to be translated. You can add
    the files to it later. Note that the structure of the source subfolder may
    take any form you like. If the files to be translated are parts of a tree
    structure (as in a website), you need only specify the top-level subfolder
    and OmegaT will maintain the entire contents, while keeping the tree
    structure intact.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>target</title>

    <para>This subfolder is initially empty. To add contents to it, select
    <menuchoice>
        <shortcut>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>D</keycap>
          </keycombo>
        </shortcut>

        <guimenu>Project</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Create Translated Documents</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>. Files within the <filename>source</filename> folder,
    whether translated or not, are then generated here, with the same
    hierarchy as present in the source subfolder. The contents of the target
    subfolder will reflect the current state of the translation, as present in
    the project translation memory, saved in the current <emphasis
    role="bold">/omegat/project_save.tmx</emphasis>. Untranslated segments
    will hereby remain in the source language.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>tm</title>

    <para>The /tm/ folder can contain any number of ancillary translation
    memories - i.e. tmx files. Such files can be created in any of the three
    varieties indicated above. Note that other CAT tools can export (and
    import as well) tmx files, usually in all three forms. The best thing of
    course is to use OmegaT-specific TMX files (see above), so that the
    in-line formatting within the segment is retained.</para>

    <para>The contents of translation memories in the tm subfolder serve to
    generate suggestions for the text(s) to be translated. Any text, already
    translated and stored in those files, will appear among the fuzzy matches,
    if it is sufficiently similar to the text currently being
    translated.</para>

    <para>If the source segment in one of the ancillary TMs is identical to
    the text being translated, OmegaT acts as defined in the <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Options</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Editing Behavior...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> dialog window. For instance (if the default is accepted),
    the translation from the ancillary TM is accepted and prefixed
    with<emphasis> [fuzzy]</emphasis>, so that the translator can review the
    translations at a later stage and check whether the segments tagged this
    way, have been translated correctly<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>.</guimenu>
      </menuchoice></para>

    <para>It may happen, that translation memories, available in the
    <filename>tm</filename> subfolder, contain segments with identical source
    text, but differing targets. TMX files are read sorted by their names and
    segments within a given TMX file line by line. The last segment with the
    identical source text will thus prevail (Note: of course it makes more
    sense to avoid this to happen in the first place).</para>

    <para>Note that the TMX files in the tm folder can be compressed with
    gzip.</para>

    <section>
      <title>tm/auto</title>

      <para>If it is clear from the very start, that translations in a given
      TM (or TMs) are all correct, one can put them into the<emphasis
      role="bold"> tm/auto</emphasis> folder and avoid confirming a lot
      of<emphasis> [fuzzy]</emphasis> cases.</para>

      <para><orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Put the TMX in /tm/auto.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Open the project. The changes are displayed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Make a slight change anywhere in the project. This modifies
            <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> (by adding proper
            Translation Units from "auto" TMX)</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <para>Note: if TMX is removed from /tm/auto before step 3, no extra
      Translation Unit is added.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>tm/enforce</title>

      <para>If you have no doubt that a TMX is more accurate than the
      <filename>project_save.tmx</filename> of OmegaT, put this TMX in
      /tm/enforce to overwrite existing default translations
      unconditionally.</para>

      <para><orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Put the TMX in /tm/enforce.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Open the project. The changes are displayed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Make a slight change anywhere in the project. This modifies
            <filename>project_save.tmx</filename>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Make decision about immunity of the enforced
            segments:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>If they <emphasis>don't need</emphasis> to stay immune
                  from further changes, then remove the TMX from
                  /tm/enforce.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>If they <emphasis>need</emphasis> to stay immune from
                  further changes, then keep the TMX in /tm/enforce.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <para>Note: if TMX is removed from /tm/enforce before step 3,
      enforcements aren't kept at all.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>tm/mt</title>

      <para>In the editor pane, when a match is inserted from a TMX contained
      in a folder named <filename>mt</filename>, the background of the active
      segment is changed to red. The background is restored to normal when the
      segment is left.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>tm/penalty-xxx</title>

      <para>Sometimes, it is useful to distinguish between high-quality
      translation memories and those that are, because of the subject matter,
      client, revision status, etc., less reliable. For translation memories
      in folders with a name <filename>penalty-xxx</filename> (with xxx
      between 0 and 100), matches will be degraded according to the name of
      the folder: a 100% match in any of TMs, residing in a folder called
      <filename>penalty-30</filename> for instance, will be lowered to a 70%
      match. The penalty applies to all three match percentages: matches 75,
      80, 90 will in this case be lowered to 45, 50, 60.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>dictionnary</title>

    <para>Initially empty, this folder will contain dictionaries you have
    added to the project. See <link
    linkend="appendix.dictionaries">Dictionaries</link> for more on this
    subject.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>glossary</title>

    <para>This folder is initially empty. It will contain glossaries you will
    be using in the project. See <link
    linkend="appendix.glossaries">Glossaries</link> for more on this
    subject.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="folder.omegat">
    <title>omegat</title>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">omegat</emphasis> subfolder contains at
    least one and possibly several other files. The most important file here
    is the <filename>project_save.tmx, </filename>that is the working
    translation memory for the project. Backups of this file (with extension
    bak) are added progressively to this subfolder, first at the beginning of
    the translation session, at its end, and while the translation
    progresses.</para>

    <para>During translation additional files may get created in this
    subfolder as follows</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>stats.txt</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>contains the current statistics of the current project. You
          can view it by selecting <guimenuitem>Tools &gt;
          Statistics</guimenuitem></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>ignored_words.txt.</term>

        <term>learned_words.txt</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>are created and used by the spell checker. If you already have
          collected words you wish the spell checker to ignore / accept, you
          just need to copy the corresponding two files into the
          <filename>omegat</filename>subfolder of your current project.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>project_stats_match.txt</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>contains the latest project match statistics, generated by
          <guimenuitem>Tools &gt; Match Statistics</guimenuitem></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>segmentation.conf</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>if existing, it contains project-specific segmentation
          rules.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>filters.xml</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>if existing, it contains project-specific file filters.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>uiLayout.xml</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>if existing, it contains project-specific GUI settings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>omegat.project (file)</title>

    <para>Contains project parameters as defined in the <link
    linkend="dialogs.projectproperties">Project properties</link>
    dialog.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>.repositories</title>

    <para>In a team project, this folder contains a versioned copy of the
    project tree structure linked directly to the remote server.</para>

    <para>You can make changes to remote files (e.g. deleting a file) using
    this folder and a Git or SVN client.</para>

    <para>In some operating systems, this folder is not displayed by default.
    Activate the "Show hidden files" option to make it visible.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
