<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.project.properties">
  <title>Project properties<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Project</primary>

      <secondary>Properties</secondary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para/>

  <section id="properties.dialog">
    <title>Properties dialog</title>

    <para>The <menuchoice>
        <shortcut>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>E</keycap>
          </keycombo>
        </shortcut>

        <guimenu>Project</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Properties...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> dialog is used to define and modify the project folders
    and languages.</para>

    <para>It is possible to modify the project properties during a translation
    session. Note that changes to the project setup may have some
    consequences, especially, when the project has already been started. Until
    you have some experience with OmegaT, it is safest to consider all
    settings final once the translation has started – unless of course you
    realize a major mistake has been made. See the section Preventing data
    loss for ways and means of protecting your work.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Project properties window</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/NewProject_25.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/NewProject_25.png" width="80%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>It contains:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An area for setting project source and target languages with
        drop-down menus</para>

        <para>You can either enter the source and target languages by hand or
        use the drop down menu. Bear in mind that changing the languages may
        render the currently used translation memories useless since their
        language pair may not longer match the new languages.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Enable Sentence-level segmentation</guilabel> check
        box</para>

        <indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project</primary>

          <secondary>Enable Sentence-level segmentation</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>The segmentation settings only address the way the source files
        are handled by <application>OmegaT</application>. The predominant way
        of segmenting the sources is the sentence-level segmenting, so this
        check box should in a normal case be left checked.</para>

        <para>In some seldom cases the alternative, i.e. segmenting by
        paragraphs, may be preferred. Changing this flag does not modify the
        segmentation of already existing translation memories. If you decide
        mid-translation to switch from sentence to paragraph translation, the
        internal translation memory of the project will not be changed (OmegaT
        may upgrade old translation memories that did not use sentence
        segmentation, but not vice versa).</para>

        <para>Changing segmentation settings may cause some already translated
        segments to be split or merged. This will effectively return them to
        the "untranslated" status, as they will no longer match segments
        recorded in the project memory, even though their original translation
        is still there.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><guibutton>Segmentation...</guibutton> button<indexterm
            class="singular">
            <primary>Segmentation</primary>

            <secondary>global vs project rules</secondary>
          </indexterm></para>

        <para>The segmentation rules are generally valid across all the
        projects. The user, however, may need to generate a set of rules,
        specific to the project in question. Use this button to open a
        dialog,activate the check box <guimenuitem>Project specific
        segmentation rules</guimenuitem>, then proceed to adjust the
        segmentation rules as desired . The new set of rules will be stored
        together with the project and will not interfere with the general set
        of segmentation rules. To delete project specific Segmentation rules,
        uncheck the check box. See chapter <link
        linkend="chapter.segmentation">Source Segmentation</link> for more
        information on segmentation rules. <emphasis/></para>

        <para><emphasis>Hint:</emphasis> the set of segmentation rules for a
        given project is stored as
        <filename>project/omegat/segmentation.conf.</filename></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guibutton>File Filters...</guibutton> button<indexterm
            class="singular">
            <primary>File Filters</primary>

            <secondary>global vs project file filters</secondary>
          </indexterm></para>

        <para>In a similar fashion as above the user can create
        project-specific File filters, which will be stored together with the
        project and will be valid for the current project only. To create a
        project-specific set of file filters, click on the <guibutton>File
        filter ... </guibutton>button, then activate <guimenuitem>Enable
        project specific filters</guimenuitem> check box in the window, that
        opens. A copy of the changed filters configuration will be stored with
        the project. To delete project specific file filters, uncheck the
        check box. Note that in the menu <guimenuitem>Options-&gt;File
        Filters</guimenuitem>, the global user filters are changed, not the
        project filters. See chapter<link linkend="chapter.file.filters"> File
        filters </link>for more on the subject. <emphasis/></para>

        <para><emphasis>Hint:</emphasis> the set of file filters for a given
        project is stored as
        <filename>project/omegat/filters.xml.</filename></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Autopropagation </emphasis>check
        box<emphasis role="bold"><indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Project</primary>

            <secondary>Autopropagation option</secondary>
          </indexterm></emphasis></para>

        <para>In case multiple translations are available in these translation
        memories for any given source segment, the Autopropagation checkbox
        offers the user the following two possibilities as regards automatic
        translation : if checked, the first translated segment will be assumed
        as the valid translation and its target text will be automatically
        used for later hits during the translation process. Mistranslated
        segments can of course be corrected later manually. If the
        Autopropagation checkbox is not checked, the segments with alternative
        translations are left untranslated until the user has decided
        which of the alternatives is to be used.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An area for setting project folders<indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Glossary</primary>

            <secondary>Location of the writable glossary file</secondary>
          </indexterm></para>

        <indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Project</primary>

          <secondary>Changing the folder structure</secondary>
        </indexterm>

        <para>if you enter names of folders that do not exist yet,
        <application>OmegaT</application> creates them for you. In case you
        decide to modify project folders, keep in mind that this will not move
        the contained files from old folders to the new location.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
