<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.searches">
  <title>Searches<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Searches</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section id="search.window">
    <title>Search window</title>

    <figure id="text.search.window">
      <title>Text search Window<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Search window</primary>

          <secondary>Example</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/TextSearch25.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/TextSearch25.png" width="90%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <note>
      <para>The above search finds all target segments that contain
      characters, rather improbable in the target - i.e. Slovenian -
      language.</para>
    </note>

    <section>
      <title>Searching<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Shortcuts</primary>

          <secondary>Search - Ctrl+F</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para><application>OmegaT</application> provides a powerful range of
      search functions. Open the Search window with <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo> and enter the word or phrase you wish to search for in the
      Search for box. Alternatively, in the Editor window, select a word or
      phrase in the editing field (target text of the current segment) and hit
      <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap>F</keycap>
        </keycombo>. The word or phrase is entered in the Search for box
      automatically. You can have several Search windows open at the same
      time, but close them when they are no longer needed so that they do not
      clutter your desktop.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Search location</title>

      <para>Searches are performed by default in both the source and target
      sections of the project, but you can limit your search to just the
      source or the target text. You may search in</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the project only (default setting)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>both the project and the reference translation memories in
          /tm/ (check <emphasis>Search TMs)</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>a single file or a folder containing a set of files (check
          <emphasis>Search files)</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>When searching through files (as opposed to translation memories),
      <application>OmegaT</application> restricts the search to files in
      source file formats. Consequently, although OmegaT is quite able to
      handle<filename> tmx</filename> files, it does not include them in the
      Search files search. If you turn on <emphasis role="bold"><indexterm
          class="singular">
          <primary>Searches</primary>

          <secondary>Advanced Options</secondary>
        </indexterm>Advanced Options</emphasis>, you can combine the search
      with the name of the author of the translation and time of the last
      change made.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="using.wild.cards">
    <title>Using wild cards<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Searches</primary>

        <secondary>Using wild cards</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>In both exact and keyword searches, the wild card search characters
    '*' and '?' can be used. They have the meaning, familiar to Word
    users:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'*' matches zero or more characters, from the current position
        in a given word to its end. The search term <literal>'run*'</literal>
        for example would match words <literal>'run'</literal>,
        <literal>'runs'</literal> and <literal>'running'</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'?' matches any single character. For instance, <literal>'run?'</literal> 
        would match the word <literal>'runs'</literal> and
        <literal>'runn'</literal> in the word
        <literal>'running'</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The matches will be displayed in bold blue. Note that '*' and '?'
    have special meaning in regular expressions, so wild card search, as
    described here, applies to exact and keyword search only (see
    below).</para>
  </section>

  <section id="search.methoids">
    <title>Search methods and options<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Searches</primary>

        <secondary>Methods and options</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Select the method using the radio buttons. The following search
    methods are available:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>exact search</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for segments containing the exact string you specified.
          An exact search looks for a phrase, i.e. if several words are
          entered, they are found only if they occur in exactly that sequence.
          Searching for <literal>open file</literal> will thus find all
          occurrences of the string <emphasis><literal>open
          file</literal></emphasis>, but not <emphasis><literal>file
          opened</literal></emphasis> or <emphasis><literal>open input
          file</literal></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>keyword search</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for segments containing all keywords you specified, in
          any order. Select keyword search to search for any number of
          individual full words, in any order. OmegaT displays a list of all
          segments containing all of the words specified. Keyword searches are
          similar to a search "with all of the words" in an Internet search
          engine such as Google (AND logic). Using keyword search with
          <emphasis><literal>open file</literal></emphasis> will thus find all
          occurrences of the string <emphasis><literal>open
          file</literal>,</emphasis> as well as <emphasis><literal>file
          opened</literal>, <literal>open input file</literal>, <literal>file
          may not be safe to open</literal></emphasis>, etc.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">regular expressions</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The search string will be treated as a regular expression. The
          search string - [a-zA-Z]+[öäüqwß] - in the example above for
          instance looks for words in the target segment, containing
          questionable characters from German keyboard. Regular expressions
          are a powerful way to look for instances of a string. See more in
          the chapter<link linkend="chapter.regexp"> Regular
          Expressions.</link></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Additionally to one of the methods above you can select the
    following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">case sensitive</emphasis>: the search will
        be performed for the exact string specified; i.e. capitalization is
        observed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">in source: </emphasis>search in the source
        segments</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">in translations: </emphasis>search in the
        target segments</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">in notes: </emphasis>search in notes to
        segments</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">search TMs</emphasis>: translation
        memories in the <filename>tm</filename> folder are included in the
        search.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">display all results: </emphasis>clearing
        this check box will case OmegaT show just the first occurrence of a
        hit, if several hits exist</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If you click on the button <guibutton>Advanced options</guibutton>
    additional criteria (author of the translation, date translated etc) as
    shown in the above image can be selected.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="search.result.display">
    <title>Search results display</title>

    <para>Pressing the search button after entering a string in the search
    field displays all the segments in the project that include the entered
    string. As <application>OmegaT</application> handles identical segments as
    one single entity, only the first unique segment is shown. The segments
    are displayed in order of appearance in the project. Translated segments
    are displayed with the original text at the top and the translated text at
    the bottom, untranslated segments are displayed as the source only.</para>

    <para>Clicking on a segment opens it in the Editor for modifications. You
    can then switch back to the Search window for the next segment found, for
    instance to check and, if necessary, correct the terminology.</para>

    <para>You may have several Search windows open at the same time. You can
    quickly see their contents by looking at their title: it will contain the
    search term used.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
