<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.spellchecker">
  <title>Spell checker<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Spell checker</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>OmegaT has a built-in spell checker based on the spelling checker used
  in OpenOffice.org, Firefox and Thunderbird. It is consequently able to use
  the huge range of free spelling dictionaries available for these
  applications.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Installing spelling dictionaries</title>

    <para>Before the spell check function can be used, a suitable dictionary
    or dictionaries (i.e. for your target language) must be installed. To
    install spelling dictionaries, follow this procedure:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In your file manager, create a new folder in a suitable location
        in which to store spelling dictionaries (D:\Translations\spellcheckers
        in the example below).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In OmegaT, select <guisubmenu><indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>Menu Options</primary>

            <secondary>Spell checking</secondary>
          </indexterm></guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Options &gt; Spell
        Checking</guimenuitem>, then click <guibutton>Choose
        </guibutton>beside the Dictionary file folder field. Navigate to and
        select the folder you created for dictionaries.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Place the dictionary files you wish to use in this folder. There
        are essentially two ways in which you can do this. You can either copy
        files manually, i.e. from elsewhere on your system, using your file
        manager; or you can use OmegaT's <emphasis role="bold">"Install new
        dictionary"</emphasis> function to provide a list of available
        dictionaries to select from. Note that the "Install" function requires
        an Internet connection. The selected languages will then be installed
        and will eventually appear in your spell checker setup window (this
        may take a while).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Copying the files manually makes sense if you already have suitable
    dictionary files on your system, for instance as part of your
    OpenOffice.org or Thunderbird installation. It is simpler, however, to
    look for dictionaries online, using the <emphasis role="bold">URL of
    online dictionaries</emphasis> field:</para>

    <figure id="spellchecker.setup">
      <title><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Spell checker</primary>

          <secondary>Spell checker setup</secondary>
        </indexterm>Spellchecker setup</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/SpellcheckerSetup_25.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/SpellcheckerSetup_25.png" width="80%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Clicking on <guibutton>Install new dictionary</guibutton> button
    will open the Dictionary installer window, where you can select the
    dictionaries you want to install. Make sure the language code of your
    target files corresponds to the dictionary's language code: an FR-FR
    dictionary will not work with an FR target setting. You need to change the
    setting to FR-FR to have the spell checker recognize the correct
    dictionary for your target. Look for files with the name, indicating the
    language used and having extensions <emphasis>aff</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>dic.</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using spelling dictionaries</title>

    <para>There is no need to instruct OmegaT to use a particular spelling
    dictionary; OmegaT will use the correct language dictionary based upon the
    language codes of your project. Check however that the language codes are
    exactly the same: an FR-FR dictionary will not work with an FR target
    setting, for example. If necessary, edit the file names of the dictionary
    or change your project's language settings.</para>

    <para>To enable the spell checker, select <guimenuitem>Options &gt; Spell
    Checking</guimenuitem> and tick the <guilabel>Automatically check the
    spelling of text</guilabel> check box (see above).</para>

    <figure id="spellchecker.in.action">
      <title><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Spell checker</primary>

          <secondary>Spell checker in action</secondary>
        </indexterm>Spellchecker in action</title>

        <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/SpellcheckingText.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/SpellcheckingText.png" width="80%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Right-clicking on an underlined word (Artund in the figure above)
    opens a drop-down menu listing suggestions for the correction (Art und).
    You can also instruct the spell checker to ignore all the occurrences of
    the mis-spelled word, or add it to the dictionary.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="hints">
    <title>Hints<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Spell checker</primary>

        <secondary>Hints</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>If the spell checker is not working, then make sure first that the
    check box <guilabel>"Automatically check the spelling of text"</guilabel>
    in the spell checker dialog (<guisubmenu>Options &gt; Spell
    checking...)</guisubmenu> is checked.</para>

    <para>Also check that the target language code of your project against the
    available vocabularies in the setup window. The spell checker uses the
    target language code to determine the language to be used : if the target
    language is Brazilian Portuguese (PT_BR), the subfolder with vocabularies
    must contain the two vocabulary files, called
    <emphasis>pt_br.aff</emphasis> and <emphasis>pt_br.dic</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>If you have already translated a large body of text, and then
    realize the target language code of the project does not match the spell
    checker's language code (you specified pt_BR as the language, but there
    are no pt_BR vocabularies, for instance) you can simply copy the two
    corresponding files and rename them (e.g. from
    <emphasis>pt_PT.arr</emphasis> and <emphasis>pt_PT.dic</emphasis> to
    <emphasis>pt._BR.arr</emphasis> and <emphasis>pt_BR.dic</emphasis>). Of
    course it is much wiser, to take a short break and download the correct
    versions of the spell checker.</para>

    <para>Note that <filename>Remove</filename> physically removes the
    selected vocabularies. If they are used by some other application on your
    system, they will disappear from that application, too. If, for whatever
    reason, you need to do this from time to time, it may make sense to copy
    the files involved to a different folder, reserved just for use by
    OmegaT.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
