<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.TaaS">
  <title>Using TaaS in OmegaT<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Search</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section id="TaaS.options">
    <title>Generalities</title>

    <para>The TaaS service at https://demo.taas-project.eu/info provides
    terminology services in European languages. It allows accessing both
    public and private data, where private glossaries (called "collections")
    can be extracted from existing documents, and the target terms partly
    populated automatically from various sources.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="TaaS.options">
    <title>Public and private collections</title>

    <para>OmegaT allows accessing the public part of TaaS without any
    registration.</para>

    <para>To access the private part, a user must create a key using
    https://demo.taas-project.eu/account/keys/create?system=omegaT.</para>

    <para>The key must then be given to OmegaT using -Dtaas.user.key=xxxxx.
    OmegaT configuration launchers (OmegaT.l4J.ini, omegat.kaptn and
    OmegaT.sh) contain a template entry.</para>

    <para>When accessing the service without a private key, the following
    message will be put in the log: TaaS API key not found. Go to
    https://demo.taas-project.eu/account/keys/create?system=omegaT to create
    your own key then give it to OmegaT with -Dtaas.user.key=xxxxx
    (TAAS_API_KEY_NOT_FOUND)</para>
  </section>

  <section id="TaaS.options">
    <title>Accessing the TaaS service</title>

    <para>Click on <emphasis role="bold">Options, Glossary</emphasis> to
    display the following options:</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Browse TaaS Collections</emphasis> will allow
    browsing existing collections for the source and target languages of the
    project, and downloading them. Private collections are displayed in bold.
    The collections are downloaded as TBX glossaries in the current glossary
    folder.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">TaaS Terminology Lookup</emphasis>: when
    checked, will allow querying TaaS data on a segment by segment basis. All
    collections (public and private) will be queried for the source and target
    language.</para>

    <para>To limit the amount of data, it is possible to select a specific
    domain by selecting <emphasis role="bold">Select TaaS Terminology Lookup
    Domain</emphasis>. In that dialog, it's possible to select All domains or
    a specific one.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
