<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="windows.aligner">
  <title id="windows.aligner.title">Aligner</title>

  <para>Alignment is the process of creating a bilingual translation memory
  from a pair of already translated monolingual documents. Aligning the contents of the files is a two-step process. First, the files are read by the aligner, which attempts to match the segments that correspond to one another in the original and translated texts. Next, the translator reviews the results and makes any necessary manual adjustments.</para>

  <para>The aligner can read all the file formats supported by OmegaT. Select
  <link endterm="menus.tools.align.files.title"
  linkend="menus.tools.align.files"/> in the <link endterm="menus.tools.title"
  linkend="menus.tools"/> menu to access this tool. This brings up the
  <guilabel>Align Files</guilabel> dialog, where you specify the source and
  target languages and select the two files you want to align.</para>

  <note>
    <para>If you have a translation project open, the aligner will
    automatically use the languages from that project, as well the
    project-specific segmentation rules, if any.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Clicking the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button in the<guilabel>Align Files</guilabel> dialog brings up the <guilabel>Align</guilabel> window, which shows the results of the automatic alignment.</para>

  <para>The main part of the window is divided into three columns:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Keep</guilabel>: The segment pairs in rows that have this check box ticked are saved to the translation memory file. Unticked rows are discarded.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Source</guilabel>: The segments from the original
          text.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Target</guilabel>: The segments from the translated
          text.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <section id="windows.aligner.adjust">
    <title id="windows.aligner.adjust.title">Step 1: Adjust alignment
    parameters</title>

    <para>In this step, the bottom part of the window presents various
    parameters and options you can change if the initial alignment looks like
    it could be improved. It also shows an <guilabel>Average score</guilabel> result for the alignement. As a rule of thumb, the lower
    that score, the more accurate the alignment. Changing a parameter immediately recalculates the alignment, allowing you to quickly try different combinations to obtain the best results.</para>
    
    <para>The available parameters and options are:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <para><emphasis>Parameters</emphasis></para>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Comparison mode</guilabel></term>        
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Heapwise</guilabel>: This mode compares the documents globally.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Parsewise</guilabel>: This mode compares the documents segment by segment. It is only shown when it is available for the files being aligned.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>ID</guilabel>: This mode applies to files consisting of <literal>key = value</literal> entries. This works even if the order of the keys differ in each file, and when the files have a different number of entries. It is only shown when both selected files are recognized as key=value files.</para>
              </listitem>            
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Algorithm:</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Viterbi</guilabel>: The default algorithms used to align the documents.</para> 
              </listitem>
              <listitem><para><guilabel>Forward-Backward</guilabel>: An alternative algorithm that can be used to align the documents.</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
              <para>There is no hard and fast rule on which algorithm is better. Try both, and use the one that yields the better results for your files.</para>
          </listitem>        
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Calculator:</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para></para>            
          </listitem>        
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Counter:</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para></para>            
          </listitem>        
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  
  <variablelist>
    <para><emphasis>Options</emphasis></para>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><guilabel>Segment</guilabel></term>
      <listitem>
        <para></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><guilabel>Remove Tags</guilabel></term>
      <listitem>
        <para></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><guilabel>Highlight</guilabel></term>
      <listitem>
        <para></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><guibutton>Rules...</guibutton></term>
      <listitem>
        <para></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><guibutton>Filters...</guibutton></term>
      <listitem>
        <para></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><guibutton>Pattern...</guibutton></term>
      <listitem>
        <para></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
    
    <para>Click <guibutton>Continue</guibutton> to proceed to the next
    step.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="windows.aligner.manual.corrections">
    <title id="windows.aligner.manual.corrections.title">Step 2: Make manual
    corrections</title>

    <para>Manual adjustments are generally required after the initial
    automatic alignment process.</para>

    <para>The manual step window presents the original and translated text in
    the source and target columns, respectively.</para>

    <para>To align a source and target segment found in different rows:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the first segment.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Press the space bar (the shortcut for <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Start Pinpoint Align</guimenuitem></menuchoice>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click on the corresponding segment in the other column.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>After repeating the process a few times, press <keycombo><keycap>C</keycap><keycap>r</keycap></keycombo> (or select <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Realign pending</guimenuitem></menuchoice> )to update the alignment of the remaining segments.</para>

    <para>To move one or more segments individually, select them and press
    <userinput>U</userinput> or <userinput>D</userinput> (or click the
    <guilabel>Move Up</guilabel> or <guilabel>Move Down</guilabel>
    button).</para>

    <para>Only rows with the <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> box ticked in the first
    column are saved to the translation memory.</para>

    <para>After you finish aligning the two columns, click <guibutton>Save
    TMX...</guibutton> to create the translation memory.</para>
  </section>
</section>
