<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="windows.aligner">
  <title id="windows.aligner.title"><guilabel>Align Files</guilabel></title>

  <para>Use <link endterm="menus.tools.title"
  linkend="menus.tools"/><link endterm="menus.tools.align.files.title"
  linkend="menus.tools.align.files"/> to access this tool.</para>

  <para>OmegaT also offers a command line based alignment mode for key-based
  formats. See the <link linkend="launch.with.command.line.mode.console.align"
  endterm="launch.with.command.line.mode.console.align.title"/> option for
  details.</para>

  <warning>
    <para>The aligner does not allow you to save your work partway through an
    alignment. Therefore, it is recommended that you divide the files to align
    into shorter files that you can comfortably align in a single session. Doing
    so has the added benefit of reducing mismatches in the initial automatic
    alignment, making the manual correction step smoother.</para>
  </warning>


  <para>Alignment is the process of creating a bilingual translation memory from
  a pair of already translated monolingual documents. Aligning the contents of
  the files is a four-step process:</para>

  <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Specify the source and target languages and select the two files you
	  want to align.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>The aligner reads the files and attempts to match the
	  segments that correspond to one another in the original and translated
	  texts.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Review the results and makes any necessary manual
	  adjustments.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Save the result to a TMX file.</para>
	</listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>The aligner can read all file formats supported by OmegaT.</para>
  
  <note>
    <para>If you have a translation project open, the aligner will automatically
    use the languages from that project, as well the project-specific
    segmentation rules, if any.</para>
  </note>

  <para>After selecting the language and files, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>
  button to bring up the <guilabel>Align</guilabel> window, which shows the
  results of the automatic alignment.</para>

  <para>The main part of the window is divided into three columns:</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><guilabel>Keep</guilabel>: The segment pairs in rows that have this
      box checked are saved to the translation memory file.  Unchecked rows are
      discarded.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><guilabel>Source</guilabel>: The segments from the original
      text.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><guilabel>Target</guilabel>: The segments from the translated
      text.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section id="windows.aligner.adjust">
    <title id="windows.aligner.adjust.title">Settings</title>

    <para>In this step, the bottom part of the window presents various
    parameters and options you can change if the initial alignment looks like it
    could be improved. It also shows an <guilabel>Average score</guilabel>
    result for the alignment. As a rule of thumb, the lower that score, the more
    accurate the alignment. Changing a parameter immediately recalculates the
    alignment, allowing you to quickly try different combinations to obtain the
    best results.</para>

    <para>The available parameters and options are:</para>

    <variablelist>
	  <title>Parameters</title>
	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Comparison mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Heapwise</guilabel>: This mode compares the
              documents globally.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Parsewise</guilabel>: This mode compares the
              documents segment by segment. It is only shown when it is
              available for the files being aligned.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>ID</guilabel>: This mode applies to files
              consisting of <literal>key = value</literal> entries. This works
              even if the order of the keys differs in each file, and when the
              files have a different number of entries. It is only shown when
              both selected files are recognized as key=value files.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Algorithm:</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Viterbi</guilabel>: The default algorithms used to
              align the documents.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Forward-Backward</guilabel>: An alternative
              algorithm that can be used to align the documents.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>There is no hard-and-fast rule on which algorithm you should
          choose. Try both, and use the one that yields the better result for
          your files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Calculator:</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Normal</guilabel>: The default statistical
              distribution used to align the documents.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Poisson</guilabel>: An alternative statistical
              distribution that can be used to align the documents.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>As with the algorithms, there is no hard-and-fast rule on which
          statistical distribution you should choose. Try both and use the one
          that yields the better result for your files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Counter:</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Character</guilabel>: The basic unit used to
              determine the size of segments in languages that do not use a
              space to delimit words.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Word</guilabel>: The basic unit used to determine
              the size of segments in languages that use a space to delimit
              words.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The aligner automatically selects the counter based on the
          source and target languages of files to align. It defaults to
          <guilabel>Character</guilabel> if at least one of the languages
          involved does not delimit words with spaces, and to
          <guilabel>Word</guilabel> otherwise. If you are working with one of
          each, you can try to switch between the two to see which one yields
          better results.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
	  <title>Options</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Segment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The aligner uses sentence segmentation by default. Uncheck the
          check box to use paragraph segmentation. See the <link
          endterm="dialogs.preferences.segmentation.setup.title"
          linkend="dialogs.preferences.segmentation.setup"/> preferences.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Remove Tags</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The aligner includes tags in the segments by default. Uncheck
          the check box to apply the <link
          endterm="dialogs.project.properties.remove.tags.title"
          linkend="dialogs.project.properties.remove.tags"/> option.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="windows.aligner.adjust.highlight">
        <term id="windows.aligner.adjust.highlight.title">Highlight</term>
        <listitem>
		  <para>Uncheck the check box to turn off highlighting.</para>

          <para>The aligner uses the regular expression <code>\d+</code>
          to highlight all numbers in the source and target segments.</para>
		  <para>You can modify the regular expression to add highlighted
		  parts. See the <link linkend="app.regex" endterm="app.regex.title"/>
		  chapter for details.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Rules...</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Clicking this button lets you edit the segmentation rules that
          apply to this project. See the <link linkend="app.segmentation"
          endterm="app.segmentation.title"/> appendix for details.</para>

          <warning>
            <para>If you modify the segmentation rules, you will be asked if you
            want to save those changes when you exit the aligner. The default
            choice is <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>, which may not be what you want
            if you edited the global OmegaT segmentation rules.</para>
          </warning>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Filters...</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Clicking this button lets you edit the file filters that apply
          to this project. See the <link
          linkend="dialogs.preferences.file.filters"
          endterm="dialogs.preferences.file.filters.title"/> preferences for
          details.</para>

          <warning>
            <para>If you modify the file filters, you will be asked if you want
            to save those changes when you exit the aligner. The default choice
            is <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>, which may not be what you want if you
            edited the global OmegaT file filters.</para>
          </warning>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pattern...</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This option lets you enter a regular expression to define the
          pattern used to highlight text in the source and target
          segments. By default, the aligner uses <literal>\d+</literal> to
          highlight numbers. If your texts contain other elements that would be
          useful to highlight, modify the regular expression to include those
          elements, using the <literal>|</literal> symbol to separate each
          element.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>      
    </variablelist>

    <para>You can also access the <guilabel>Highlight</guilabel> option and the
    dialog to modify the pattern from the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu, and the
    other options from the <guimenu>Options</guimenu> menu.</para>

    <para>In addition, the <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu provides the following
    commands:</para>
	
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><guimenuitem>Save TMX...</guimenuitem>: This item is grayed out
        until the next step is complete.</para>
      </listitem>
	  
      <listitem>
        <para><guimenuitem>Reset</guimenuitem>: This command restores all
        parameters to their default value. It can also be called by clicking the
        <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> at the bottom right of the window or
        pressing
        <keycombo><keycap>C</keycap><keycap>S</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guimenuitem>Reload</guimenuitem>: This command reloads the file
        from the disk. You can use this command to parse and align the files
        again if you had to modify their contents.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem>: This closes the
        <guilabel>Align</guilabel> dialog. Doing so in this step cancels the
        alignment without saving any data to a translation memory file. You can
        also call this command by pressing
        <keycombo><keycap>C</keycap><keycap>W</keycap></keycombo>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu is grayed out in this step.</para>

    <para>Once you are satisfied with the results of this step, click the
    <guibutton>Continue</guibutton> button to proceed to the next one.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="windows.aligner.manual.corrections">
    <title id="windows.aligner.manual.corrections.title">Corrections</title>

    <para>Manual adjustments are generally required after the initial automatic
    alignment process. This generally involves moving segments up or down to
    align them with the correct segments in the other language, as well as
    splitting or merging segments. The aligner also allows you to edit the
    contents of a segment, which can be useful if you notice errors such as a
    spelling mistake in a segment.</para>

    <para>All available actions can be accessed from the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
    menu or by pressing the corresponding shortcut key. The most common actions
    are also accessible from the buttons at the right of the main pane.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The shortcut keys are well worth remembering if you use the aligner
      often or work on large documents, as they allow you to carry out actions
      very quickly.</para>
    </note>

    <para>To perform an action, select the applicable segment or block of
    consecutive segments. Individual segments can be selected with the mouse or
    the arrow keys. Segment blocks can be selected with the mouse by clicking
    the first segment, and holding the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key while clicking
    the last segment.</para>

	<para>Alternatively, you can press the arrow keys while holding
	<keycap>Shift</keycap> to select consecutive segments. The available actions
	are presented below.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Move Up (<keycap>U</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Moves the selected segment, or block of consecutive segments, up
          one row.</para>
          <para>This command is also available from the button at the right of
          the main window pane.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Move Down (<keycap>D</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Moves the selected segment, or block of consecutive segments,
          down one row.</para>

          <para>This command is also available from the button at the right of
          the main window pane.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Split (<keycap>S</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If a single segment is selected, this command opens the
          <guilabel>Split Text</guilabel> dialog. Use the mouse or arrow keys to
          place the cursor at the location where you want to split the text, and
          click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button or press
          <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>

          <para>If two or more segments occupying separate cells in the same row
          (multi-cell segments containing lines without a <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> check box) are selected, this command will 
          split the selected cells back into separate rows (with a
          <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> check box).</para>

		  <para>This command is also available from the button at the right of
          the main window pane.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Merge (<keycap>M</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If only one segment is selected, the aligner will merge it with
          the following segment. If two or more segments are selected, they will
          all be merged, but remain in separate cells. Calling the command on
          the same selection one more time merges the contents of all selected
          cells into a single cell.</para>

		  <para>This command is also available from the button at the right of
          the main window pane.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Edit (<keycap>E</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This command can only be performed on a single segment. Calling
          this command opens the <guilabel>Edit Text</guilabel> dialog, which
          allows you to make changes to the text of the segment. Use the
          <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button to close the dialog when
          finished. In this dialog, the <keycap>Enter</keycap> enters a line
          break in the text.</para>

		  <para>Use
		  <keycombo><keycap>C</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo> to close
		  it without using the mouse.</para>

		  <para>This command is also available from the button at the right of
          the main window pane.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Mark Accepted (<keycap>A</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this command to confirm that the alignment of the segments
          in the selected row or block of rows is correct. This highlights the
          corresponding <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> column in green.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Mark Needs Review (<keycap>R</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this command to identify a row or block of rows for which
          the alignment of the segments is in doubt. This highlights the
          corresponding <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> column in red.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Clear Mark (<keycap>C</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this command to remove one or more marks set by the
          <guilabel>Mark Accepted</guilabel> or <guilabel>Mark Needs
          Review</guilabel> commands.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Realign Pending
        (<keycombo><keycap>C</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If any rows have been marked as accepted, use this command to
          update the alignment for the remaining rows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Keep All</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this command to check the <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> box for
          all rows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Keep None</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this command to uncheck the <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> check
          box for all rows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term>Toggle Selected (<keycap>K</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this command to switch the <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> check
          box of the selected row or block of rows from checked to unchecked, or
          vice versa.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Start Pinpoint Align (<keycap>Space</keycap>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the corresponding segments are several rows apart and you
          want to quickly align them, use this command to select the first 
          segment and then click on the corresponding segment in the other
          column.</para>
		  
		  <para>You can also use the arrow keys and press <keycap>Space</keycap>
		  in the corresponding segment.</para>
		  
          <para>Segments aligned using this method are automatically marked as
          accepted.</para>

		  <para>It can be helpful to run the <guimenuitem>Realign
          Pending</guimenuitem> command after using the pinpoint align command 
          a few times.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>After you finish aligning the two columns, click the <guibutton>Save
    TMX...</guibutton> button to create the translation memory.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Only rows with a checked <guilabel>Keep</guilabel> box in the first
      column are saved to the translation memory.</para>
    </note>


    <para>In addition to the <guibutton>Save TMX...</guibutton> button, the
    bottom part of the <guilabel>Align</guilabel> window in the manual
    correction step features the same <guilabel>Highlight</guilabel> check box
    and <guibutton>Pattern...</guibutton> button as in the first step. This
    option is also accessible from the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>There is also a <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> button at the bottom of
      the window. <emphasis role="bold">Use it with caution!</emphasis> Clicking
      this button will discard all your changes and bring you back to the first
      step.</para>
    </warning>    
    
  </section>
</section>
