<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="windows.project.files">
  <title id="windows.project.files.title">Project Files</title>

  <para>This window is displayed automatically when OmegaT loads a project. It
  can also be called at any time by selecting <link
  linkend="menus.project.project.files"
  endterm="menus.project.project.files.title"/> in the <link
  linkend="menus.project" endterm="menus.project.title"/> menu.</para>

  <para>The window displays the following information:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The total number of translatable files in the project, which are the
      files in the <link linkend="project.folder.source"
      endterm="project.folder.source.title"/> folder in a format recognized by
      OmegaT. This number is displayed in parentheses in the window
      title.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The list of all translatable files in the project.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
      <para>The file list entries include the name, filter type, encoding and
      number of segments of the file</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The total number of segments, the number of unique segments in the
      entire project, and the number of unique segments already translated are
      shown at the bottom of the file list.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
	  
  <para>You can:
  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>click on any file to open it for translation in the <link
	  linkend="panes.editor" endterm="panes.editor.title"/>,</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
      <para>select a file using the <keycap>Up</keycap> and
      <keycap>Down</keycap> keys,</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>type a string to filter the list on files with that string in their
	  name,</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
      <para>sort the files by clicking on any of the column headers,</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>select one or more files in the list and, use one of the
	  <guibutton>Move...</guibutton> buttons on reorder the selected file or
	  files,</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
      <para><keycap>right-click</keycap> on a filename to open a context menu
      from which you can open the source file and (if it exists) the target
      file, or</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem><para>use
	<keycombo><keycap>C</keycap><keycap>Right-click</keycap></keycombo> to open
	their location.</para>
	</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>The number of <emphasis role="bold">unique</emphasis> segments is
  calculated by taking all segments and subtracting all duplicate
  segments.</para>

  <warning><para>Modifying the segmentation rules will modify the number of
  segments and unique segments.</para></warning>

  <para>The difference between the &quot;Number of segments&quot; and
  &quot;Number of unique segments&quot; gives an approximate idea of the number
  of repetitions in the text. The <link linkend="project.folder.project.stats"
  endterm="project.folder.project.stats.title"/> file located in the <link
  linkend="project.folder.omegat.folder"
  endterm="project.folder.omegat.folder.title"/> folder of your project contains
  more detailed segment information, broken down by source file.</para>

  <para>The <guilabel>Copy Files To Source Folder</guilabel> and the
  <guilabel>Download MediaWiki Page</guilabel> buttons perform the same function
  as the equivalent item in the <link linkend="menus.project"
  endterm="menus.project.title"/> menu.</para>

    <note><para>It is possible to stop the window from displaying automatically
    by setting the <code>project_files_show_on_load</code> option to
    <code>false</code> in <link
    linkend="configuration.folder.default.contents.omegat.prefs"
    endterm="configuration.folder.default.contents.omegat.prefs.title"/>.</para></note>

</section>
