<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="windows.project.files">
  <title id="windows.project.files.title">Project Files</title>

  <para>This window is displayed automatically when OmegaT loads a project,
  and at any time by using <link linkend="menus.project.project.files" endterm="menus.project.project.files.title"/>.</para>

  <note><para>It is possible to inhibit the window displaying
  at opening, by setting <emphasis>project_files_show_on_load</emphasis> to
  <emphasis>false</emphasis> in the <link linkend="configuration.folder.default.contents.omegat.prefs" endterm="configuration.folder.default.contents.omegat.prefs.title"/> configuration file. See <link linkend="configuration.folder" endterm="configuration.folder.title"/> for detail.</para></note>

  <para>The window displays the following information:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>the total number of translatable files in the project. These are the
      files present in the <link linkend="project.folder.source"
      endterm="project.folder.source.title"/> folder in a format that OmegaT is
      able to recognize. This number is displayed in brackets, next to the
      window name.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>the list of all translatable files in the project. Clicking on any
      file will open it for translation.</para>

      <para>Typing any text will open a <guilabel>Filter</guilabel> field at the
      bottom of the window where parts of filenames can be entered. You can use
      arrows to select a file, and open it for translation by pressing
      <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>

      <note><para>Filenames (in first column) can be sorted alphabetically by
      clicking in the header. It also possible to change the position of a
      filename, by clicking on it and pressing the <guibutton>Move ...</guibutton>
      buttons on the right.</para></note>

      <para>Right-clicking on a filename opens a popup that allows to open the
      source file and (if it exists) the target file.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>File entries include their names, file filter types, their
      encoding and the number of segments each file contains</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The total number of segments, the number of unique segments in the
      whole project, and the number of unique segments already translated are
      shown at the bottom</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The set of <emphasis role="bold">Unique</emphasis> segments is computed
  by taking all the segments and removing all duplicate segments (the definition
  of “unique” is case-sensitive: &quot;Run&quot; and &quot;run&quot; are treated
  as being different).</para>

  <para>The difference between &quot;Number of segments&quot; and &quot;Number
  of unique segments&quot; provides an approximate idea of the number of
  repetitions in the text. The <link linkend="menus.tools.statistics"
  endterm="menus.tools.statistics.title"/> item in the <link linkend="menus.tools"
  endterm="menus.tools.title"/> menu will give you more information.</para>

  <para>Modifying the segmentation rules may have the effect of modifying the
  number of segments/unique segments. This, however, should generally be avoided
  once you have started translating the project. See <link
  linkend="appendix.segmentation" endterm="appendix.segmentation.title"/> for
  details.</para>

  <para>The buttons at the bottom can be used to add files to your project:
  <variablelist>
	<varlistentry id="windows.project.files.copy.files"><term
	id="windows.project.files.copy.files.title">Copy Files to Source
	Folder...</term>
	<listitem><para>Copies the selected files to the <link
  linkend="project.folder.source.title" endterm="project.folder.source.title"/>
  folder and reloads the project to take the new files into account.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry id="windows.project.files.download.page"><term
	id="windows.project.files.download.page.title">Download Mediawiki
	Page...</term>
	<listitem><para>Asks for the page URL and downloads it into the <link
  linkend="project.folder.source.title" endterm="project.folder.source.title"/> folder.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </para>
</section>
