<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="appendix.legal.notices">
  <title><indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Advertentias legal</primary>
    </indexterm>Advertentias legal</title>

  <section id="legal.notices.for.documentation">
    <title>For the documentation<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Legal notices</primary>

        <secondary>For the documentation</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright</emphasis></para>

    <para>The documentation distributed with <application>OmegaT</application>
    includes the User Manual and the readme.txt document. The
    documentation is Copyright ©2013 Vito Smolej. The author of the Chapter
    <emphasis>Learn to use OmegaT in 5 minutes!</emphasis> is Samuel Murray,
    Copyright ©2005-2012.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Distribution and
    modifications</emphasis></para>

    <para>The documentation is a free document; you can redistribute it and/or
    modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
    by the Free Software Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or (if
    you prefer) any later version.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Warranty</emphasis></para>

    <para>The documentation is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for more detail.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="legal.ntices.for.application">
    <title>For the application<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Legal notices</primary>

        <secondary>For the application</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"><application>OmegaT</application>
    </emphasis> is Copyright © 2000-2013 Keith Godfrey, Zoltan Bartko, Volker Berlin, Didier Briel,
    Kim Bruning, Alex Buloichik, Thomas Cordonnier, Sandra Jean Chua, 
    Martin Fleurke, Wildrich Fourie, Phillip Hall, Jean-Christophe Helary, Thomas Huriaux, 
    Hans-Peter Jacobs, Kyle Katarn, Ibai Lakunza Velasco, Guido Leenders, Aaron Madlon-Kay, 
    Fabián Mandelbaum, John Moran, Maxym Mykhalchuk, Arno Peters, 
    Henry Pijffers, Briac Pilpré, Tiago Saboga, Andrzej Sawuła, 
    Benjamin Siband, Yu Tang, Rashid Umarov, Antonio Vilei, Martin Wunderlich and Michael Zakharov.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Distribution and
    modifications</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">OmegaT
    </emphasis> is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
    Software Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or (if you prefer)
    any later version.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Warranty</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"> <application>OmegaT</application>
    </emphasis>is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
    ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
    more detail.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>