<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="appendix.legal.notices">
  <title><indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>法律声明</primary>
    </indexterm>法律声明</title>

  <section id="legal.notices.for.documentation">
    <title>对于文档<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>法律声明</primary> <secondary>对于文档</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">版权</emphasis></para>

    <para>The documentation distributed with <application>OmegaT</application>
    includes the User Manual and the readme.txt document. The
    documentation is Copyright ©2013 Vito Smolej, ©2014-2016 Vincent Bidaux. The author of the Chapter
    <emphasis>Learn to use OmegaT in 5 minutes!</emphasis> is Samuel Murray,
    Copyright ©2005-2012.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">发布和修改</emphasis></para>

    <para>本文档是自由文档，在遵守自由软件基金会（FSF）发布的的 GNU 通用公共许可证的版本3或者更高版本的前提下，您可以对它进行修改或者重新发布。</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">保证</emphasis></para>

    <para>The documentation is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General
    Public License for more details.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="legal.ntices.for.application">
    <title>对于应用程序<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>法律声明</primary> <secondary>对于应用程序</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">版权</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"><application>OmegaT</application> </emphasis> 版权所有 © 2000-2016 Keith Godfrey, Lev Abashkin, Zoltan Bartko, Volker Berlin, Didier Briel, Kim Bruning, Alex Buloichik, Thomas Cordonnier, Sandra Jean Chua, Enrique Estévez Fernández, Martin Fleurke, Wildrich Fourie, Tony Graham, Phillip Hall, Jean-Christophe Helary, Chihiro Hio, Thomas Huriaux, Hans-Peter Jacobs, Kyle Katarn, Piotr Kulik, Ibai Lakunza Velasco, Guido Leenders, Aaron Madlon-Kay, Fabián Mandelbaum, Manfred Martin, Adiel Mittmann, Hiroshi Miura, John Moran, Maxym Mykhalchuk, Arno Peters, Henry Pijffers, Briac Pilpré, Tiago Saboga, Andrzej Sawuła, Benjamin Siband, Yu Tang, Rashid Umarov, Antonio Vilei, Ilia Vinogradov, Martin Wunderlich and Michael Zakharov.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">发布和修改</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">OmegaT </emphasis>是自由软件，在遵守自由软件基金会（FSF）发布的 GNU 通用公共许可证的版本3或者更高版本的前提下，您可以对它进行修改或者重新发布。</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">保证</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold"> <application>OmegaT</application>
    </emphasis>is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
    ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for
    more detail.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>