<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.files.to.translate">
  <title>待译文件</title>

  <section id="file.formats">
    <title>文件格式<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>源文件</primary> <secondary>文件格式</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>目标文件</primary> <secondary>文件格式</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><application>You can use OmegaT</application> to translate files in
    a number of file formats. There are basically two types of file formats,
    plain text and formatted text.</para>

    <section>
      <title>纯文本文件<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>目标文件</primary> <secondary>纯文本文件</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>源文件</primary> <secondary>纯文本文件</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Plain text files contain text only, so their translation is as
      simple as typing the translation. There are several methods to specify
      the file's encoding so that its contents are not garbled when opened in
      <application>OmegaT</application>. Such files do not contain any
      formatting information beyond the &quot;white space&quot; used to align text,
      indicate paragraphs or insert page breaks. They are not able to contain
      or retain information regarding the color, font etc of the text.
      Currently, <application>OmegaT</application> supports the following
      plain text formats:<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>文件格式</primary> <secondary>无格式</secondary> <seealso>源文件</seealso>
        </indexterm></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>ASCII 文本（.txt 等）</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>编码文本（*.UTF8）</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Java 资源文件（*.properties）</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>PO 文件（*.po）</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>INI (key=value) 文件（*.ini）</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>DTD 文件（*.DTD）</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DokuWiki文件（*.txt）</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>SubRip 标题文件（*.srt）</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Magento CE Locale CSV文件（*.csv）</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><application>OmegaT</application> 可以处理的其它的纯文本文件可以通过将其文件扩展名关联到所支持的文件类型（比方说，.pod 文件可以关联到 ASCII 文本过滤器）并使用特定的分割 规则来进行预处理。</para>

      <para>PO files<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>源文件</primary> <secondary>PO双语文件</secondary>
        </indexterm> can contain both the source and the target text. Seen
      from this point of view, they are plain text files<emphasis>
      plus</emphasis> translation memories. If for a given source segment
      there is as yet no existing translation in the project translation
      memory (project_save.tmx), the current translation will be saved in the
      project_save.tmx as the default translation. In case, however, the same
      source segment already exists with a different translation, the new
      translation will be saved as an alternative.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>格式化文本文件<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>目标文件</primary> <secondary>格式化文本文件</secondary> <seealso>标记文本</seealso>
        </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>源文件</primary> <secondary>格式化文本文件</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Formatted text files contain information such as font type, size,
      color etc. as well as text. They are commonly created in word processors
      or HTML editors. Such file formats are designed to hold formatting
      information. The formatting information can be as simple as “this is
      bold”, or as complex as table data with different font sizes, colors,
      positions, etc. In most translation jobs, it is considered important for
      the formatting of the original text to be retained in the translation.
      OmegaT allows you to do this by marking the characters/words that have a
      special formatting with easy-to-handle tags. Simplifying the original
      text formatting greatly contributes to reducing the number of tags.
      Where possible, unifying the fonts, font sizes, colors, etc. used in the
      document simplifies the task of translation and reduces the possible
      number of tag errors. Each file type is handled differently in OmegaT.
      Specific behavior can be set up in the file filters. At the time of
      writing, OmegaT supports the following formatted text formats:
      <indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>文件格式</primary> <secondary>格式化</secondary> <seealso>源文件</seealso>
        </indexterm></para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>ODF - OASIS Open Document Format (*.ods, *.ots, *.odt,
            *.ott, *.odp, *.otp)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Microsoft Office Open XML (*.docx, *.dotx, *.xlsx, *.xltx,
            *.pptx)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>(X)HTML (*.html, *.xhtml,*.xht)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>HTML Help Compiler (*.hhc, *.hhk)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>DocBook (*.xml)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>XLIFF (*.xlf, *.xliff, *.sdlxliff)——一个源对应多个目标</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>QuarkXPress CopyFlowGold (*.tag, *.xtg)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>ResX 文件 (*.resx)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Android 资源 (*.xml)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>LaTex (*.tex, *.latex)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Help (*.xml) 和 Manual (*.hmxp) 文件</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Typo3 LocManager (*.xml)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>WiX Localization (*.wxl)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Iceni Infix (*.xml)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Flash XML export (*.xml)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Wordfast TXML (*.txml)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Camtasia for Windows (*.camproj)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Visio (*.vxd)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Java property XML (*.xml) </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Schematron (*.sch) </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>RELAX NG schema for XML (*.rng) </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>其它的格式化文本文件可以通过将其文件扩展名关联到所支持的文件类型（假设相应的分割规则可以正确分割它们）来让 OmegaT 进行处理。</para>
    </section>
    <section>
		<title>PDF文件<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>目标文件</primary> <secondary>s</secondary>PDF文件 
        </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>源文件</primary> <secondary>PDF文件</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>
  <para>PDF files are a special case. They contain text formatting
  information, but such information cannot be reused by
  <application>OmegaT</application> in order to create target files.
  Thus, PDF files are handled as plain text files, and output files are
  plain text files.</para>
  <para>如果您需要在翻译中复制文本格式（以及其他东西，如绘图），有三种方法可以尝试：</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>使用 <application>OmegaT的</application> 默认过滤器 （PDF输入），翻译， 创建目标文件（将会是纯文本文件，手动添加相关的格式和项目</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Use the Iceni Infix filter.
      See <ulink url="https://omegat.org/howtos/iceni_infix.html ">Howto - Translating PDF files with Iceni Infix and OmegaT</ulink>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>将源文件导入<ulink url="https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/draw/ ">LibreOffice Draw</ulink>，将其保存为ODG文件，并在需要时将其导出为PDF。</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> the above information
  applies only to PDF files with a text layer. If you have a PDF file
  made of scanned pages (sometimes such files are referred to as ‘dead’
  PDFs), you need to use an OCR (optical character recognition) program
  to recognize the text and convert it to a format that can be handled
  by OmegaT.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="other.file.formats">
    <title>其它文件格式<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>目标文件</primary> <secondary>其他文件格式</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>源文件</primary> <secondary>其他文件格式</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>还存在适合 OmegaT 处理的其他纯文本或格式化文本文件。</para>

    <para><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>目标文件</primary> <secondary>文件转换工具</secondary>
      </indexterm>External tools can be used to convert files to supported
    formats. The translated files will then need to be converted back to the
    original format. For example, if you have an outdated Microsoft Word
    version, that does not handle the ODT format, here's a round trip for Word
    files with the DOC extension:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>将文件导入到ODF writer</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>以 ODT 格式保存文件</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>对它进行翻译并创建目标 ODT 文件</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>在ODF writer中加载目标文件</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>保存该文件为 DOC 格式</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The quality of formatting of the translated file will depend on the
    quality of the round-trip conversion. Before proceeding with such
    conversions, be sure to test all options. Check the <ulink url="http://www.omegat.org">OmegaT home page</ulink> for an up-to-date
    listing of auxiliary translation tools.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="right.to.left.languages">
    <title>自右向左语言<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>自右向左语言</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>目标文件</primary> <secondary>自右向左语言</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>源文件</primary> <secondary>自右向左语言</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Justification of source and target segments depends upon the project
    languages. By default, left justification is used for Left-To-Right (LTR)
    languages and right justification for Right-To-Left (RTL) languages. You
    can toggle between different display modes by pressing <keycombo>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>

        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>O</keycap>
      </keycombo> (this is the letter O and not the numeral 0). The <keycombo>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>

        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>O</keycap>
      </keycombo> toggle has three states:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>缺省对齐方式，这由语言决定的</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>左对齐</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>右对齐</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Using the RTL mode in <application>OmegaT</application> has no
    influence whatsoever on the display mode of the translated documents
    created in <application>OmegaT</application>. The display mode of the
    translated documents must be modified within the application (such as
    Microsoft Word) commonly used to display or modify them (check the
    relevant manuals for details). Using <keycombo>
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>

        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>O</keycap>
      </keycombo> causes both text input and display in
    <application>OmegaT</application> to change. It can be used separately for
    all three panes (Editor, Fuzzy Matches and Glossary) by clicking on the
    pane and toggling the display mode. It can also be used in all the input
    fields found in <application>OmegaT</application> - in the search window,
    for segmentation rules etc.</para>

    <para>对于 Mac OS X 用户，请注意：使用 <keycombo> <keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>O</keycap> </keycombo> 快捷键而 <emphasis role="bold">不是</emphasis>cmd+Ctrl+O.</para>

    <section>
      <title>在片段中混合自右向左和自左向右字符串<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>自右向左语言</primary> <secondary>混合 RTL 和 LTR 字符串</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>目标文件</primary> <secondary>混合 RTL 和 LTR 字符串</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>源文件</primary> <secondary>混合 RTL 和 LTR 字符串</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>When writing purely RTL text, the default (LTR) view may be used.
      In many cases, however, it is necessary to embed LTR text in RTL text.
      For example, in OmegaT tags, product names that must be left in the LTR
      source language, place holders in localization files, and numbers in
      text. In cases like these it becomes necessary to switch to RTL mode, so
      that the RTL (in fact bidirectional) text is displayed correctly. It
      should be noted that when <application>OmegaT</application> is in RTL
      mode, both source and target are displayed in RTL mode. This means that
      if the source language is LTR and the target language is RTL, or vice
      versa, it may be necessary to toggle back and forth between RTL and LTR
      modes to view the source and enter the target easily in their respective
      modes.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>自右向左片段中的 <application>OmegaT</application> 标签<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>自右向左语言</primary> <secondary>自右向左语言中的 OmegaT 标签</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>As stated above, OmegaT tags are LTR strings. When translating
      between RTL and LTR languages, correctly reading the tags from the
      source and entering them properly in the target may require the
      translator to toggle between LTR and RTL modes numerous times.</para>

      <para>If the document allows, the translator is strongly encouraged to
      remove style information from the original document so that as few tags
      as possible appear in the OmegaT interface. Follow the indications given
      in Hints for tags management. Frequently validate tags (see Tag
      validation) and produce translated documents (see below and Menu) at
      regular intervals to make it easier to catch any problems that arise. A
      hint: translating a plain text version of the text and adding the
      necessary style in the relevant application at a later stage may turn
      out to be less hassle.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>创建已译自右向左文档<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>自右向左语言</primary> <secondary>创建 RTL 目标文件</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>自右向左语言</primary> <secondary>目标文件</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>自右向左语言</primary> <secondary>创建 RTL 目标文本</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>When the translated document is created, its display direction
      will be the same as that of the original document. If the original
      document was LTR, the display direction of the target document must be
      changed manually to RTL in its viewing application. Each output format
      has specific ways of dealing with RTL display; check the relevant
      application manuals for details.</para>

      <para>无论如何对于.docx文件会自动进行一些更改：<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>段落、节和表被设为双向</listitem>

          <listitem>阅读方向（文本元素）被设为RTL</listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>To avoid changing the target files display parameters each time
      the files are opened, it may be possible to change the source file
      display parameters such that such parameters are inherited by the target
      files. Such modifications are possible in ODF files for example.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>