<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.glossaries">
  <title>术语表<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>OmegaT 窗口和窗格</primary> <secondary>术语表窗格</secondary>
    </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>术语表</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>术语表是用于 <application>OmegaT</application> 的文件，它由用户手工创建和更新。</para>

  <para>如果某个 <application>OmegaT</application> 项目包含一个或多个术语表文件，当前片段中出现的任何术语将自动显示在术语表查看器中。</para>

  <para>You define its location and name in the project properties dialog. The
  extension must be <filename>.txt</filename> or <filename>.utf8</filename>
  (if not, it will be added). The location of the file must be within the
  <filename>/glossary</filename> folder, but it can be in a deeper folder
  (e.g., <filename>glossary/sub/glossary.txt</filename>). The file does not
  need to exist when setting it, it will be created (if necessary) when adding
  a glossary entry. If the file already exists, no attempt is done to verify
  the format or the character set of the file: the new entries will always be
  in tab-separated format and UTF-8. As the existing content will not be
  touched, damage to an existing file would be limited.</para>

  <section>
    <title>用法</title>

    <para>To use an existing glossary, simply place it in the<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>项目文件</primary> <secondary>术语表子目录</secondary>
      </indexterm> <filename>/glossary</filename> folder after creating the
    project. <application>OmegaT</application> automatically detects glossary
    files in this folder when a project is opened. Terms in the current
    segment which <application>OmegaT</application> finds in the glossary
    file(s) are displayed in the Glossary pane:</para>

    <indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>术语表，术语表窗格</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>术语表窗格</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/GlossaryPane_25.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/GlossaryPane_25.png" width="60%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The word before the = sign is the source term, and its translation
    is (or are) the words after =. The vocabulary entry can have a comment
    added. The glossary function only finds exact matches with the glossary
    entry (e.g. does not find inflected forms etc.). New terms can be added
    manually to the glossary file(s) during translation, for example in a text
    editor. Newly added terms will not be recognized once the changes in the
    text file have been saved.</para>

    <para>源术语可以不是一个单词，例如：</para>

    <figure>
      <title>术语表中的多单词条目——示例<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>术语表窗格</secondary> <tertiary>多单词条目</tertiary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/MultiTerm_Glossary_25.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/MultiTerm_Glossary_25.png" width="80%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The underlined item &quot;pop-up menu&quot; can be found in the glossary pane
    as &quot;pojavni menu&quot;. Highlighting it in the Glossary pane and then
    rightclicking insets at the cursor position in the target
    segment.<footnote>
        <para>Note that in the above case, this is just half (or even less) of
        the story, as the target language (Slovenian) uses declension. So the
        inserted &quot;pojavni meni&quot; in the nominative form - has to be changed to
        &quot;pojavnem meniju&quot; , i.e. to the locative. So it is probably faster to
        type the term correctly right away without bothering with the glossary
        and its shortcuts.</para>
      </footnote></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>文件格式</secondary>
      </indexterm>文件格式<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>项目文件</primary> <secondary>用户文件</secondary> <seealso>术语表</seealso>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Glossary files are simple plain text files containing three-column,
    tab-delimited lists with the source and target terms in the first and
    second columns respectively. The third column can be used for additional
    information. You can have entries with the target column missing, i.e.
    just containing the source term and the comment.</para>

    <para>The encoding of glossaries is determined automatically. Of course,
    the encoding must be compatible with both the languages contained, so
    Unicode is recommended.</para>

    <para>Also supported is the CSV format. This format is the same as the tab
    separated one: source term, target term. Comment fields are separated by a
    comma ','. Strings can be enclosed by quotes &quot;, which allows having a
    comma inside a string:</para>

    <para><literal>&quot;This is a source term, which contains a comma&quot;,&quot;c'est un
    terme, qui contient une virgule&quot;</literal></para>

    <para>In addition to the plain text format, TBX format <indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>TBX 格式</secondary>
      </indexterm> is also supported as a read-only glossary format. The
    location of the <filename>.tbx</filename> file must be within the
    <filename>/glossary</filename> folder, but it can be in a deeper folder
    (e.g., <filename>glossary/sub/MyGlossary.tbx</filename>).</para>

    <para>TBX - Term Base eXchange - is the open, XML-based standard for
    exchanging structured terminological data, TBX has been approved as an
    international standard by LISA and ISO. If you have an existing
    terminology handling system it is quite possible it offers the export of
    terminology data via TBX format. <ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/Language/en-US/Terminology.aspx">Microsoft
    Terminology Collection</ulink> <indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>微软术语集</secondary>
      </indexterm> can be downloaded in nearly 100 languages and can serve as
    a cornerstone IT glossary.</para>

    <para>注意：<filename>MultiTerm导出的.tbx格式</filename>文件似乎不太可靠（2013年11月），建议使用MultiTerm的<filename>.tab</filename>文件。</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>如何创建术语表<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>创建术语表</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>The project setting allows one to enter a name for a writable
    glossary file (see beginning of this chapter). Right-click in the glossary
    pane or press <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+G</keycap> to add a new entry. A dialog
    opens, allowing you to enter the source term, target term and any comments
    you may have:</para>

    <mediaobject role="html">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/GlossaryEntry_25.png"/>
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="images/GlossaryEntry_25.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The contents of glossary files are kept in memory and are loaded
    when the project is opened or reloaded. Updating a glossary file is thus
    rather simple: press <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+G</keycap> and enter the new term,
    its translation and any comments you may have (ensuring you press tab
    between the fields) and save the file. The contents of the glossary pane
    will be updated accordingly.</para>

    <para><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>可写术语表的位置</secondary>
      </indexterm>The location of the writable glossary file can be set in the
    <guimenuitem>Project &gt; Properties ... </guimenuitem>dialog. The
    recognized extensions are <filename>TXT</filename> and
    <filename>UTF8</filename></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note: </emphasis>Of course there are other
    ways and means to create a simple file with tab delimited entries. Nothing
    speaks against using Notepad++ on Windows, GEdit on Linux for instance or
    some spreadsheet program for this purpose: any application, that can
    handle UTF-8 (or UTF-16 LE) and that can show white space (so that you do
    not miss the required <keycap>TAB</keycap> characters) can be used.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>优先级</secondary>
      </indexterm>优先术语</title>

    <para>优先术语表 (默认的glossary/glossary.txt) 结果会在术语窗口和翻译建议中中优先出现。</para>

    <para>优先术语表和非优先术语表中的术语可能混合，优先术语表中的词汇以粗体展现。</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>Trados MultiTerm</secondary>
      </indexterm>使用Trados MultiTerm</title>

    <para>Data exported from Trados MultiTerm can be used as
    <application>OmegaT</application> glossaries without further modification,
    provided they are given the file extension <filename>.tab</filename> and
    the source and target term fields are the first two fields respectively.
    If you export using the system option &quot;Tab-delimited export&quot;, you will
    need to delete the first 5 columns (Seq. Nr, Date created etc).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>术语表</primary> <secondary>术语表相关问题</secondary>
      </indexterm>常见术语表问题</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">问题：未显示术语表术语——可能的解决方法：</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>&quot;glossary&quot; 目录中没有找到术语表文件。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>术语表文件为空。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>词条的各项间未使用 TAB 字符分隔。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>术语表文件没有正确的拓展名 (.tab, .utf8 or .txt)。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>术语表词条和文档中的原文未完全匹配－－例如该词条是复数形式。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>术语表文件没有采用正确的编码。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>当前片段中没有任何术语与术语表中的术语相匹配。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>上述一个或多个问题已经被修正，但项目还没有被重新载入。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">问题：在术语表窗格中某些字符显示不正确。</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>...但在编辑窗格中能正确显示这些字符：扩展名与文件编码方式不匹配。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>