<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.machine.translate">
  <title>机器翻译<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>机器翻译</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section>
    <title>引言<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>机器翻译</primary> <secondary>介绍</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>As opposed to user-generated translation memories (as in the case of
    <application>OmegaT</application>) Machine translation (MT) tools use
    rule-based linguistic tools to create a translation of the source segment
    without the need for a translation memory. Statistical learning
    techniques, based on source and target texts, are used to build a
    translation model. Machine translation services have been achieving good
    and steadfastly improving results in research evaluations.</para>

    <para>To activate any of the Machine Translation services, go to
    <guimenuitem>Options &gt; Machine Translate ...</guimenuitem> and activate
    the service desired. Note that they are all web-based: you will have to be
    on-line if you want to use them.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="introduction">
    <title>谷歌翻译<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>机器翻译</primary> <secondary>谷歌翻译</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Google Translate is a payable service offered by Google, for
    translating sentences, web sites and complete texts between an
    ever-growing number of languages. At the time of writing the list includes
    more than 50 languages, from Albanian to Yiddish, including of course all
    the major languages. The current version of the service is based on usage,
    with the price of 20 USD per million characters at the time of writing.
    <emphasis role="bold"/></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Important: </emphasis>Google Translate API v2
    requires billing information for all accounts before you can start using
    the service (see <ulink url="https://developers.google.com/translate/v2/pricing?hl=en-US">Pricing
    and Terms of Service</ulink> for more). To identify yourself as a valid
    user for the Google services, you use your private unique key sent to you
    by Google, when you have registered for the service. See chapter <link linkend="chapter.installing.and.running">Installing and Running</link>,
    section Launch command arguments, for details on how to add this key to
    the OmegaT environment.</para>

    <para>The quality of the Google Translate translation depends on one side
    on the reservoir of target-language texts and the availability of their
    bilingual versions, on the other hand on the quality of the models built.
    It is pretty much certain that while the quality may be insufficient in
    some cases, it will definitely get better with time and not worse.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><application>OmegaT</application> 用户和谷歌翻译</title>

    <para>The <application>OmegaT</application> user is not forced to use
    Google Translate. If used, neither the user's decision to accept the
    translation nor the final translation are made available to Google. The
    following window shows an example of a) the English source b) Spanish and
    c) Slovenian Google Translate translation.</para>

    <figure id="moby.dick">
      <title>谷歌翻译 - 示例</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="images/MobyDick.png"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="images/MobyDick.png" width="60%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Spanish translation is better than the Slovenian. Note
    <emphasis>interesar</emphasis> and<emphasis> navegar</emphasis> in
    Spanish, are correctly translated as the verbs interest and sail
    respectively. In the Slovenian version both words have been translated as
    nouns. It is actually quite probable that the Spanish translation is based
    at least partially on the actual translation of the book.</para>

    <para>Once you have activated the service, a suggestion for the
    translation will appear in the Machine Translate pane every time a new
    source segment is opened. If you find the suggestion acceptable, press
    <keycombo>
        <keycap><indexterm class="singular">
            <primary>快捷键</primary> <secondary>机器翻译——Ctrl+M</secondary>
          </indexterm>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>M</keycap>
      </keycombo> to replace the target part of the opened segment with the
    suggestion. In the above segment, for instance, <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>M</keycap>
      </keycombo> would replace the Spanish version with the Slovenian
    suggestion.</para>

    <para>如果不希望 <application>OmegaT</application> 把源片段发送至谷歌获取译文，请取消选项菜单中的谷歌翻译菜单项。</para>

    <para>Note that nothing but your source segment is sent to the MT service.
    The online version of Google Translate allows the user to correct the
    suggestion and send the corrected segment in. This feature, however, is
    not implemented in OmegaT.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Belazar<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>机器翻译</primary> <secondary>Belazar</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><ulink url="http://belazar.info/">Belazar</ulink> 是用于俄罗斯－白俄罗斯语言对的机器语言翻译工具。</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Apertium<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>机器翻译</primary> <secondary>Apertium</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para><ulink url="http://www.apertium.org/">Apertium</ulink> is a
    free/open-source machine translation platform, initially aimed at
    related-language pairs, like CA, ES, GA, PT, OC and FR but recently
    expanded to deal with more divergent language pairs (such as
    English-Catalan). Check the web site for the latest list of implemented
    language pairs.</para>

    <para>该平台提供</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>语言独立的机器翻译引擎</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>工具用来管理必要语言学数据，确保可以根据已有语言对建立机器翻译系统</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>用于不断增长的语言对数目的语言学数据</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Apertium 使用浅层传播机器翻译引擎（shallow-transfer machine translation engine ）来处理输入的文本，就像汇编行：去除格式，形态分析，语音消歧，浅层结构传播，词汇传播，形态生成以及重新格式化。</para>

    <para>使用 Apertium 为各种语言对构建机器翻译系统是可行的，在底端，Apertium 使用基于 XML 的简单标准格式对需要的语言学数据（通过手工或转换现有数据）进行编码，并使用提供的工具被编译为引擎可用的高级格式。</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>MyMemory（机器）<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>机器翻译</primary> <secondary>MyMemory</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>By default, MyMemory allows a maximum of 100 requests per day. By
    specifying an email address, it is possible to use 1000 requests per day
    instead of 100 ones.</para>

    <para>邮箱认证方式至少有以下三种</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>在OmegaT.l4J.ini文件（只限Windows操作系统）中将：</para>

          <para># MyMemory email</para>

          <para>改为:</para>

          <para>MyMemory 你的邮箱名@邮箱地址.com</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>通过命令行打开OmegaT，输入命令：</para>

          <para>-Dmymemory.api.email=你的邮箱名@邮箱地址.com</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>在Kaptain启动器中（仅限Linux操作系统）, 将邮箱地址输入到“Online Services” 标签的对应域中。</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>MyMemory provides also <emphasis role="bold">Human
    translations</emphasis> originating from professional translators, LSPs,
    customers and multilingual web content. To get these translations, you
    must upload your source file <ulink url="http://mymemory.translated.net/">on their site</ulink> that generates
    a TMX file. Then you must put this TMX file in the /tm/ or /tm/auto/
    folder of your OmegaT project.</para>

    <para>MyMemory offers also the possibility to manage <emphasis role="bold">private TMs</emphasis>. Note: OmegaT does not interact
    dynamically with them (you must export/import TMX files manually).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Microsoft Translator<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>机器翻译</primary> <secondary>微软翻译</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>通过以下步骤获得微软翻译许可证：</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>登陆微软Azure Marketplace： <ulink url="http://datamarket.azure.com/">http://datamarket.azure.com/</ulink></para>

        <para>如果您还没有Azure Marketplace账户，您首先需要注册一个账户。</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>点击页面上方“我的账户”选项</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>在接近底部的位置您会看到以下条目及其对应值：<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>主账户API Key（对应<code>microsoft.api.client_secret</code> 命令行参数）</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>客户ID（对应<code>microsoft.api.client_id</code>命令行参数）</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>许可OmegaT中的微软翻译需编辑其启动器或了解如何通过命令行启动OmegaT，见 <link linkend="chapter.installing.and.running">安装和运行</link>。</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Yandex Translate<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>机器翻译</primary> <secondary>Yandex Translate</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>若需使用OmegaT中的Yandex Translate，您需 <ulink url="http://api.yandex.com/key/form.xml?service=trnsl ">从Yandex获得API Key</ulink>。</para>

    <para>The obtained API key needs to be passed to OmegaT at startup through
    <code>yandex.api.key</code> command-line parameter. To do that edit OmegaT
    launcher or see chapter <link linkend="chapter.installing.and.running">Installing and Running</link> to
    learn how to start OmegaT from the command line.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Google.Translate.troubleshooting">
    <title>机器翻译 - 故障排除<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>机器翻译</primary> <secondary>故障排除</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>如果在机器翻译窗格中没有出现任何东西，检查下列内容：</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Are you online? You need to be online to be able to use an MT
        tool.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What is the language pair you need? Check if the selected
        service offers it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Google Translate does not work: have you applied <ulink url="https://developers.google.com/translate/v2/faq">Translate API
        service</ulink>? Note that Google Translate service is not free of
        charge, see chapter <link linkend="chapter.installing.and.running">Installing and Running</link>
        (runtime parameters) for more on that.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>&quot;Google Translate returned HTTP response code: 403 ...&quot;: check
        that the 38-characters key, entered in the pinfo.list file, is
        correct. Check that <ulink url="https://developers.google.com/translate/v2/faq">Translate API
        service </ulink>has been activated.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Google Translate does not work: - with the Google API key
        entered as requested. Check in Options &gt; Machine Translate, that
        Google Translate V2 is checked.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Google Translate V2 reports &quot;Bad request&quot; - check the source and
        target languages for your project. Having no languages defined elicits
        this kind or a response.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>