<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../../docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter.searches">
  <title>搜索<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>搜索</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <section id="search.window">
    <title>搜索窗口<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>快捷键</primary> <secondary>搜索——Ctrl+F</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Open the Search window with <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>F</keycap>
      </keycombo> and enter the word or phrase you wish to search for in the
    <emphasis>Search for</emphasis> box.</para>

    <para>Alternatively, you can select a word or phrase in the Editor pane,
    Fuzzy matches pane or Glossary pane and hit <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>F</keycap>
      </keycombo>. The word or phrase is entered in the <emphasis>Search
    for</emphasis> box automatically. You can have several Search windows open
    at the same time, but close them when they are no longer needed so that
    they do not clutter your desktop.</para>

    <para>Click the dropdown arrow of the <emphasis>Search for</emphasis> box
    to access the last 10 searches.</para>

    <para>The Search window has its own menus:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>File &gt; Search for selection (<keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>F</keycap>
          </keycombo>): refocus on the search field and select all its
        contents.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>File &gt; Close (<keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>W</keycap>
          </keycombo>): close the search window (in the same way as
        <keycap>Esc</keycap>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Edit &gt; Insert source (<keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>Shift</keycap>

            <keycap>I</keycap>
          </keycombo>): insert current segment source.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Edit &gt; Replace with source (<keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>Shift</keycap>

            <keycap>R</keycap>
          </keycombo>): replace with current segment source.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Edit &gt; Create Glossary Entry (<keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

            <keycap>Shift</keycap>

            <keycap>G</keycap>
          </keycombo>): add a new glossary item.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="using.wild.cards">
    <title>使用通配符<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>搜索</primary> <secondary>使用通配符</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>In both exact and keyword searches, the wild card search characters
    '*' and '?' can be used. They have the meaning, familiar to Word
    users:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'*' matches zero or more characters, from the current position
        in a given word to its end. The search term <literal>'run*'</literal>
        for example would match words <literal>'run'</literal>,
        <literal>'runs'</literal> and <literal>'running'</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'?' matches any single character. For instance,
        <literal>'run?'</literal> would match the word
        <literal>'runs'</literal> and <literal>'runn'</literal> in the word
        <literal>'running'</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The matches will be displayed in bold blue. Note that '*' and '?'
    have special meaning in regular expressions, so wild card search, as
    described here, applies to exact and keyword search only (see
    below).</para>
  </section>

  <section id="search.methoids">
    <title>搜索方式和选项<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>搜索</primary> <secondary>方式和选项</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Select the method using the radio buttons. The following search
    methods are available:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>精确搜索</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for segments containing the exact string you specified.
          An exact search looks for a phrase, i.e. if several words are
          entered, they are found only if they occur in exactly that sequence.
          Searching for <literal>open file</literal> will thus find all
          occurrences of the string <emphasis><literal>open
          file</literal></emphasis>, but not <emphasis><literal>file
          opened</literal></emphasis> or <emphasis><literal>open input
          file</literal></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>关键字搜索</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for segments containing all keywords you specified, in
          any order. Select keyword search to search for any number of
          individual full words, in any order. OmegaT displays a list of all
          segments containing all of the words specified. Keyword searches are
          similar to a search &quot;with all of the words&quot; in an Internet search
          engine such as Google (AND logic). Using keyword search with
          <emphasis><literal>open file</literal></emphasis> will thus find all
          occurrences of the string <emphasis><literal>open
          file</literal>,</emphasis> as well as <emphasis><literal>file
          opened</literal>, <literal>open input file</literal>, <literal>file
          may not be safe to open</literal></emphasis>, etc.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">正则表达式</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The search string will be treated as a regular expression. The
          search string - [a-zA-Z]+[öäüqwß] - in the example above for
          instance looks for words in the target segment, containing
          questionable characters from German keyboard. Regular expressions
          are a powerful way to look for instances of a string. See more in
          the chapter<link linkend="chapter.regexp"> Regular
          Expressions.</link></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>对上面的几种方式，您还可以选择下列选项：</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">区分大小写</emphasis>：搜索工作将会严格匹配指定字符串，即遵循大小写状态。</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Space matches nbsp</emphasis>: when this
        option is checked, a space character put in search entry can match
        either a normal space character or a non-breacking space (\u00A)
        character.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">源片段：</emphasis>在源片段中搜索</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">目标片段：</emphasis>在目标片段中搜索</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">笔记：</emphasis>在笔记中搜索</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">in comments: </emphasis>search in comments
        to segments</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Translated or untranslated:
        </emphasis>search in both translated and untranslated segments.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Translated: </emphasis>search only in
        translated segments.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Untranslated: </emphasis>search only in
        untranslated segments.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Display: all matching segments:
        </emphasis>if checked, all the segments are displayed one by one, even
        if they are present several times in the same document or in different
        documents.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Display: file names: </emphasis>if
        checked, the name of the file where each segment is found is displayed
        above each result.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Search in Project</emphasis>: check
        <emphasis>Memory</emphasis> to include the project memory
        (project_save.tmx file) in the search. Check <emphasis>TMs</emphasis>
        to include the translation memories located in the
        <filename>tm</filename> folder in the search. Check
        <emphasis>Glossaries</emphasis> to include the glossaries located in
        the <filename>glossary</filename> folder in the search.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Search in Files: </emphasis>search in a
        single file or a folder containing a set of files. When searching
        through files (as opposed to translation memories), OmegaT restricts
        the search to files in source file formats. Consequently, although
        OmegaT is quite able to handle<filename> tmx</filename> files, it does
        not include them in the Search files search.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If you click on the button <guibutton>Advanced options</guibutton>
    additional criteria (author or changer of the translation, date
    translated, excluding orphan segments, etc) can be selected. When
    <emphasis>Full/Half width char insensitive</emphasis> option is checked,
    searches for fullwidth forms (CJK characters) will match halfwidth forms
    and vice versa.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="search.result.display">
    <title>搜索结果展示</title>

    <para>Pressing the search button after entering a string in the search
    field displays all the segments in the project that include the entered
    string. As <application>OmegaT</application> handles identical segments as
    one single entity, only the first unique segment is shown. The segments
    are displayed in order of appearance in the project. Translated segments
    are displayed with the original text at the top and the translated text at
    the bottom, untranslated segments are displayed as the source only.</para>

    <para>Double-clicking on a segment opens it in the Editor for
    modifications (one single click does it when <emphasis role="bold">Auto-sync with Editor</emphasis> option is checked). You can
    then switch back to the Search window for the next segment found, for
    instance to check and, if necessary, correct the terminology.</para>

    <para>In the Search window, you can use standard shortcuts (<keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>N</keycap>
      </keycombo>, <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>P</keycap>
      </keycombo>) to move from one segment to another.</para>

    <para>You may have several Search windows open at the same time. You can
    quickly see their contents by looking at their title: it will contain the
    search term used.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="search.filter">
    <title>Filter entries in editor according to search</title>

    <para>For easier navigation in the search result set, you can apply the
    search to the editor. Press the <emphasis role="bold">Filter</emphasis>
    button on the bottom to limit the shown entries in the editor window to
    those that match the current search. You can use normal navigation to go
    to e.g. the next (untranslated) segment that matches the search
    criteria.</para>

    <para>NB:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         A search may be limited to 1000 items, so if you search on a common phrase, the editor then shows only those 1000 matching entries, and not all entries that match the search criteria. 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         A file might have no matching entries, so it will show empty. 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         If a search removes duplicates, those duplicates will not be in the Editor. 
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To remove a filter, press the <emphasis role="bold">Remove
    filter</emphasis> button, or reload a project.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>